<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Majority of homes in most areas have an EPC rating below C</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/energyefficiencyofhousinginenglandandwales2023</link>
         <description>Majority of homes in most areas have an EPC rating below C 1 November 2023 In the majority of council areas across England and Wales, at least half of homes have energy efficiency ratings of D or below. Energy Performance Certificates (EPCs) indicate the energy efficiency of homes, with ratings from band A (most efficient) to band G (least efficient). The UK government has said it wants as many homes as possible to reach band C by 2035. More energy efficient homes tend to require less energy to heat, which in turn reduces energy costs as well as carbon dioxide emissions. Of all local authority districts, 26% had more than half of their dwellings at band C or above as of March 2023. Of those, just over half (52%) were in London or the South East. The median energy efficiency rating for all homes, both in England and in Wales, was band D. The median is the middle value of all the energy efficiency ratings. Older properties tend to be less energy efficient. Of all homes built before 1930 in both England and Wales, more than 80% were rated in bands D to G. Newer homes are more likely to have higher EPC ratings Individual Energy Performance Certificate (EPC) bands by age of property band, England and Wales, up to March 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Read our Energy efficiency of housing in England and Wales: 2023 article 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">46914889</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Employee earnings fell 1.5% after inflation in April 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/earningsandworkinghours/bulletins/annualsurveyofhoursandearnings/2023</link>
         <description>Employee earnings fell 1.5% after inflation in April 2023 1 November 2023 Median (middle) earnings for full-time employees was £682 in April 2023, which is a 6.2% increase over the £642 in April 2022; this is the highest growth since comparable records began in 1997. This represented a growth across all major occupational groups, particularly for lower-paying occupations (with caring, leisure and other service occupations up 9.4% and sales and customer service occupations up 9.2% compared with the previous year). However, overall, median earnings fell 1.5% on the year in real terms (adjusted for inflation using Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers' housing costs (CPIH)). Read our full bulletin on Employee earnings in the UK: 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">43601471</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around a third of adults unaware of important energy support schemes </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/housing/articles/changesinprivaterentalsectorbehaviourengland/february2022toseptember2023</link>
         <description>Around a third of adults unaware of important energy support schemes 3 November 2023 Around a third of adults in Great Britain have not heard of important government schemes that could help with their energy bills this winter. That is according to those surveyed between 18 and 29 October 2023 for our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin. Of those asked, 36% had not heard of any of the government schemes they were asked about, such as the Energy Price Guarantee or the Warm Home Discount. The survey also revealed that about 4 in 10 adults (39%) who pay energy bills said it was very or somewhat difficult to afford them. This was compared with 42% during a similar period one year ago (12 to 23 October 2022). Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top One in five rentals had seen a 10% price rise in September 2023 3 November 2023 New experimental analysis has found that prices had risen by 10% or more for around one in five privately rented properties revisited in September 2023. Prices had risen by 10% or more for 21% of privately rented properties in England and 17% in Wales. The analysis tracks the price changes of individual privately rented properties over time. On average, properties are revisited (and prices recorded) every 12 months in England, and every nine months in Wales. Of properties in England revisited between July and September 2023, prices had risen since the last visit for around 6 in 10 properties. In Wales, prices had risen for around 4 in 10 properties. In both countries, this is a higher proportion than last year (July to September 2022). While rental prices were more likely to have increased recently in England than in Wales, when a property’s price did increase, the average increase was higher in Wales (11.3%) than in England (9.7%). In all English regions, properties revisited between July and September 2023 were more likely to have seen price rises of 10% or more, compared with properties revisited between July and September 2022. In London, almost a quarter of privately rented homes revisited in July to September 2023 had seen price rises of 10% or more since the last visit. Read the full bulletin on Changes in private rental sector behaviour, England and Wales: February 2022 to September 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">45318433</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK real GDP showed no growth in the third quarter of 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/balanceofpayments/articles/impactoftradeingoodsdatacollectionchangesonuktradestatistics/previousReleases</link>
         <description>UK real GDP showed no growth in the third quarter of 2023 10 November 2023 The first quarterly estimate for Quarter 3 (July to Sept) 2023 shows the UK economy was broadly unchanged following modest growth of 0.2% in the previous quarter. Real gross domestic product (GDP) is a measure of the value of all goods and services produced in the UK after adjusting for price changes over time. GDP growth continued to slow in the most recent quarter UK, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2022 to Quarter 3 (July to Sept) 2023 Source: GDP first quarterly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart GDP growth continued to slow in the most recent quarter Image .csv .xls Following no growth in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023, service sector output decreased by 0.1% in Quarter 3 2023 driven by falls of 0.4% and 1.2% in real estate activities, and transportation and storage, respectively. There was no growth in production output in Quarter 3 2023, despite a 0.1% increase in manufacturing. Elsewhere, construction output rose by 0.1%. Growth in the volume of net trade (defined by the difference in exported and imported goods and services) was offset by falls in business investment (down 4.2%), household spending (down 0.4%) and government consumption (down 5.0%) in the most recent quarter. Business investment fell by 4.2% in the latest quarter following growth of 4.1% in Quarter 2 2023 because of increases in transport investment, especially in aircraft imports from the United States in April 2023. Households reduced their spending in the three months to September 2023, in particular their spending on “miscellaneous” goods and services (such as jewellery, clocks and watches), air and water transport, and food and non- alcoholic drink. Government consumption fell on the quarter, mainly reflecting lower spending on health and education. Read our latest bulletin on UK quarterly GDP. 🠕 Back to the top Total imports of goods decreased substantially in September 10 November 2023 Total imports of goods in &quot;current prices&quot;, which are not adjusted for inflation, decreased by £2.9 billion (6.2%) in September 2023. Imports from non-EU countries fell by £1.5 billion, while imports from the-EU fell by £1.4 billion. Total exports of goods decreased by £0.9 billion (2.9%) in September 2023, because of a £0.5 billion fall in exports to the EU and a £0.4 billion fall to non-EU countries. After removing the effect of inflation, total goods imports decreased by £2.3 billion (5.7%) in September 2023. This was because imports from the EU fell by £0.9 billion (4.2%) and imports from non-EU countries fell by £1.3 billion (7.7%). Total goods exports fell by £0.6 billion (2.1%) in September 2023, after the effect of inflation is removed. Exports to the EU decreased by £0.4 billion (3.4%) and exports to non-EU countries fell by £0.1 billion (0.9%). The total trade in goods and services deficit narrowed by £7.1 billion to £6.0 billion in Quarter 3 (July to Sept) 2023 , the result of a substantial fall in imports; the total trade deficit has declined steadily since Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2022 when it stood at £26.9 billion. Imports fell substantially in September 2023, with exports falling by a lesser amount EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted, January 2020 to September 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">32685728</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Alternative measures to GDP to measure economic welfare </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/grossdomesticproductandwelfare</link>
         <description>Alternative measures to GDP to measure economic welfare 13 November 2023 While gross domestic product (GDP) is typically viewed as a way of measuring production and productivity, its limitations as a measure of welfare or wellbeing are widely known. There are two alternative measures of economic activity which are based on GDP but give more significance to welfare. These measures provide additional insights into the changing UK economy that are not fully captured in GDP. The first, real gross domestic income (GDI), is a measure of the purchasing power of GDP, reflecting how movements in the terms of trade can impact a nation’s ability to consume in world markets. Despite a deterioration in the UK’s terms of trade in the last two years following a strong rise in global energy and commodity prices, over the longer term the UK has benefitted from an improvement in its terms of trade. The second, real income, is a measure that is linked to the level of sustainable consumption, namely the income generated by a country that can be used to fund current and future consumption opportunities. This measure has often diverged from real GDP, suggesting the growth in UK welfare is not always in line with the volume of output or production. Real GDI has generally grown faster than real GDP, but real income has grown relatively slower Real gross domestic product (GDP), real gross domestic income (GDI) and real income (1987 = 100), UK, 1987 to 2022 Source: UK National Accounts, The Blue Book 2023 from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Real GDI has generally grown faster than real GDP, but real income has grown relatively slower Image .csv .xls Read our full Gross Domestic Product and Welfare article 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">68035002</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Real terms pay continues to rise as vacancies keep falling</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/uklabourmarket/latest</link>
         <description>Real terms pay continues to rise as vacancies keep falling 14 November 2023 Annual pay growth in real terms (adjusted for inflation) across Great Britain rose on the year by 1.4% for total pay (including bonuses) and 1.3% for regular pay (excluding bonuses), respectively, according to the latest data from the UK Labour Market Survey. By contrast, annual growth for regular pay (not adjusted for inflation) was 7.7% in July to September 2023. Though slightly lower than previous periods, this remains one of the highest annual growth rates since comparable records began in 2001. Estimated UK job vacancies fell in August to October 2023 for the 16th consecutive period, dropping by 58,000 vacancies to 957,000 on the quarter. This represents a decrease of 5.7% since May to July 2023 across 16 of the 18 industry sectors. Read more in our latest UK labour market bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">12162631</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House prices appear to fall while private rents see record rises </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukoctober2023</link>
         <description>House prices appear to fall while private rents see record rises 15 November 2023 Average UK house prices are estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in the 12 months to September 2023 (provisional estimate). This is down from an increase of 0.8% in the 12 months to August 2023 (revised estimate). The average UK house price was £291,000 in September 2023 (provisional), which is little changed from a year earlier, but above the recent low in March 2023. Average UK house prices were little changed in the 12 months to September 2023 (provisional estimate) Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to September 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices were little changed in the 12 months to September 2023 (provisional estimate) Image .csv .xls Average house prices are estimated to have fallen in England and Wales in the year to September 2023 (by 0.5% and 2.7%, respectively), while in Scotland house prices rose by 2.5% over the same period. In Northern Ireland, average house prices rose by 2.1% in the year to quarter 3 (July to September) 2023. It’s important to note that our provisional house price estimates are based on smaller data volumes than usual, meaning that future revisions to these figures may be larger than usual. For more information please see our full UK House Price Index bulletin . Private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 6.1% in the year to October 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 6.0% in England, 6.9% in Wales and 6.2% in Scotland in the year to October 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since records began (January 2006 for England, January 2010 for Wales, and January 2012 for Scotland). Private rental prices in London (which accounts for almost a third of UK rental expenditure ) increased by 6.8% in the 12 months to July 2023, the highest of any English region. This is the highest annual percentage change in London since the series began in January 2006.  The North East saw the lowest increase in rental prices, at 4.7% in the year to October 2023. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top Inflation falls to lowest level in almost two years 15 November 2023 The rate at which prices of goods and services are rising has fallen to the lowest level since November 2021, according to the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH) . Annual CPIH inflation, rose by 4.7% in the year to October 2023, down from 6.3% in September. CPIH inflation has fallen from a recent peak of 9.6% in October 2022, which was the highest in over 40 years according to indicative estimates . Some of the main downward effects on inflation came from housing and household services, particularly gas and electricity prices. Gas prices fell 31.0% in the year to October 2023, while electricity prices fell by 15.6%. These are the lowest annual inflation rates for gas and electricity since records began in January 1989. Energy prices remain high, however. The price of gas in October 2023 was around 60% higher than two years previously, while the price of electricity was 40% higher. Read our full Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">21491861</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Sales volumes at lowest levels in over two years </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainoctober2023</link>
         <description>Sales volumes at lowest levels in over two years 17 November 2023 Retail sales in Great Britain have fallen to the lowest levels since February 2021, when lockdown restrictions were still in place. Sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought) dropped by 0.3% in October 2023 following a revised drop of 1.1% the previous month, falling to the lowest level in more than two years, when restrictions on non-essential retail were still in place across the country. Automotive fuel sales fell by 2.0% in October 2023, sinking to the lowest level since March 2021. Retailers reported that the drop could be because drivers are being more cautious with money this month. The steady rise of fuel prices since July 2023 could also be a factor. Sales volumes at non-food stores fell by 0.2% in October 2023 following a 2.1% drop the previous month. Poor weather and reduced footfall were seen as potential causes by retailers. Meanwhile, non-store retailers (mostly online shops) saw a 0.8% rise in sales this month after a 2.4% decrease in September 2023. When compared with their pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic level in February 2020, total retail sales were 16.9% higher in value terms, but volumes were 3.1% lower. Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Volume and value sales, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, October 2019 to October 2023 Source: Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Image .csv .xls Read our full Retail sales, Great Britain: October 2023 release bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">18460332</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 09:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
