<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Largest negative terms-of-trade effect since 1970s</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/thetermsoftradethepurchasingpowerofgdp</link>
         <description>

Largest negative terms-of-trade effect since 1970s8 February 2023The impact of higher energy and commodity prices on the UK economy has lowered our terms of trade. This has reduced the UK’s purchasing power — it can import fewer goods and services given the same level of exports. The consequences of this terms-of-trade effect is an unavoidable hit to UK real gross domestic income (GDI). The size and persistence of this effect will depend on how import and export prices evolve over the coming years, and how much of a net energy importer the UK continues to be. Real gross domestic income contracted by 0.2% in the year to Quarter 3 (July to Sept) 2022. Many European countries have experienced a negative terms of trade effect as net energy importers. Italy, Germany and Japan are the G7 countries that have experienced a larger negative terms-of-trade effect than the UK over the last year. However, Norway saw the largest positive purchasing power effect among the OECD countries, while Canada and the Unites States are the only G7 countries to have had a positive terms-of-trade effect over the last year. This reflects how these countries are net energy exporters. 

The UK is currently experiencing its largest negative terms-of-trade effect since the mid-1970s 
Percentage point difference in 4-quarter growth rates of UK real GDI and real GDP, Quarter 1 1970 to Quarter 3 2022 







Source: Office for National Statistics

Notes:

We look at the 4-quarter change in real GDP and real GDI as a proxy of the underlying trend.
Positive values indicate a positive welfare effect, where the change in real GDI is higher than the change in real GDP. Negative values indicate a negative welfare effect, where the change in real GDI is lower than the change in real GDP. 


Download this chart The UK is currently experiencing its largest negative terms-of-trade effect since the mid-1970s 
Image

.csv


.xls



Read our article on The Purchasing Power of GDP, UK: 2022
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">51289695</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Energy prices are main concern of one in five businesses</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators9february2023</link>
         <description>

Energy prices are main concern of one in five businesses9 February 2023Nearly one in five (19%) businesses reported energy prices were their main concern for February 2023, when asked between 23 January and 5 February 2023. This was followed by inflation of goods and services prices (16%) and falling demand for goods and services (13%). In late January 2023, nearly two in five (37%) businesses had taken some form of action to reduce their energy costs in the last three months, with 23% of those businesses reporting they had switched electrical equipment off or on standby more than usual when not in use. Of the 45% of businesses that were not planning to reduce their energy costs in the next three months, 60% said their business’s energy efficiency had already been optimised. 

Read our full Business insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin
🠕 Back to the top

Spending up in pubs and restaurants in early February9 February 2023Debit card spending in pubs and restaurants and on fast food rose above levels recorded before the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic in the week to 5 February 2023.That was the first increase above the pre-pandemic baseline (the average for February 2020) since early December 2022, according to data collected by financial technology company Revolut.Debit card spending also rose in all categories monitored by the company when compared with the equivalent week of 2022. Spending was 47 percentage points higher on retail, and 39 percentage points greater for vehicle fuel.It is important to note that the figures are not adjusted for the potential effects of inflation (the rising price of goods and services) on the value of transactions.A separate indicator of debit and credit card spending, known as the CHAPS monthly index, shows that work-related spending (including on road fuel) in January 2023 was 15 percentage points higher than a year earlier.That was the largest increase of any category and was followed by “social” and “staple” spending, which both increased by 11 percentage points.Figures from job search engine Adzuna show that the number of online job adverts on 3 February 2023 was 21% lower than the number seen a year earlier.

Read our Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 9 February 2023 bulletin
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">66316726</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.5% in December 2022</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpmonthlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>

UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.5% in December 202210 February 2023Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have fallen by 0.5% in December 2022, following growth of 0.1% in November 2022.Looking at the broader picture, UK GDP remained flat in the three months to December 2022 compared with the three months to September 2022.Services fell by 0.8% in December 2022, after an increase of 0.2% in November 2022. The largest contribution to the fall came from education and human health activities, which fell by 2.6% and 2.8%, respectively.Production output grew by 0.3% in December 2022, after a growth of 0.1% in November 2022. Electricity, gas, steam and air conditioning supply was the largest contributor to the production sector’s growth.Construction saw no growth in December 2022, following a fall of 0.5% in November 2022.

The Services sector was the main contributor to negative monthly GDP growth in December 2022
Contributions to monthly GDP growth, December 2021 to December 2022, UK







Source: Office for National Statistics – GDP monthly estimate

Notes:
Sum of component contributions may not sum to total growth because of rounding.

Download this chart The Services sector was the main contributor to negative monthly GDP growth in December 2022
Image

.csv


.xls



Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">32565916</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Fuel imports increase for the first time since August 2022 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/balanceofpayments/bulletins/uktrade/latest</link>
         <description>

Fuel imports increase for the first time since August 2022 10 February 2023Gas prices increased sharply contributing to a large increase in the value of gas imports from Norway in December 2022. When the effect of inflation is removed, fuel imports from non-EU countries increased by a much smaller amount in December 2022. The value of goods imported to the UK increased by £1.6 billion (2.9%) in December 2022. After removing the effect of inflation, imports of goods increased by £0.7 billion (1.5%). Imports of goods from EU countries increased by £1.0 billion (3.8%) and imports from non-EU countries rose by £0.5 billion (1.9%) in December 2022, in value terms. The value of goods exports decreased by £0.8 billion (2.3%) in December 2022, linked to a fall in exports to non-EU countries. After removing the effect of inflation, total exports of goods decreased by £0.1 billion (0.3%). The trade balance of exports and imports over the year for goods and services, excluding precious metals, widened by £85.3 billion to a deficit of £108.0 billion in 2022 when compared with 2021, driven by a 32.5% increase in import values. Imports of goods from both EU and non-EU countries increased in December 2022EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, December 2019 to December 2022


Embed code

Embed this interactive


Copy





Download the dataNotes: 

Caution should be taken when interpreting these data as there is a discontinuity from January 2021 in EU trade following an HM Revenue and Customs data collection change. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics article, provides more detail.
Staged customs controls allowed traders importing goods from the EU to delay customs declarations in 2021 by up to 175 days, and as a result some double counting may have occurred between January and June 2022. Read our blog for more detail. 
Find out more about how we are producing consistent estimates for trade following the UK’s EU exit. 

Read the main bulletin on UK trade 
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">25264979</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around 1 in 30 adults miss work because of industrial action </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain25januaryto5february2023</link>
         <description>

Around 1 in 30 adults miss work because of industrial action 10 February 2023Around 1 in 30 working adults reported that they missed work because of industrial action between 25 January and 5 February 2023. That is 3% of working adults across Britain, according to our latest Public Opinions and Social Trends Survey. That means 97% of respondents said they had not missed work as a result of industrial action. The survey period covers strike action by teachers, train drivers, civil servants and university staff, although the majority of responses came before the industrial action taken on 1 February. When asked about the important issues facing the UK today, 92% of adults cited the cost of living, which made it the most commonly reported issue. That was followed by the NHS (87%), the economy (77%), climate change and the environment (56%). There has been a slight increase in adults reporting the NHS as an important issue over the winter period, and a decrease in reporting climate change and the environment. This may be due to seasonal pressures and cold weather. 

The cost of living remains the most pressing concern 
Proportion of all adults in Great Britain, by issue, 26 October 2022 to 5 February 2023 







Source: Office for National Statistics – Opinions and Lifestyle Survey (OPN)

Notes:

Question: &quot;What do you think are important issues facing the UK today?&quot;
Respondents were able to choose more than one option.


Download this chart The cost of living remains the most pressing concern 
Image

.csv


.xls


Around 9 in 10 adults (94%) reported their cost of living had increased compared with a year ago, while 69% reported an increase compared with one month ago. 

Read our Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 25 January to 5 February 2023 bulletin 
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">37345863</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Young people least likely to work from home</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/wellbeing/articles/characteristicsofadultsexperiencingenergyandfoodinsecuritygreatbritain/22novemberto18december2022</link>
         <description>

Young people least likely to work from home13 February 2023Younger workers continue to be least likely to only work from home (6%). Those aged 16 to 24 years had the highest rate of those travelling to work at 79%, while those aged 34 to 44 years had the lowest rate at 48%, in the period September 2022 to January 2023.The group aged 16 to 24 years also had the highest rate of workers who did not have the ability to work from home, with just under two in three (65%) reporting this. Those aged 25 to 34 years, 35 to 44 years, and 45 to 54 years reported higher rates of home or hybrid working compared with the group aged 16 to 24 years. 16- to 24-year-olds most likely to travel to work without the option to work from homeProportion of working adults in Great Britain, September 2022 to January 2023


Embed code

Embed this interactive


Copy





Download the dataThe levels of people working from home peaked during the coronavirus (COVID-19) lockdown at 49%. Throughout 2022 the percentage of adults who worked from home varied between 25% and 40%, without a clear upward or downward trend. Overall, 44% of workers reported home or hybrid working and 56% reported solely travelling to work in the last seven days.In the most recent period (25 January to 5 February 2023), 40% of working adults reported having worked from home at some point in the past seven days. A higher rate of workers travelling to work (46%) reported not being able to work from home compared with those who travelled to work but could work from home (10%). 

Read our article Characteristics of Homeworkers, Great Britain: September 2022 to January 2023
🠕 Back to the top

Adults in rented homes more likely to experience energy and food insecurity13 February 2023Adults in Great Britain who live in rented housing have higher odds of experiencing some form of energy and food insecurity than those who own their home outright. Those living in rented housing were more than three times as likely to experience some form of food insecurity than those who own their home outright, according to analysis of the ONS’s Winter Survey data, collected between 22 November and 18 December 2022. “Food insecurity ” is when a household does not have enough food to lead a healthy life. We classed adults as experiencing some form of food insecurity if they reported one or more of the following: 

being worried that their food would run out before they could afford to buy more
running out of food before they could afford more 
thinking they or their household could not afford to eat a balanced diet
Adults in rented housing were also around three times more likely to experience some form of energy insecurity than those who own their homes outright.Adults were considered to be experiencing energy insecurity if they reported one or more of the following:

being behind on gas or electricity bill payments
finding it very difficult to afford their energy bills 
never or hardly ever being able to keep warm in their home 
Both food and energy insecurity were more likely among adults with an income below £40,000 and £30,000 per year, respectively, when compared with those earning £40,000 or more.

Read our full bulletin on the characteristics of adults experiencing energy and food insecurity in Great Britain
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">60619742</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>One in five online job adverts in December 2022 were in London</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/articles/labourdemandvolumesbyprofessionandlocalauthorityuk/january2017todecember2022</link>
         <description>

One in five online job adverts in December 2022 were in London13 February 2023One in five jobs advertised online in December 2022 were in London, according to new experimental analysis of Textkernel data. The number of adverts in London was equal to more than 4% of the city’s working age population, higher than in any other UK region. Outside London, six local authorities (Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol, Leeds, Glasgow and Liverpool) had the greatest share of online job adverts in December 2022; they also had the highest increase in their share of total adverts over the previous year. In the UK, the volume of online job adverts fell 56% between December 2021 and December 2022, although they remained above pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic levels, after sharp declines and subsequent increases in adverts during 2020 and 2021. The share of postings advertising healthcare jobs increased between 2021 and 2022, largely from an increase in demand for care assistants, nursing and specialised nurses. The share of adverts for jobs in sales and trading fell the most, followed by those in communication, marketing and public relations. You can select a profession in the following drop-down menu to see how demand for that job type has changed over time in a given area. We have used summary profession categories, with professions that fall into the “other” category not included. Explore demand for different professions over time by local areaShare of online job adverts of a given profession within a given local authority, Local authorities of the UK, January 2017 to December 2022


Embed code

Embed this interactive


Copy





Download the data for online job adverts by local authority (XLSX, 125KB)

Read our full bulletin on labour demand volumes by profession and local authority
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">90951183</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Labour disputes cost more than 800,000 working days in December 2022</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uklabourmarketfebruary2023</link>
         <description>

Labour disputes cost more than 800,000 working days in December 202214 February 2023More working days were lost to labour disputes across the UK in December 2022 than in any other month since November 2011. A total of 843,000 working days were lost over the month, which was significantly more than the 461,000 recorded for November 2022. Our labour market data also show that the rate of annual regular (excluding bonuses) pay growth among employees was 6.7% between October and December 2022, which was the strongest growth rate seen outside of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Annual regular pay grew by 7.3% in the private sector and 4.2% in the public sector. However, regular pay fell in real terms by 2.5% over the period after adjusting for inflation (the rising cost of goods and services). The economic inactivity rate decreased by 0.3 percentage points in the three months to December 2022, to 21.4%. Estimates between July to September 2022 and October to December 2022 show that there was a record-high net flow out of economic inactivity, driven by people moving from economic inactivity to employment. The data also show that the number of vacancies fell by 76,000 in the three months to January 2023, to 1,134,000. That was the seventh consecutive quarterly fall since the three months to July 2022, with respondents to our survey continuing to cite economic pressures as a factor in holding back on recruitment. 

Read our Labour market overview, UK: February 2023 bulletin
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">83606184</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 09:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
