<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Nearly 3 in 10 businesses report worker shortages</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/businessindustryandtrade/business/businessservices/bulletins/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy/latest</link>
         <description>Nearly 3 in 10 businesses report worker shortages 6 April 2023 Nearly 3 in 10 (28%) businesses with 10 or more employees reported a shortage of workers in late March 2023. Of these businesses, nearly half (49%) said employees were working increased hours, while 40% of businesses were unable to meet demands. Among businesses with 10 or more employees, the human health and social work industry was most affected by worker shortages. Nearly half (44%) of these businesses reported worker shortages, according to the latest data from the Business Insights and Conditions Survey, collected from 20 March to 2 April 2023. Energy prices and inflation remain the main concerns for businesses. However, taxation has become more of a concern for businesses, but concerns about energy prices and falling demand for goods and services have fallen, in the most recent survey results. Read our full bulletin on Business insights and impact on the UK economy . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">83469309</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rises in consumer spending, energy prices, and possible redundancies</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators6april2023</link>
         <description>Rises in consumer spending, energy prices, and possible redundancies 6 April 2023 Revolut debit card spending rose by 16 percentage points across all categories compared with the previous week. “Retail” spending represented the largest increase, rising by 28 percentage points, followed by “entertainment”, which rose by 16 percentage points. However, although these rises are large , they are not unusual and follow typical within-month spending patterns. “Retail” spending also rose by around twice the level of increase seen in the “travel and accommodation” and “automotive fuel” categories, which increased by 14 and 13 percentage points, respectively. The System Average Price of gas saw a record increase for 2023, rising by 7% in the week to 2 April. However, the current price is nearly two-thirds lower than the equivalent week last year. According to our analysis of data made available by Elexon, the System Price of electricity also saw a record increase for 2023 in the latest week, rising by around a quarter compared with the previous week. However, this price is around half as much as the price seen during the equivalent period last year. The number of potential redundancies proposed by employers was around nine times higher than the equivalent week last year. Read our full bulletin on Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 6 April 2023 . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">25892077</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have remained flat in February 2023</title>
         <link>https://blog.ons.gov.uk/2023/02/10/trading-places/</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have remained flat in February 2023 13 April 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have shown no growth in February 2023, where falls in services and production were offset by growth in construction. This follows growth of 0.4% in January 2023. Looking at the broader picture, GDP grew by 0.1% in the three months to February 2023 compared with the three months to November 2022. Services fell by 0.1% in February 2023, after growing by 0.7% in January 2023. The largest contributions to the fall in February 2023 came from education, and public administration and defence; compulsory social security. Industrial action took place in both of these industries in February 2023. Production output fell by 0.2% in February 2023, following a fall of 0.5% in January 2023. Electricity, gas, steam and air conditioning supply was the largest contributor to the fall within the production sector. Construction saw a 2.4% growth in February 2023, following a 1.7% fall in January 2023. Growth in the construction sector offset falls in services and production in February 2023 Contributions to monthly GDP growth, February 2022 to February 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Notes: Sum of component contributions may not sum to total growth because of rounding. Download this chart Growth in the construction sector offset falls in services and production in February 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP. 🠕 Back to the top UK trade in goods and services deficit continues to widen because of falls in exports 13 April 2023 The total trade in goods and services deficit, the amount by which the cost of a country's imports exceeds the value of its exports, widened by £2.3 billion to £23.5 billion in the three months to February 2023, as exports fell by more than imports. The value of goods exports decreased by £1.1 billion (3.5%) in February 2023, linked to a fall in fuel exports to EU countries. Accounting for inflation, total exports of goods decreased by £0.8 billion (3.1%). The value of goods imported to the UK decreased by £0.7 billion (1.4%) in February 2023. After removing the effect of inflation, imports of goods decreased by £0.6 billion (1.5%). Imports of goods from EU countries increased by £0.4 billion (1.5%) and imports from non-EU countries fell by £1.1 billion (4.5%) in February 2023, in value terms. Fuel imports from non-EU countries fell by £0.8 billion because of reduced imports of gas and crude oil from the United States and gas from Norway in February 2023. The continued fall in gas prices contributed to this. Imports of goods from non-EU countries continued to decrease in February 2023, while imports from the EU increased EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, February 2020 to February 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Notes: Caution should be taken when interpreting these data as there is a discontinuity from January 2021 in EU trade following an HM Revenue and Customs data collection change. Our article, Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics , provides more detail. Staged Customs Controls allowed traders importing goods from the EU to delay customs declarations in 2021 by up to 175 days, and as a result some double counting may have occurred between January and June 2022. For more detail, read our Trading places: How we are producing consistent estimates of trade figures following the UK’s EU exit blog . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">77656376</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Easter boosts debit card spending on eating out and pubs</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators14april2023</link>
         <description>Easter boosts debit card spending on eating out and pubs 14 April 2023 Revolut debit card spending rose by 17 percentage points in the “pubs, restaurants and fast food” category, compared with the previous week. While four of the six spending categories saw increases in debit card spending, “pubs, restaurants and fast food” saw the largest increase. The “travel and accommodation” category remained broadly unchanged, while the “retail” category was the only category which decreased, dropping by 9 percentage points, likely the result of store closures over the Easter weekend. Experimental data from the CHAPS-based indicator of aggregate credit and debit card spending estimates an increase in all of the four of its spending categories in the latest week to 6 April 2023, with “staple” showing the biggest increase at 13 percentage points. The monthly CHAPS-based indicator of aggregate credit and debit card spending in March 2023 was 3 percentage points higher than in February 2023, having trended upwards since the start of the year, in line with usual seasonal patterns. All spending categories except “delayable” increased from February 2023 to March 2023, with the largest increase reported in the &quot;staple&quot; category, up 7 percentage points compared with February 2023. “Delayable” decreased by 3 percentage points compared with February 2023. The monthly CHAPS indicator in March 2023 was 2 percentage points higher than in March 2022. All categories except &quot;delayable&quot; increased compared with March 2022, with &quot;staple&quot; spending seeing the largest increase of 12 percentage points, followed by &quot;work related&quot; increasing by 10 percentage points and &quot;social&quot; increasing by 3 percentage points. Retail footfall saw an increase in the week to 9 April 2023, increasing to 108% of the level in the previous week. All three categories increased, with high street footfall, shopping centre footfall and retail park footfall at 113%, 105% and 101%, respectively, driven by increased activity over the Easter weekend at monitored retail zones. Similarly, all categories were above the level in the equivalent period of 2022, with high street footfall, shopping centre footfall and retail park footfall at 115%%, 107% and 103%, respectively. Retail footfall increased in all of the 12 UK regions and countries in the week to 9 April 2023, with the largest increase in the South West where footfall was 113% of the level of the previous week. Footfall in all 12 UK regions and countries was above the level in the equivalent period of 2022, with Scotland and Northern Ireland the furthest above this both at 118%. Read our bulletin Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 14 April 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">64163950</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Energy dependent goods and services contributed most to inflation</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/ukgovernmentgrossregionalcapitalandnoncapitalexpenditureonresearchanddevelopmentexperimental2020to2021</link>
         <description>Energy dependent goods and services contributed most to inflation 17 April 2023 Energy prices were a primary cause of consumer price inflation in the year to February 2023, as households faced higher costs. Direct effects of energy prices accounted for a third of the 10.4% increase in consumer prices in the year to February 2023. But energy prices also had an indirect effect on the prices of goods and services, as businesses experienced increased fuel bills and production costs. We looked at these indirect effects by estimating the energy intensity of goods and services in the prices “basket”, used to calculate inflation in consumer prices (CPI). “Very high” energy intensity goods and services explained around a fifth of inflation in February 2023. These included transport services, which are particularly reliant on fuel but also services like restaurants and cafes. A further quarter of inflation was accounted for by “high” energy intensive goods. Overall, more than three-quarters of the 10.4% increase in consumer prices was attributable to direct energy costs and these “very high” and “high” energy intensive goods and services. More than three-quarters of the 10.4% increase in CPI in February 2023 can be explained by the direct effects of energy prices and where the indirect effects are largest Contributions to CPI inflation by energy intensity, percentage points, January 2019 to February 2023 Source: Consumer Prices Index and Input Output Tables from the Office for National Statistics Notes: See our full Energy Intensity of the Consumer Prices Index article for how we defined energy intensity groups and the CPI weightings used. Download this chart More than three-quarters of the 10.4% increase in CPI in February 2023 can be explained by the direct effects of energy prices and where the indirect effects are largest Image .csv .xls While energy costs have contributed a lot to prices rising, other factors are also significant, such as labour and other input costs. Rents are not energy intensive but account for almost two-thirds of spending on housing and household services by weight, and prices are going up largely because of housing market factors. Some products, such as newspapers and clothing, are less dependent on energy costs, because most of their value comes from labour rather than raw materials. Overall, for the CPI “basket”, indirect energy costs accounted for about 6.6% of the price of products. Read the full article on the Energy Intensity of the Consumer Prices Index 🠕 Back to the top Public-funded R&amp;D expenditure highest in London and South East 17 April 2023 Half of the UK’s public-funded research and development (R&amp;D) expenditure was in London, the South East and the East of England in the financial year ending 2021. R&amp;D refers to activity in all sectors of the economy, from universities to businesses and government departments, which aims to create new concepts, products and processes. This type of expenditure is seen as important as it is linked to economic growth. The UK’s total public-funded expenditure on R&amp;D was £14.5 billion in the financial year ending 2021. Excluding any R&amp;D expenditure abroad, around half (49.9%) of that was in London, the South East and the East of England – also referred to as the Greater South East, with 40.4% in London and the South East alone. The figure is for gross expenditure, which means the total amount spent before any deductions are made for income generated from R&amp;D. These estimates will be used as a baseline to measure progress against the government’s Levelling Up mission on public-funded R&amp;D. Read the full article on UK public-funded gross regional capital and non-capital expenditure on research and development: financial year ending 2021 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">72836960</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Earnings are still falling</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uklabourmarketapril2023</link>
         <description>Earnings are still falling 18 April 2023 Total pay (including bonuses) for employees rose by 5.9% in December 2022 to February 2023, and growth in regular pay (excluding bonuses) was 6.6%. However, in real terms (adjusted for inflation) growth in total pay fell by 3.0% and regular pay dropped by 2.3% over the same period. The UK employment rate was estimated at 75.8% in December 2022 to February 2023, 0.2 percentage points higher than September to November 2022. This increase was driven by part-time employees and self-employed workers. The most recent estimate of payrolled employees for March 2023 shows another monthly increase to 30.0 million, up 31,000 on the revised February 2023 figures. The unemployment rate for December 2022 to February 2023 increased by 0.1 percentage points on the quarter to 3.8%. The increase was driven by people unemployed for up to 6 months. Those aged 16 to 24 years have largely been responsible for a decrease in economic inactivity by 0.4 percentage points, with the economic inactivity rate falling to 21.1% during December 2022 to February 2023. The number of job vacancies in the UK fell by 47,000 from January to March 2023, standing at 1.105 million vacancies. Economic pressures were a factor in holding back on recruitment according to survey respondents. There were 348,000 working days lost because of labour disputes in February 2023, up from 210,000 in January 2023. Over three-fifths of the strikes in February were in the education sector. Read our latest Labour market overview, UK 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">72483093</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Overall inflation eases but food prices still rising sharply</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/indexofprivatehousingrentalpricesukmarch2023</link>
         <description>Overall inflation eases but food prices still rising sharply 19 April 2023 Changes in the cost of motor fuels helped slow the overall rate of rising prices paid by UK consumers for goods and services in the 12 months to March 2023. However, the price of food and drink as well as gas and electricity continued to increase at historic rates. As measured by the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH), the annual inflation rate fell slightly to 8.9% in March 2023. That was a slightly lower rate of increase compared with the 9.2% rise recorded in the 12 months to February 2023, but was still high compared with recent years. One of the main factors behind the slowing annual inflation rate was a drop in the price of motor fuels, which fell by 5.9% in the year to March 2023, compared with a rise of 4.6% in February. Despite the slowing of the overall annual rate, food and non-alcoholic drink prices still rose by 19.2% in the year to March 2023, up from 18.2% in February. The latest figure is the highest increase observed for over 45 years. Electricity and gas prices also rose by 66.7% and 129.4%, respectively, in the year to March 2023 (unchanged from February). These prices were also among the main drivers of inflation. Read our latest Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top House price growth slows while private rents see record rises 19 April 2023 Annual growth in UK house prices has continued to slow, as the average cost of a home fell for the third consecutive month in February 2023. Average house prices in the UK increased by 5.5% in the year to February 2023, down from 6.5% in the year to January 2023. The average price of a house was £288,000, which is £16,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £5,000 less than in November 2022. House prices grew the least in Scotland at a rate of 1.0% in the year to February 2023. This was lower than all English regions and lower than the overall rate seen across England (6.0%). Of all English regions, London saw the lowest annual growth in house prices (2.9%) and the West Midlands saw the highest (8.6%). Meanwhile, private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 4.9% in the 12 months to March 2023. This is the eleventh consecutive month of record-breaking growth in UK rental prices. Private rent prices rose 4.6% in England, 4.4% in Wales and 5.1% in Scotland in the year to March 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since January 2006 in England, since January 2010 in Wales, and since January 2012 in Scotland. Rental prices in London rose 4.8% in the year to March 2023. This is the biggest annual percentage change in London since December 2012. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">94005360</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 09:15:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
