<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 09:12:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have increased 0.1% in the first quarter of 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/businessindustryandtrade/constructionindustry/bulletins/constructionoutputingreatbritain/march2023</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have increased 0.1% in the first quarter of 2023 12 May 2023 The first quarterly estimate of real gross domestic product (GDP) shows that the UK economy grew by 0.1% in Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023. Real GDP is estimated to have increased by 0.1% in Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023 UK, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2022 to Quarter 1 2023 Source: GDP first quarterly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Notes: Q1 refers to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar), Q2 refers to Quarter 2 (Apr to June), Q3 refers to Quarter 3 (July to Sept) and Q4 refers to Quarter 4 (Oct to Dec). No periods are open to revision in this publication. Download this chart Real GDP is estimated to have increased by 0.1% in Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023 Image .csv .xls The services sector grew by 0.1% in Quarter 1 2023 with the largest positive contributor being information and communication which grew by 1.2%, with increases in computer programming, consultancy and related activities; and telecommunications. Production output increased by 0.1% in Quarter 1 2023 following no growth in the previous quarter and five consecutive falls before that. Elsewhere, construction output increased for the sixth consecutive quarter. The implied price of GDP was 6.3% higher in Quarter 1 2023 than the same quarter a year ago. Growth has been driven by strong rises in household spending due to recent inflationary pressures, though these price increases are slowing. Read our latest bulletin on UK quarterly GDP. 🠕 Back to the top UK trade fell in March 2023 12 May 2023 In March 2023, the total value of UK goods imports decreased by £1.4 billion (2.8%), and goods exports fell by £0.7 billion (2.3%) compared with February 2023. The monthly falls in both imported and exported goods, were primarily because of decreases in trade with non-EU countries, while trade with the EU remained stable. Imports of goods from non-EU countries continued to decrease in March 2023, while imports from the EU remained stable EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted, January 2020 to March 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. The unchanged level of imports from the EU in March 2023 was because of a rise in imports of machinery and transport equipment being offset by a fall in fuel imports. All other commodities remained stable in March. The quarterly trade in goods deficit narrowed by £8.9 billion to £55.0 billion in Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023, while the trade in services surplus widened by £1.3 billion to £39.8 billion. These changes to the quarterly trade balances were primarily because of falls of £3.8 billion in machinery and transport equipment imports, £3.3 billion in fuel imports and £2.0 billion in imports of other business services. The total trade in goods and services deficit narrowed by £10.2 billion to £15.1 billion in Quarter 1 2023, whereas exports fell by a lesser £5.2 billion. Read our latest UK trade: March 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top In March 2023 construction output increased by 0.2% 12 May 2023 In March 2023 construction output in Great Britain is estimated to have increased by 0.2% compared to February 2023, and by 4.1% compared to March 2022. March 2023 had the highest construction output (£15,616 million) since records began. The increase in monthly construction output was caused by a 0.7% increase in new work, while repair and maintenance decreased by 0.6%. The increase in construction output compared to March 2022 was caused by a 6.1% increase in repair and maintenance, and a 2.8% increase in new work. At the sector level, the main reasons for the monthly increase were increases in “infrastructure new work” and “public other new work” sectors; which increased by 2.2% (£51 million) and 6.5% (£48 million), respectively. Construction output increased 0.7% in Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023 compared with Quarter 4 (Oct to Dec) 2022. This increase came solely from a rise in repair and maintenance (4.9%), as new work saw a decrease of 1.9%. Total construction new orders decreased by 12.4% (A decrease of £1,571 million) in Quarter 1 2023 compared with Quarter 4 2022; this quarterly fall came mainly from “private commercial” and “private housing new orders”, which fell 22.3% (£773 million) and 18.4% (£607 million), respectively. The annual rate of construction output price growth was 8.5% in the 12 months to March 2023; this has slowed slightly from the record annual price growths in both May 2022 and June 2022 (10.4%). Read our latest Construction output bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">45807236</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 09:12:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Record high number inactive because of long term sickness </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uklabourmarketmay2023</link>
         <description>Record high number inactive because of long term sickness 16 May 2023 Labour market data show the economic inactivity rate fell by 0.4 percentage points on the quarter, to 21.0% in January to March 2023. However, those inactive because of long term sickness reached a record high in the same period. Flows estimates show that between October to December and for January to March 2023 there has been a record high net flow of people moving out of economic inactivity. This has largely been driven by people moving from economic inactivity into employment. The UK employment rate was estimated at 75.9% in January to March 2023, with a 0.2 percentage point rise from October to December 2022. This was driven by rises in part-time employees and self-employed workers. Read our latest UK Labour Market bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">671065</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 09:12:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Consumer behaviour indicators decrease</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators18may2023</link>
         <description>Consumer behaviour indicators decrease 18 May 2023 UK consumer behaviour indicator activity has decreased in the latest week, coinciding with the coronation of King Charles III and Camilla, Her Majesty the Queen. In the latest week there were notable falls in spending, potentially also driven by usual within month spending patterns. The aggregate CHAPS-based indicator of credit and debit card purchases decreased by 10 points in the week to 11 May 2023 according to data from the Bank of England. The monthly indicator in April 2023 was 1 percentage point higher than in April 2022. Of the four CHAPS spending categories, “staple” and “work related” both saw an increase, at 12 and 4 percentage points. Meanwhile, “delayable” decreased by 9 percentage points and “social” remained unchanged compared with April 2022. Revolut debit card spending decreased by 10 percentage points in the week to 14 May 2023 compared with the previous week. It was 17 percentage points higher than the equivalent period last year. Five of the six Revolut spending categories saw decreases in debit card spending when compared with the previous week. The biggest decreases were in the “retail” and “pubs, restaurants, and fast food” categories, decreasing 16 and 10 percentage points, respectively. Entertainment was the only category to see an increase, rising by 4 percentage points. Overall retail footfall decreased in the week to 14 May 2023 to 96% of the level of the previous week but was 101% of the level in the equivalent week last year, according to data from Springboard. Read our Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">25532050</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 09:12:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Fewer trading businesses report being affected by price rises</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy18may2023</link>
         <description>Fewer trading businesses report being affected by price rises 18 May 2023 Business conditions continue to be affected by price rises, although there has been a steady downward trend in the number of trading businesses affected since September last year. More than a third (35%) of trading companies reported an increase in the price of goods or services bought in April 2023 compared with the previous month, according to the latest Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS) . However, this has dropped by 2 percentage points compared with March 2023 and is currently at the lowest level seen since March 2022. Almost two-thirds (63%) of businesses not permanently stopped trading reported that they have been affected by general price increases, and over a third of companies saying the same about rising energy costs in April 2023. By contrast, the proportion of trading businesses who expect to raise the prices of their goods or services in June 2023 fell by 5 percentage points, dropping from 23% to 18% compared with expectations for May 2023. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">81713071</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 09:12:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Cost of living increases for around two-thirds of UK adults</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain4to14may2023</link>
         <description>Cost of living increases for around two-thirds of UK adults 19 May 2023 Around two-thirds of UK adults (67%) have experienced an increased cost of living in the last month, when asked between May 4 and May 14 2023. This is according to our latest Public opinions and social trends release. The most common reasons reported by adults who said that their cost of living had increased were an increase in the price of food shopping (96%), an increase in gas or electricity bills (74%) and an increase in the price of fuel (38%). When they were asked what they feel are the most important issues facing the UK today, the most reported issues were the cost of living (91%), the NHS (82%), the economy (73%) and climate change and the environment (59%). around two-thirds (67%) said that their cost of living had increased over the past month, more than 9 in 10 (93%) said it had gone up compared with a year ago. Some of the most frequent actions adults took because of the rising cost of living included spending less on non-essentials (66%), using less fuel in the home (49%) and shopping around more (49%). Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">60244961</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 09:12:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
