<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>UK labour productivity 10% lower than other G7 nations in 2021 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/internationalcomparisonsofukproductivityicpfinalestimates2021</link>
         <description>

UK labour productivity 10% lower than other G7 nations in 2021 11 January 2023The UK had lower labour productivity than France, Germany and the USA during 2021, when measured as a ratio of economic output per hour worked. Comparing the gross domestic product (GDP) with an estimate of total hours worked (after considering overtime and various forms of leave), the UK had an output of £46.92 in current prices for every hour worked in 2021. This was 10% lower than the overall average among Canada, France, Germany, Italy, and the USA. These countries together with Japan, for which 2021 data are not available, and the UK form the G7. 

Labour productivity in the UK was lower than the USA, France and Germany in 2021
Annual output per hour worked (component method), whole economy, current price (CP) in GBP, 2021 







Source: Organisation for Economic Co-operation Development data, Office for National Statistics calculations


Download this chart Labour productivity in the UK was lower than the USA, France and Germany in 2021
Image

.csv


.xls


The USA had the highest economic output at £58.88 per hour worked during 2021, followed by Germany (£55.83) and France (£55.50). Both Italy and Canada had lower economic outputs per hour worked than the UK at £45.33 and £42.94, respectively. All G7 countries experienced a recovery in their output per hour worked during 2021 after productivity declined across the board during 2020, the first year of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. While the UK had the largest decline in output per hour worked (12%) in 2020, the UK also experienced faster growth in this metric (22%) than any other G7 country in 2021. 

Read our full bulletin on international comparisons of UK productivity for 2021
🠕 Back to the top 


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">64366364</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Debit card spending falls, in line with seasonal patterns </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators12january2023</link>
         <description>

Debit card spending falls, in line with seasonal patterns 12 January 2023Debit card spending fell by 7% in the latest week, with most consumer behaviour indicators falling in line with expected seasonal patterns. According to data from Revolut, all spending categories were above the level of seen in the equivalent period of 2022, with “automotive fuel” and “entertainment” spending 47 percentage points and 38 percentage points higher, respectively. Spending in pubs, restaurants and fast food and entertainment decreased the most, in the latest period, falling by 25 and 14 percentage points, respectively. The automotive fuel category saw the largest increase, of three percentage points. Although spending in the entertainment category rose above the pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) baseline for the first time since February 2020 in the previous week, it fell again to 12 percentage points below this level. Overall retail footfall fell to 84% of the level of the previous week, according to Springboard. These data are not adjusted for the potential effects of inflation on the value of transactions 

Read our bulletin on Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 12 January 2023 
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">51686287</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Fuel imports from non-EU countries fell for third month in a row</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktradenovember2022</link>
         <description>

Fuel imports from non-EU countries fell for third month in a row13 January 2023Gas prices continued to decrease in November 2022, leading to the third consecutive month of decreases in the value of fuel imports to the UK from non-EU countries. However, the overall value of goods imports to the UK increased by £1.8 billion (3.5%). Goods imports from EU countries increased by £1.2 billion (4.7%) and imports from non-EU countries rose by £0.6 billion (2.2%), both driven by rising imports of machinery and transport equipment. When removing the effect of inflation, total imports of goods increased by £2.5 billion (6.1%) in November 2022. This was because of a £1.3 billion (7.0%) increase in imports from non-EU countries, and a £1.2 billion (5.3%) increase in imports from the EU. Total exports of goods increased slightly by £0.2 billion (0.7%) in November 2022, with an increase in exports to non-EU countries partially offset by falling exports to the EU. The decrease in exports to the EU was driven by a £0.4 billion fall in fuel exports. When removing the effect of inflation, total exports of goods increased by £0.5 billion (1.7%) in November 2022. Exports to non-EU countries increased by £0.6 billion (4.6%) while exports to the EU fell by £0.2 billion (1.2%). The trade in goods and services deficit, excluding precious metals, narrowed by £6.5 billion to £20.2 billion in the three months to November 2022. This was driven by a decrease in goods imports from non-EU countries, which is linked to falling fuel prices. Imports of goods from both EU and non-EU countries rose in November 2022EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, November 2019 to November 2022


Embed code

Embed this interactive


Copy





Notes:

Caution should be taken when interpreting these data as there is a discontinuity from January 2021 in EU trade following an HM Revenue and Customs data collection change. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics article provides more detail.
Download the data

Read our latest UK Trade bulletin.
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">7317058</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have grown 0.1% in November 2022 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpmonthlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>

UK GDP estimated to have grown 0.1% in November 2022 13 January 2023Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have grown 0.1% in November 2022, following growth of 0.5% in October 2022. Looking at the broader picture, UK GDP fell by 0.3% in the three months to November 2022 compared with the three months to August 2022. Services grew by 0.2% in November 2022, after an increase of 0.7% in October 2022. The largest contribution to the growth came from administrative and support activities, which grew by 2.0% in November 2022, following growth of 1.7% in October 2022. Production output fell by 0.2% in November 2022, after a fall of 0.1% in October 2022 . The fall of 0.5% in manufacturing was the largest contributor to the production sector’s negative growth. Construction saw no growth in November 2022, following an increase of 0.4% in October 2022. 

Services was the main contributor to positive monthly GDP growth in November 2022 
Contributions to monthly GDP growth, November 2021 to November 2022, UK 







Source: Office for National Statistics – GDP monthly estimate 


Download this chart Services was the main contributor to positive monthly GDP growth in November 2022 
Image

.csv


.xls



Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP.
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">85651678</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>A fifth of adults say travel plans affected by rail strikes </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain21december2022to8january2023</link>
         <description>

A fifth of adults say travel plans affected by rail strikes 13 January 2023Around 1 in 5 adults across Great Britain said their travel plans in the previous two weeks had been disrupted by rail strikes. That is according to data collected between 21 December 2022 and 8 January 2023 from the Opinions and Lifestyle Survey, which covers the period of industrial action on the rail network in the lead-up to, and after, Christmas. The survey also reveals around 9 in 10 adults (92%) reported the cost of living as an important issue facing the UK today. More than 8 in 10 (85%) said the NHS was an important issue, up from 81% among those surveyed between 7 and 18 December 2022. That was followed by 75% who cited the economy, while 58% said climate change. 

The cost of living was the most frequently cited concern 
Proportion of all adults in Great Britain, 21 December 2022 to 8 January 2023







Source: Office for National Statistics (ONS) - Opinions and Lifestyle Survey (OPN)


Download this chart The cost of living was the most frequently cited concern 
Image

.csv


.xls


The survey also revealed around two-thirds (65%) of adults have reported they are spending less on non-essentials because of the rising cost of living, while around 4 in 10 adults (41%) reported spending less on food shopping and essentials. That was down from 46% among those asked between 22 November and 4 December 2022. However, it was still far higher than the 25% who said the same when the question was first asked between 15 December 2021 and 3 January 2022. 

Read our latest bulletin on Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">55782062</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Real value of pay continues to fall </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uklabourmarketjanuary2023</link>
         <description>

Real value of pay continues to fall 17 January 2023Regular pay for UK employees fell at near-record levels in the three months to November 2022 after accounting for the rising cost of living. Average regular pay (excluding bonuses) among employees grew 6.4% in September to November 2022, which is the strongest growth rate seen outside the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. The private sector saw growth of 7.2%, while it rose by 3.3% in the public sector. After adjusting for inflation (the rising cost of goods and services), however, pay fell in real terms over the year by 2.6%, which is among the largest drops since records began in 2001. The number of vacancies across the UK in October to December 2022 also fell by 75,000, to 1,161,000, which survey respondents say reflects economic pressures. Although that means there have been six quarterly (three-month period) falls in a row, the number of vacancies remains at historically high levels. The redundancy rate also increased to 3.4 per 1,000 employees in September to November 2022 but remains low. Economic inactivity (people not working nor seeking work) fell very slightly in the last quarter (September to November 2022), although 21.5% of those aged 16 to 64 years in the UK were still classed as economically inactive. 

Read our Labour market overview, UK: January 2023
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">5781872</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Inflation continues to ease from record highs </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukdecember2022</link>
         <description>

Inflation continues to ease from record highs 18 January 2023The annual inflation rate in the UK has continued to ease from 40-year highs, driven by lower rises in motor fuel prices. This was partially offset by higher rises in prices for passenger travel, notably for air travel, which reached record highs. In the year to December 2022, the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupier’s housing costs (CPIH) rose by 9.2%, down from 9.3% in November and 9.6% in October. Indicative modelled estimates suggest that the October rate was the highest rate in over 40 years. In the most recent month however, the CPIH annual rate was equal to the rate recorded just over 30 years earlier, between September and December 1990. The Consumer Prices Index (CPI) rose by 10.5% in the 12 months to December 2022, down from 10.7% in November and 11.1% in October. These falls were driven by lower inflation in transport, notably for motor fuels. The annual CPIH inflation rate for transport was 6.9% in December 2022, down for a sixth consecutive month from a peak of 15.2% in June 2022, and the lowest rate since May 2021. 

Transport inflation eased in December 2022 
CPIH, transport and motor fuels annual inflation rates, UK, December 2012 to December 2022 







Source: Office for National Statistics – Consumer price inflation


Download this chart Transport inflation eased in December 2022 
Image

.csv


.xls


The easing in motor fuels inflation in December 2022 was partially offset by annual price rises of 11.3% for passenger transport by road (largely because of coach fares) and 44.1% for passenger transport by air. The annual inflation rate for passenger transport by air of 44.1% is the largest recorded rate for this class in the national statistic series, which begins in January 2006, and in the constructed series, which begins in January 1989. 

Read our latest Consumer Prices Index bulletin
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">45878293</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 09:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
