<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Stronger than forecast GDP improves debt picture</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Stronger than forecast GDP improves debt picture 22 August 2023 Public sector debt at the end of July 2023 was estimated at 98.5% of GDP (Gross Domestic Product). This means that the level of debt was 1.5% less than the value of the annual output of the UK economy. This represents an increase in debt of 1.9 percentage points (ppts) of GDP compared with the same point last year but 4.0 ppts less than the level forecast by the Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR) in March 2023. July saw upward revisions to our previous estimate of GDP, which have led to downward revisions to the debt ratio for recent months, with debt at the end of June being reduced by 1.3 ppts from 100.8% to 99.5% of GDP. This downward revision means that the last time the debt-to-GDP ratio was above 100% was at the end of the financial year ending March 1961. We recently published a blog explaining How the ONS estimates UK debt to GDP figures and its susceptibility to revision. In July 2023, the public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income, requiring it to borrow £4.3 billion, which is £3.4 billion more than in July last year but £1.7 billion less than forecast by the OBR. This was the fifth highest July borrowing on record, behind that of July 2020, during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic period, and that of July 2009, 2010 and 2011, following the global economic downturn. July receipts are boosted by self-assessed income tax each year, with the £11.8 billion received this month being £2.5 billion more than in July 2022, and a July record. However, inflation continues to put upward pressure on spending, with increases in July’s interest costs, central government consumption (pay and procurement), and uprated benefit payments. Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">19976198</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Half of adults spend more to get their usual food shop </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain9to20august2023</link>
         <description>Half of adults spend more to get their usual food shop 25 August 2023 Around half (51%) of adults across Great Britain say they are spending more than usual to get what they normally buy when food shopping. This is according to those asked between 9 and 20 August 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . It was up from 43% in the previous survey period (26 July to 6 August 2023). Over half (53%) of adults reported that their cost of living had increased compared with a month ago. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">29133549</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Domestic and inward mergers decreased in April to June 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/mergersandacquisitionsinvolvingukcompaniesapriltojune2023</link>
         <description>Domestic and inward mergers decreased in April to June 2023 5 September 2023 Provisional estimates for Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 indicate decreased numbers of domestic and inward mergers and acquisitions (M&amp;A), although the number of outward acquisitions increased when compared with Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023. Domestic mergers and acquisitions (M&amp;A) involve UK companies acquiring other UK companies. Inward M&amp;A involve foreign companies acquiring UK companies. Outward M&amp;A involve UK companies acquiring foreign companies. In Quarter 2 2023, the total combined number of cross-border and domestic M&amp;A involving a change in majority share ownership was 450, which was 58 transactions fewer than Quarter 1 2023 (508). The value of inward M&amp;A in Quarter 2 2023 was £7.4 billion, £4.4 billion lower than the previous quarter (£11.8 billion) and £4.7 billion lower than the same quarter last year (£12.1 billion). The total value of outward M&amp;A in Quarter 2 2023 was £2.3 billion, £0.6 billion lower than in Quarter 1 2023 (£2.9 billion) and £2.4 billion lower than Quarter 2 2022 (£4.7 billion). The value of domestic M&amp;A during Quarter 2 2023 was £2.4 billion, £0.3 billion lower than Quarter 1 2023 (£2.7 billion) and £1.1 billion lower than Quarter 2 2022 (£3.5 billion). The data produced and published for the Mergers and Acquisitions Survey involving UK companies only include transactions that result in a change of ultimate control of the target company and have a value of £1 million or more. We advise caution when comparing results for January to June 2023 as these numbers are provisional and may be subject to revisions until early 2024. Revisions can be in either direction, but historically have been more likely to be upward than downward. Read Mergers and Acquisitions involving UK Companies April to June 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">29415424</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>August bank holiday coincides with retail spending increase </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators7september2023</link>
         <description>August bank holiday coincides with retail spending increase 07 September 2023 Retail debit card spending increased by 12 percentage points in the week to 3 September 2023, which included the August bank holiday. Consumer behaviour indicators showed an increase, according to data from Revolut. Higher retail spending and a 1 percentage point rise in travel and accommodation spending contributed to a rise of 1 percentage point in overall debit card spending. Travel and accommodation and retail spending increases were partially offset by four of the six sector categories showing decreased spending. “Pubs, restaurants and fast food” spending had the largest decrease of 8 percentage points, followed by “Entertainment”, which decreased by 7 percentage points. Total Revolut debit card spending was 21 percentage points above the equivalent period in 2022, with all six categories seeing increases in spending since last year. The largest increase was &quot;retail&quot;, which increased by 32 percentage points, followed by “food and drink”, which increased by 28 percentage points when compared with the equivalent period in 2022. Read our latest bulletin Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 7 September 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">81443372</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>More than 4 in 10 mortgage and rent payers struggling</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain23augustto3september2023</link>
         <description>More than 4 in 10 mortgage and rent payers struggling 08 September 2023 More than 4 in 10 (42%) rent or mortgage payers in Britain say they are finding it difficult to afford the payments. This is according to those asked between 23 August and 3 September 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . The figure was 35% during a similar period one year ago (31 August to 11 September 2022). The survey also reveals that more than 4 in 10 (45%) reported that their rent or mortgage payments had gone up in the past six months, while 1 in 50 (2%) said they were currently behind on their rent or mortgage payments. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">73117200</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Average annual UK pay hits joint record levels</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/uklabourmarket/latest</link>
         <description>Average annual UK pay hits joint record levels 12 September 2023 Regular annual UK pay growth (excluding bonuses) hit 7.8% in May to July 2023, matching the previous three-month period, meaning the most recent increases hit record levels since comparable records began in 2001. Real terms (adjusted for CPIH inflation) total (including bonuses) and regular pay also rose on the year by 1.2% and 0.6%, respectively. However, working days lost to industrial action soared from 160,000 in June 2023 to around 281,000 in July (an increase of around 75%), reversing the downward trend seen since the end of March this year, when the number of working days lost to labour force disputes were at their highest since December 2022. The estimated UK employment rate fell slightly from 76.0% in February to April 2023 to 75.5% in May to July 2023, a decrease driven mainly by full-time self-employed workers. By contrast, the unemployment rate rose from 3.8% in February to April 2023 to 4.3% in May to July 2023, driven largely by people who were unemployed for up to 12 months. Estimated job vacancies fell on the quarter for the 14th consecutive period in June to August 2023, dropping by around 64,000 to 989,000. Read more in our latest UK labour market bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">95536380</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.5% in July 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpmonthlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.5% in July 2023 13 September 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have fallen by 0.5% for July 2023, with falls in all three main sectors, following growth of 0.5% in June 2023. Looking at the broader picture, GDP increased by 0.2% in the three months to July 2023, with growth in all three main sectors. Services output was down 0.5% in July 2023, after growth of 0.2% in June 2023, and was the main contributor to the fall in GDP in July. Output in consumer facing services showed no growth in July 2023, following growth of 0.5% in June 2023. Production output fell by 0.7% in July 2023 after growth of 1.8% in June 2023. The construction sector declined by 0.5% in July 2023 following a 1.6% rise in June 2023. All three main sectors contributed to the fall in GDP in July Contributions to monthly GDP growth, July 2022 to July 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart All three main sectors contributed to the fall in GDP in July Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">99565432</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Total imports of goods decreased slightly in July</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktradejuly2023</link>
         <description>Total imports of goods decreased slightly in July 13 September 2023 Total imports of goods in &quot;current prices&quot;, which are not adjusted for inflation, decreased by £0.2 billion (0.4%) in July 2023. Imports from EU countries fell by £0.5 billion, while imports from non-EU countries rose by £0.3 billion. The rise in imports from non-EU countries was primarily the result of increased fuel prices, particularly a slight rebound in gas prices after the large fall in June. After removing the effect of inflation by calculating &quot;chained volume measures&quot;, total goods imports increased by £0.2 billion (0.4%) in July 2023. This was because imports from non-EU countries rose by £0.4 billion (2.1%) while imports from EU countries fell by £0.2 billion (0.8%). Total exports of goods in “current prices” increased by £0.2 billion (0.8%) because of a £0.5 billion rise in exports to EU countries, while exports to non-EU countries fell by £0.2 billion. The total trade in goods and services deficit widened by £1.2 billion to £18.8 billion in the three months to July 2023, because of a larger fall in exports than imports. Imports from the EU continue to be greater than imports from non-EU countries in July 2023 EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted, January 2020 to July 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. Read our latest UK Trade release 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">61890069</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Direct Debit failures up 14% from last year</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators14september2023</link>
         <description>Direct Debit failures up 14% from last year 14 September 2023 The total Direct Debit failure rate in August 2023 increased by 14% when compared with August 2022. These data from Pay.UK and Vocalink are part of a new monthly real-time indicator, which tracks Direct Debit average transaction and failure rate. When compared with July 2023, the total Direct Debit failure rate in August 2023 remained broadly unchanged, staying at similar levels since March 2023. The total monthly average of Direct Debit transactions saw little change in August 2023 compared with July 2023, and increased by 3 percentage points when compared with August 2022. The total Direct Debit failure rate increased by 14% in August 2023 compared with August 2022 Direct Debit failure rate, January 2019 to August 2023, non-seasonally adjusted, UK Source: Pay.UK and Vocalink Download this chart The total Direct Debit failure rate increased by 14% in August 2023 compared with August 2022 Image .csv .xls Consumer behaviour indicators generally showed decreased activity in the latest week. Revolut debit card spending fell by 11 percentage points when compared with the previous week, with a notable 21 percentage point fall in “Automotive fuel” spending. According to data from Springboard, overall UK retail footfall decreased to 96% of the previous week, coinciding with the end of the school summer holidays and the previous week containing the summer bank holiday across much of the UK. Read the latest Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 14 September 2023 release 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">65737744</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK disposable income rose between 2020 and 2021</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/regionalgrossdisposablehouseholdincomeuk1997to2021</link>
         <description>UK disposable income rose between 2020 and 2021 14 September 2023 Gross disposable household income (GDHI) in the UK rose 3.6% between 2020 and 2021, as household finances started to recover from the impacts of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. GDHI is the amount of money available for people to spend or save after taxes and benefits. In 2021, London had the highest GDHI per head of any UK nation or English region, at £31,094. Northern Ireland had the lowest, at £17,636. Of 179 local areas in the UK, 152 saw GDHI rise more than inflation (CPIH), while in the remaining 27, growth in disposable income was lower than inflation, which suggests a decrease in the real-terms value of disposable income. The local areas that saw the biggest increases in GDHI between 2020 and 2021 were the London boroughs of Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham, where disposable income rose by 6.4%. Causeway Coast and Glens in Northern Ireland had the smallest increase, at 0.2%. We have mapped how GDHI has changed in areas of the UK between 1997 and 2021. Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Read the full Regional gross disposable household income, UK: 1997 to 2021 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">14149305</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Inflation eases with food prices rising at slower pace</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukaugust2023</link>
         <description>Inflation eases with food prices rising at slower pace 20 September 2023 The rate at which prices of goods and services are rising for consumers has continued to ease, with the annual inflation rate falling to 6.3% in the year to August 2023. This was down from 6.4% in July, according to our Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH) release. The easing of inflation was partly because food and non-alcoholic beverages prices rose by a smaller amount than the same time last year. Food and non-alcoholic beverage prices rose by 0.3% between July and August 2023, compared with 1.5% between the same two months in 2022. This led to a fall in the annual rate to 13.6% in the year to August 2023. This was down from 14.9% in July and a recent high of 19.2% in March. Prices of some foods, notably milk, cheese, fish and vegetables, fell between July and August 2023. Accommodation prices also fell between July and August 2023. This helped the annual inflation rate for restaurants and hotels ease to 8.3% in August, down from 9.6% in July. Read our latest Consumer price inflation, UK: August 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">48333249</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows while private rents rise at a record pace</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/indexofprivatehousingrentalprices/latest</link>
         <description>House price growth slows while private rents rise at a record pace 20 September 2023 The annual inflation rate of average UK house prices continued to slow in the year to July 2023, with prices decreasing over the year in some regions. The provisional estimate for the average price of a UK house was £290,000 in July 2023. This is £2,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £2,000 less than the recent peak in November 2022. This represents an average increase of 0.6% in the year to July 2023 (provisional), down from growth of 1.9% in the year to May 2023 (revised estimate). House prices in England also increased by 0.6% in the 12 months to July 2023. Annual house price inflation was slower in Scotland, at 0.1%, while average house prices in Wales fell by 0.1% in the 12 months to July 2023. Of the English regions, the North East saw the highest house price inflation in the year to July 2023 (2.7%), although this was down from 5.7% in the year to June 2023. House prices in the North East remain the lowest of all English regions at £163,000. The South West saw the lowest annual inflation of any English region, with prices decreasing by 1.0% in the year to July 2023. London was the only other region where prices decreased in the year to July 2023. The North East saw the highest annual inflation in house prices of any English region All dwellings annual house price percentage change, by English region, 12 months to July 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry and Office for National Statistics Download this chart The North East saw the highest annual inflation in house prices of any English region Image .csv .xls Meanwhile, private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 5.5% in the year to August 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 5.4% in England, 6.5% in Wales and 6.0% in Scotland in the year to August 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since records began (January 2006 for England, January 2010 for Wales, and January 2012 for Scotland). Private rental prices in London (a city that accounts for almost a third of total UK rental expenditure ) increased by 5.9% in the 12 months to August 2023. This was the highest annual percentage change of any English region, and the highest in London since the series began in January 2006. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">27513165</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 09:05:21 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
