<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 09:04:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Around half of adults see rises in rent or mortgage payments </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain14to25june2023</link>
         <description>Around half of adults see rises in rent or mortgage payments 30 June 2023 Around half (47%) of adults in Great Britain have seen rises in their rent or mortgage payments in the past six months. This is according to our latest Public opinions and social trends survey , carried out between 14 and 25 June 2023. It is up from 30% of those asked in June 2022 who said that they had seen rises in the previous six months. There has been a corresponding rise among those saying that they are finding it difficult to afford their rent or mortgage payments. In the latest period, 43% said that they were finding these payments very or somewhat difficult, up from a quarter (25%) in June 2022. Among those surveyed in the latest period, 1 in 50 (2%) said that they were behind on their rent or mortgage payments. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">96406868</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Output per hour worked decreased in Quarter 1 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/productivityoverviewukjanuarytomarch2023</link>
         <description>Output per hour worked decreased in Quarter 1 2023 07 July 2023 Labour productivity in the UK, measured as output per hour worked, was 0.6% below in the year to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023 when compared with the same quarter a year ago. The decrease was driven by growth in hours worked (0.8%) being larger than growth in gross value added (GVA), which was at 0.2%. Excluding the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic period, Quarter 1 2023 saw the largest fall in output per hour worked since Quarter 1 2013. Compared with pre-pandemic levels (2019 average), output per hour worked grew 0.6% in Quarter 1 2023. This growth was driven by an increase of GVA of 0.6% since 2019. The number of hours worked remained constant over this period, with a growth of 0.0%. Other measures of productivity, such as output per worker and output per job, were 0.9% and 1.0% below their respective Quarter 1 2022 levels. This is because of higher growth in the number of workers (1.1%) and jobs (1.2%) than in GVA (0.2%). Administrative service and construction industries made the biggest upwards industry contribution to annual productivity growth (output per hour worked) as of Quarter 1 2023. In contrast, finance and insurance and real estate industries showed the biggest negative contribution to productivity growth. Read our latest Productivity overview, UK bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">6818183</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Real pay continues to fall</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/uklabourmarket/june2023</link>
         <description>Real pay continues to fall 11 July 2023 Although average total pay (including bonuses) and regular pay (excluding bonuses) continued to rise compared with the previous year, real wages which are adjusted for inflation (price rises) fell over the same period. According to the latest labour market data, average total pay (including bonuses) for UK employees rose by 6.9% in March to May 2023 compared with the same period the previous year. Regular pay (excluding bonuses) rose by 7.3%, which was also seen last month and during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. By contrast, real terms total pay (adjusted for inflation) fell by 1.2% and regular pay dropped by 0.8% over the same period. Job vacancies also continued to fall in April to June 2023 by 85,000 to 1.034 million. The estimated number of vacancies fell on the quarter for the 12th consecutive period. The UK employment rate rose again by 0.2 percentage points to 76.0% in March to May 2023, an increase driven mainly by part-time employees. UK unemployment also increased by 0.2 percentage points to 4.0%. The economic inactivity rate (people not in work or looking for work) dropped by 0.4 percentage points, down to 20.8% during March to May 2023. This was largely driven by those who were inactive for other reasons, those looking after family or home, and those who are retired. Labour disputes led to around 128,000 lost working days in May 2023, fewer than half as many working days as in April 2023, and the lowest number since July 2022. Read the full Labour Market Overview, UK: July 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">85723063</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in May 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktrademay2023</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in May 2023 13 July 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in May 2023, with the production sector being the main contributor. This follows growth of 0.2% in April 2023. Looking at the broader picture, GDP showed no growth in the three months to May 2023 compared with the three months to February 2023. Production output fell by 0.6% in May 2023 after a fall of 0.2% in April 2023, revised up from a fall of 0.3% in the previous publication. This sector was the main contributor to the fall in monthly GDP in May. Services output showed no growth in May 2023, following a growth 0.3% in April 2023. Within the sector the largest increase came from Human health and social work activities, largely driven by an increase of 1.8% in Human health activities after falls in March and April. The construction sector fell by 0.2% in May 2023 following a fall of 0.9% in April 2023, revised down from a fall of 0.6% in the previous publication. The production sector was the main contributor to the fall in GDP in May Contributions to monthly GDP growth, May 2022 to May 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics. Download this chart The production sector was the main contributor to the fall in GDP in May Image .csv .xls Read our latest UK monthly GDP bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Imports from both EU and non-EU countries rose in May 2023 13 June 2023 In May 2023, the value of goods imports increased by £2.0 billion (4.2%). Imports from non-EU countries rose by £1.3 billion while imports from EU countries grew by £0.7 billion. After removing the effect of inflation, imports of goods increased by 5.9%. The rise in imports from the EU was because of an increase in imports of cars from Germany, likely linked to the easing of supply chain issues. Imports from EU countries have been consistently greater than from non-EU countries since the end of 2022. The value of goods exports fell by £1.4 billion (4.4%) in May 2023. Exports to the EU decreased by £1.1 billion and exports to non-EU countries fell by £0.3 billion. After removing the effect of inflation, exports of goods fell by 3.2%. Imports from EU and non-EU countries rose in May 2023, while exports decreased EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted:, January 2020 to May 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. Download the data .xlsx The total trade in goods and services deficit narrowed by £5.9 billion to £18.2 billion in the three months to May 2023, compared with the three months to February 2023. This was a result of a larger fall in imports and a rise in exports. The trade in goods deficit narrowed by £6.2 billion to £54.7 billion in the three months to May 2023, while the trade in services surplus narrowed slightly by £0.3 billion to £36.5 billion. Read our latest UK trade: May 2023 bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">13375816</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Almost a quarter of businesses experiencing fall in turnover </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy13july2023</link>
         <description>Almost a quarter of businesses experiencing fall in turnover 13 July 2023 Almost a quarter (24%) of UK trading businesses reported lower turnover for June 2023 compared with May 2023. In comparison, 15% reported a higher turnover for June 2023, with both figures broadly stable with the proportions reported for May 2023. When trading businesses were asked to look ahead to August, more than half (54%) expect turnover to stay the same, while 15% expect it to increase, down from 19% reported for July 2023. Less than one in six (15%) trading businesses expect to raise the prices of goods or services they sell in August 2023; of these, a quarter (25%) reported energy prices as a reason for considering doing so, 21% reported labour costs and 19% reported raw material prices. The proportion of businesses expecting staff costs to rise over the next three months was 17%, down from 30% reported in the three months to April 2023. A quarter (25%) of businesses in the accommodation and food service activities industry said they expected their staffing costs to increase over the next three months. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">74654421</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
