<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 13:18:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Business investment lower than previously estimated </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinvestmentintheukjulytoseptember2022revisedresults</link>
         <description>

Business investment lower than previously estimated 22 December 2022Business investment in the UK fell by 2.5% in Quarter 3 (July to Sept) 2022. This figure has been revised down from the provisional estimate of a 0.5% fall. Whole economy investment (technically known as gross fixed capital formation (GFCF)), which includes business and public sector investment, grew by 1.1%. Although this is lower than the provisional estimate of 2.5%, overall investment in this area and the majority of its components remain above pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic levels. In Quarter 3 2022, whole economy investment was 0.2% above its pre-coronavirus pandemic level and 3.7% above Quarter 3 2021. Positive growth in residential property has been the main factor in whole economy investment returning to pre-pandemic levels. In Quarter 3 2022, growth in this sector remained positive, at 1.0%. Although this revised figure is slower than the provisional estimate of 4.2%, it is 12.4% above pre-pandemic levels. Whole economy investment in non-residential buildings and structures like roads, bridges and energy-related structures is now 8.3% below its pre-coronavirus pandemic level. 

Read our full bulletin about  business investment in the UK.
🠕 Back to the top 


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">53823278</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 13:18:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rising food prices leave most vulnerable worst off </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/risingfoodpricesandtheimpactonconsumers</link>
         <description>

Rising food prices leave most vulnerable worst off 22 December 2022The rising cost of supermarket staples is hitting low-income families the hardest, while households in the most-deprived areas are more likely to be buying less food. The price of food and non-alcoholic drink rose by 16.5% in the 12 months to November 2022, which was the largest increase for 45 years according to our UK Consumer Price Inflation data. Bread and cereals had the largest upward effect on the annual inflation rate in November compared with October. 

Food and drink prices are rising at the fastest rate since 1977 
Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers' housing costs (CPIH), and food and non-alcoholic drinks annual inflation rates, UK, November 2012 to November 2022 







Source: Office for National Statistics (ONS) – Consumer price inflation


Download this chart Food and drink prices are rising at the fastest rate since 1977 
Image

.csv


.xls


Our research shows that the rising prices of these basic items has a greater effect on low-income households, who spend a larger proportion of their budget on food and non-alcoholic drink. More than half (51%) of British adults reported buying less when food shopping in the last two weeks, when surveyed between 22 November and 4 December 2022. Figures covering England show that 61% of adults in the most-deprived areas were buying less on their food shop, compared with 44% of people in the least-deprived areas. This could be having a knock-on effect on some people’s health. A Food Standards Agency survey found that in November 2022, 23% of participants said they had skipped a meal or cut down the size of their meals because they could not afford to buy food in the past month. 

Read our full article here: Rising food prices leave most vulnerable worst off 
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">63305212</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 13:18:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Post-Christmas retail activity rose compared with 2021 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators6january2023</link>
         <description>

Post-Christmas retail activity rose compared with 2021 06 January 2023Retail activity fell across the UK after Christmas but was still well above the levels seen a year earlier, with Wales seeing the largest rise. Overall retail footfall in the week to 1 January 2023 fell to 84% of the level of the previous week, according to figures collected by data firm Springboard. The drop followed the busy Christmas shopping period and was in line with expected seasonal trends. Footfall in shopping centres saw the biggest decrease, at 80% of the level of the previous week. However, the level of activity was above that recorded in the same period a year earlier across all nine English regions and the three other UK nations. Wales saw the largest increase, at 121% of the level of the previous year. This coincided with national coronavirus (COVID-19) restrictions. 

Read our full bulletin on Economic activity and social change in the UK 
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">34695735</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 13:18:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Cost of future fixed-rate mortgages could increase </title>
         <link>/generator?uri=/economy/economicoutputandproductivity/output/articles/ukeconomylatest/2021-01-25/e4dcacc8&amp;format=xls</link>
         <description>

Cost of future fixed-rate mortgages could increase 9 January 2023More than 1.4 million households in the UK are facing the prospect of interest rate rises when they renew their fixed rate mortgages in 2023. Most fixed rate mortgages in the UK (57%) coming up for renewal in 2023 were fixed at interest rates below 2%. Those trying to secure a new fixed-rate deal may have to do it at a higher rate of interest. The effective interest rate on outstanding mortgages with a fixed rate was 2.08% in November 2022, according to the Bank of England (BoE). Should the interest rate on a £100,000 mortgage increase from 2% to 6%, assuming a 25-year capital and repayment mortgage, then the monthly mortgage repayment on the same mortgage would increase by £220 (from £424 to £644). However, assuming the same increase on a £300,000 mortgage, monthly repayments would rise by £661 (from £1,272 to £1,933). The BoE's Financial Stability Report - December 2022, suggests that mortgagors on fixed rates set to expire by the end of 2023 are facing monthly repayment increases of around £250 upon refinancing to a new fixed rate. 

The mortgage costs that households face depend on the amount they borrowed and the interest rate on their mortgage 
Monthly mortgage costs at differing amounts of borrowing and different fixed interest rate 







Source: Office for National Statistics

Notes:

The standard mortgage repayment formula used to estimate monthly costs assumes a 25-year repayment period for a capital and repayment mortgage


Download this chart The mortgage costs that households face depend on the amount they borrowed and the interest rate on their mortgage 
Image

.csv


.xls


Those on a variable rate mortgage, where the interest rate varies over the course of the repayment term, will have already seen higher interest rates as a result of market conditions including rises in the BoE base rate (the &quot;Bank Rate&quot;). Private renters are also facing an increase to their housing costs, with rental price growth at its highest rate in the UK since records began in 2016. 

Read our full article on how increases in mortgage costs impact households



</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">22547912</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 13:18:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK labour productivity 10% lower than other G7 nations in 2021 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/internationalcomparisonsofukproductivityicpfinalestimates2021</link>
         <description>

UK labour productivity 10% lower than other G7 nations in 2021 11 January 2023The UK had lower labour productivity than France, Germany and the USA during 2021, when measured as a ratio of economic output per hour worked. Comparing the gross domestic product (GDP) with an estimate of total hours worked (after considering overtime and various forms of leave), the UK had an output of £46.92 in current prices for every hour worked in 2021. This was 10% lower than the overall average among Canada, France, Germany, Italy, and the USA. These countries together with Japan, for which 2021 data are not available, and the UK form the G7. 

Labour productivity in the UK was lower than the USA, France and Germany in 2021
Annual output per hour worked (component method), whole economy, current price (CP) in GBP, 2021 







Source: Organisation for Economic Co-operation Development data, Office for National Statistics calculations


Download this chart Labour productivity in the UK was lower than the USA, France and Germany in 2021
Image

.csv


.xls


The USA had the highest economic output at £58.88 per hour worked during 2021, followed by Germany (£55.83) and France (£55.50). Both Italy and Canada had lower economic outputs per hour worked than the UK at £45.33 and £42.94, respectively. All G7 countries experienced a recovery in their output per hour worked during 2021 after productivity declined across the board during 2020, the first year of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. While the UK had the largest decline in output per hour worked (12%) in 2020, the UK also experienced faster growth in this metric (22%) than any other G7 country in 2021. 

Read our full bulletin on international comparisons of UK productivity for 2021
🠕 Back to the top 


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">64366364</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 13:18:19 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
