<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 09:13:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Easter boosts debit card spending on eating out and pubs</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators14april2023</link>
         <description>Easter boosts debit card spending on eating out and pubs 14 April 2023 Revolut debit card spending rose by 17 percentage points in the “pubs, restaurants and fast food” category, compared with the previous week. While four of the six spending categories saw increases in debit card spending, “pubs, restaurants and fast food” saw the largest increase. The “travel and accommodation” category remained broadly unchanged, while the “retail” category was the only category which decreased, dropping by 9 percentage points, likely the result of store closures over the Easter weekend. Experimental data from the CHAPS-based indicator of aggregate credit and debit card spending estimates an increase in all of the four of its spending categories in the latest week to 6 April 2023, with “staple” showing the biggest increase at 13 percentage points. The monthly CHAPS-based indicator of aggregate credit and debit card spending in March 2023 was 3 percentage points higher than in February 2023, having trended upwards since the start of the year, in line with usual seasonal patterns. All spending categories except “delayable” increased from February 2023 to March 2023, with the largest increase reported in the &quot;staple&quot; category, up 7 percentage points compared with February 2023. “Delayable” decreased by 3 percentage points compared with February 2023. The monthly CHAPS indicator in March 2023 was 2 percentage points higher than in March 2022. All categories except &quot;delayable&quot; increased compared with March 2022, with &quot;staple&quot; spending seeing the largest increase of 12 percentage points, followed by &quot;work related&quot; increasing by 10 percentage points and &quot;social&quot; increasing by 3 percentage points. Retail footfall saw an increase in the week to 9 April 2023, increasing to 108% of the level in the previous week. All three categories increased, with high street footfall, shopping centre footfall and retail park footfall at 113%, 105% and 101%, respectively, driven by increased activity over the Easter weekend at monitored retail zones. Similarly, all categories were above the level in the equivalent period of 2022, with high street footfall, shopping centre footfall and retail park footfall at 115%%, 107% and 103%, respectively. Retail footfall increased in all of the 12 UK regions and countries in the week to 9 April 2023, with the largest increase in the South West where footfall was 113% of the level of the previous week. Footfall in all 12 UK regions and countries was above the level in the equivalent period of 2022, with Scotland and Northern Ireland the furthest above this both at 118%. Read our bulletin Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 14 April 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">64163950</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 09:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Energy dependent goods and services contributed most to inflation</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/ukgovernmentgrossregionalcapitalandnoncapitalexpenditureonresearchanddevelopmentexperimental2020to2021</link>
         <description>Energy dependent goods and services contributed most to inflation 17 April 2023 Energy prices were a primary cause of consumer price inflation in the year to February 2023, as households faced higher costs. Direct effects of energy prices accounted for a third of the 10.4% increase in consumer prices in the year to February 2023. But energy prices also had an indirect effect on the prices of goods and services, as businesses experienced increased fuel bills and production costs. We looked at these indirect effects by estimating the energy intensity of goods and services in the prices “basket”, used to calculate inflation in consumer prices (CPI). “Very high” energy intensity goods and services explained around a fifth of inflation in February 2023. These included transport services, which are particularly reliant on fuel but also services like restaurants and cafes. A further quarter of inflation was accounted for by “high” energy intensive goods. Overall, more than three-quarters of the 10.4% increase in consumer prices was attributable to direct energy costs and these “very high” and “high” energy intensive goods and services. More than three-quarters of the 10.4% increase in CPI in February 2023 can be explained by the direct effects of energy prices and where the indirect effects are largest Contributions to CPI inflation by energy intensity, percentage points, January 2019 to February 2023 Source: Consumer Prices Index and Input Output Tables from the Office for National Statistics Notes: See our full Energy Intensity of the Consumer Prices Index article for how we defined energy intensity groups and the CPI weightings used. Download this chart More than three-quarters of the 10.4% increase in CPI in February 2023 can be explained by the direct effects of energy prices and where the indirect effects are largest Image .csv .xls While energy costs have contributed a lot to prices rising, other factors are also significant, such as labour and other input costs. Rents are not energy intensive but account for almost two-thirds of spending on housing and household services by weight, and prices are going up largely because of housing market factors. Some products, such as newspapers and clothing, are less dependent on energy costs, because most of their value comes from labour rather than raw materials. Overall, for the CPI “basket”, indirect energy costs accounted for about 6.6% of the price of products. Read the full article on the Energy Intensity of the Consumer Prices Index 🠕 Back to the top Public-funded R&amp;D expenditure highest in London and South East 17 April 2023 Half of the UK’s public-funded research and development (R&amp;D) expenditure was in London, the South East and the East of England in the financial year ending 2021. R&amp;D refers to activity in all sectors of the economy, from universities to businesses and government departments, which aims to create new concepts, products and processes. This type of expenditure is seen as important as it is linked to economic growth. The UK’s total public-funded expenditure on R&amp;D was £14.5 billion in the financial year ending 2021. Excluding any R&amp;D expenditure abroad, around half (49.9%) of that was in London, the South East and the East of England – also referred to as the Greater South East, with 40.4% in London and the South East alone. The figure is for gross expenditure, which means the total amount spent before any deductions are made for income generated from R&amp;D. These estimates will be used as a baseline to measure progress against the government’s Levelling Up mission on public-funded R&amp;D. Read the full article on UK public-funded gross regional capital and non-capital expenditure on research and development: financial year ending 2021 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">72836960</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 09:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Earnings are still falling</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uklabourmarketapril2023</link>
         <description>Earnings are still falling 18 April 2023 Total pay (including bonuses) for employees rose by 5.9% in December 2022 to February 2023, and growth in regular pay (excluding bonuses) was 6.6%. However, in real terms (adjusted for inflation) growth in total pay fell by 3.0% and regular pay dropped by 2.3% over the same period. The UK employment rate was estimated at 75.8% in December 2022 to February 2023, 0.2 percentage points higher than September to November 2022. This increase was driven by part-time employees and self-employed workers. The most recent estimate of payrolled employees for March 2023 shows another monthly increase to 30.0 million, up 31,000 on the revised February 2023 figures. The unemployment rate for December 2022 to February 2023 increased by 0.1 percentage points on the quarter to 3.8%. The increase was driven by people unemployed for up to 6 months. Those aged 16 to 24 years have largely been responsible for a decrease in economic inactivity by 0.4 percentage points, with the economic inactivity rate falling to 21.1% during December 2022 to February 2023. The number of job vacancies in the UK fell by 47,000 from January to March 2023, standing at 1.105 million vacancies. Economic pressures were a factor in holding back on recruitment according to survey respondents. There were 348,000 working days lost because of labour disputes in February 2023, up from 210,000 in January 2023. Over three-fifths of the strikes in February were in the education sector. Read our latest Labour market overview, UK 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">72483093</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 09:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Overall inflation eases but food prices still rising sharply</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/indexofprivatehousingrentalpricesukmarch2023</link>
         <description>Overall inflation eases but food prices still rising sharply 19 April 2023 Changes in the cost of motor fuels helped slow the overall rate of rising prices paid by UK consumers for goods and services in the 12 months to March 2023. However, the price of food and drink as well as gas and electricity continued to increase at historic rates. As measured by the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH), the annual inflation rate fell slightly to 8.9% in March 2023. That was a slightly lower rate of increase compared with the 9.2% rise recorded in the 12 months to February 2023, but was still high compared with recent years. One of the main factors behind the slowing annual inflation rate was a drop in the price of motor fuels, which fell by 5.9% in the year to March 2023, compared with a rise of 4.6% in February. Despite the slowing of the overall annual rate, food and non-alcoholic drink prices still rose by 19.2% in the year to March 2023, up from 18.2% in February. The latest figure is the highest increase observed for over 45 years. Electricity and gas prices also rose by 66.7% and 129.4%, respectively, in the year to March 2023 (unchanged from February). These prices were also among the main drivers of inflation. Read our latest Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top House price growth slows while private rents see record rises 19 April 2023 Annual growth in UK house prices has continued to slow, as the average cost of a home fell for the third consecutive month in February 2023. Average house prices in the UK increased by 5.5% in the year to February 2023, down from 6.5% in the year to January 2023. The average price of a house was £288,000, which is £16,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £5,000 less than in November 2022. House prices grew the least in Scotland at a rate of 1.0% in the year to February 2023. This was lower than all English regions and lower than the overall rate seen across England (6.0%). Of all English regions, London saw the lowest annual growth in house prices (2.9%) and the West Midlands saw the highest (8.6%). Meanwhile, private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 4.9% in the 12 months to March 2023. This is the eleventh consecutive month of record-breaking growth in UK rental prices. Private rent prices rose 4.6% in England, 4.4% in Wales and 5.1% in Scotland in the year to March 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since January 2006 in England, since January 2010 in Wales, and since January 2012 in Scotland. Rental prices in London rose 4.8% in the year to March 2023. This is the biggest annual percentage change in London since December 2012. Rental prices have increased more in England and Northern Ireland than in Wales and Scotland since 2015 Index of Private Housing Rental Prices indices for countries of the UK, January 2015 to March 2023 Source: Index of Private Housing Rental Prices from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Rental prices have increased more in England and Northern Ireland than in Wales and Scotland since 2015 Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">94005360</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 09:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Business conditions remain challenging but signs of improvement </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators20april2023</link>
         <description>Business conditions remain challenging but signs of improvement 20 April 2023 Business conditions remain difficult but the proportion of UK businesses reporting higher prices when purchasing goods and services continued to fall in March 2023. Almost two in five (38%) trading businesses reported an increase in the prices of goods or services bought in March 2023 compared with February 2023. However, the proportion of businesses reporting higher prices compared with the previous month has steadily fallen from a peak of 48% in September 2022. These estimates from the Business Insights and Conditions Survey show small signs of positive improvement, but it is too early to know if this is the start of a longer-term change in conditions. When asked in early April 2023, nearly a quarter (23%) of trading businesses reported they expect to raise their prices in May 2023, while more than half (53%) expect the prices of goods or services they sell to stay the same. In early April 2023, more than half (53%) of businesses with 10 or more employees reported their staffing costs had increased in the last three months; in comparison, 58% reported they expect their staffing costs to increase over the next three months, higher than the 52% of businesses that expected higher costs when asked in early January 2023. Read our Business insights and impact on the UK economy: 20 April 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Rent now less affordable than in 2019 20 April 2023 Rent is now less affordable than it was in 2019, according to new data from Dataloft, but has been broadly stable for the last two years. The average proportion of gross income spent on rent in the UK was 26.8% in March 2023, a ratio comparable with March 2022. This figure shows that there has been an increase of 1.8 percentage points in the average proportion of gross income spent on rent since 2019. The proportion of income spent on rent in March 2023 remained broadly stable, increasing by 0.2 percentage points when compared with March 2022 Median percentage of gross income spent on rent, UK, January 2019 to March 2023 Source: Dataloft Rental Market Analytics Download this chart The proportion of income spent on rent in March 2023 remained broadly stable, increasing by 0.2 percentage points when compared with March 2022 Image .csv .xls This new indicator uses data from Dataloft. They are a housing market economics consultancy that hold the UK’s largest dataset of rents achieved and renter demographics, covering around 40% of all private rentals in the UK. An affordability ratio is a measure of how much of their income a renter spends on their rent. If the percentage increases, it reflects a worsening of affordability. Read our full bulletin on Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 20 April 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">35230452</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 09:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Half of British adults worried about cost of energy and food </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainmarch2023</link>
         <description>Half of British adults worried about cost of energy and food 21 April 2023 Around half of British adults say they have worried about the cost of energy and food in recent weeks. That is according to our latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey, which asked people what issues they had worried about in the past fortnight. The most-reported problems were the cost of energy (49%) and cost of food (49%), according to responses collected between 5 and 16 April 2023. People living in the most-deprived areas in England were more likely to report such concerns. Among those living in the most-deprived fifth of areas in England, 64% said they had been worried about the cost of food and 60% about the cost of energy. This was compared with 40% and 42%, respectively, in the least-deprived fifth of areas in the country. Estimates by deprivation are provided for England only. This is because of the smaller sample sizes from the survey in Scotland and Wales. The cost of energy and food are the most common concerns Proportion of all adults in Great Britain, 5 to 16 April 2023 Source: Opinions and Lifestyle Survey from the Office for National Statistics Notes: Question: &quot; Which of the following issues, if any, have you been worried about in the past two weeks?&quot;. Base: all adults. Respondents were able to choose more than one option. 15% of adults reported that they have not been worried about any issues in the past two weeks. This has not been included in the chart because respondents who selected this response option were unable to select any other response option. Download this chart The cost of energy and food are the most common concerns Image .csv .xls Around two in five British adults (39%) also said they had been affected by industrial action in the last month, which was up from 27% in the previous survey period (22 March to 2 April 2023). This coincided with industrial action taken by NHS workers in England and civil servants in His Majesty’s Passport Office. Read our full Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 5 to 16 April 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Retail sales volumes fall by 0.9% 21 April 2023 Retail sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought) are estimated to have fallen by 0.9% in March 2023. The retail sales volume fall follows a rise of 1.1% in February 2023 and 1.2% in January, meaning that the broader picture shows sales volumes rising by 0.6% in the three months to March 2023 when compared with the three previous months. This has been the first three-month on three-month rise since August 2021. Non-food store sales volumes fell by 1.3% in March 2023, following a rise of 2.4% in February. Food store sales volumes fell by 0.7% in March 2023, following a rise of 0.6% in February 2023. Non-store retailing, the majority of which are online stores, saw sales volumes fall by 0.8% in March 2023, which followed a rise of 0.3% in February 2023. Meanwhile, automotive fuel sales volumes rose by 0.2% in March 2023 following a fall of 1.2% in February 2023. Fuel sales remain at 8.5% below their pre coronavirus (COVID-19) February 2020 levels. Retail sales in March 2023 were impacted by falls in non-food stores sales volumes Contribution to monthly growth, volume seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, March 2023 compared with February 2023 Source: Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry from the Office for National Statistics Notes: Individual contributions may not sum to the total because of rounding. Download this chart Retail sales in March 2023 were impacted by falls in non-food stores sales volumes Image .csv .xls Read our full Retail sales; Great Britain: March 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">53711160</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 09:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
