<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>UK business investment revised up in April to June 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/businessinvestment/latest</link>
         <description>UK business investment revised up in April to June 2023 29 September 2023 UK business investment increased by 4.1% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023, revised up from the provisional estimate of 3.4% growth. This reflects upwards revisions to investments in transport, intellectual property products (IPP), and information and communication technology (ICT) and other machinery and equipment. Business investment has grown by 9.2% compared with the same quarter a year ago. Whole economy investment (technically known as gross fixed capital formation), which includes investment by business and public sector investment, increased by 0.8% in Quarter 2 2023. This was revised up from the provisional estimate of 0.0% growth. The largest contribution to growth in the latest quarter came from transport, with a smaller positive contribution coming from intellectual property products. Business investment, after lagging behind whole economy investment for much of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic and the period after, is now closing the gap. Business investment continued to grow at a faster rate than gross fixed capital formation (GFCF) in Q2 2023 UK business investment and whole economy investment, chained volume measure, seasonally adjusted, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 1997 to Quarter 2 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: Q1 refers to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar), Q2 refers to Quarter 2 (Apr to June), Q3 refers to Quarter 3 (July to Sept) and Q4 refers to Quarter 4 (Oct to Dec). UK business investment, chained volume measure, seasonally adjusted, excluding the reclassification of British Nuclear Fuels (BNFL) in Quarter 2 2005. Quarter 2 2020 was the largest fall on record for gross fixed capital formation, excluding the reclassification of British Nuclear Fuels in Quarter 2 2005. Index is referenced to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar), 1997 = 100. Download the data .xlsx This release contains data that are consistent with the UK National Accounts (also known as the Blue Book 2023), which will be released on 31 October 2023. Data for all periods in this release are subject to revision in line with the National Accounts Revision Policy. Read the full bulletin on Business investment in the UK: April to June 2023 revised results 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">47939294</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.2% in August 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktradeaugust2023</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.2% in August 2023 12 October 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have grown by 0.2% in August 2023, following a fall of 0.6% in July 2023. Looking at the broader picture, GDP increased by 0.3% in the three months to August 2023, with growth in all sectors. Services output grew by 0.4% in August 2023, after a fall of 0.6% in July 2023, and was the main contributor to the growth in GDP in July. Output in consumer facing services fell by 0.6% in August 2023 following a fall of 0.2% in July. Production output fell by 0.7% in August 2023, following a fall of 1.1% in July 2023. The construction sector declined by 0.5% in August 2023, following a 0.4% decrease in July 2023. Services output was the main contributor to the growth in GDP in August 2023 Contributions to monthly GDP growth, August 2022 to August 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Services output was the main contributor to the growth in GDP in August 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our latest UK monthly GDP bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top Total imports of goods from the non-EU countries rose in August 12 October 2023 Total imports of goods in &quot;current prices&quot;, which are not adjusted for inflation, increased by £0.8 billion (1.7%) in August 2023. Imports from EU countries fell by £0.2 billion, while imports from non-EU countries rose by £1.0 billion. The rise in imports from non-EU countries was mainly the result of higher imports of oil and gas. After removing the effect of inflation by calculating &quot;chained volume measures&quot;, total goods imports decreased by £0.4 billion (1.1%) in August 2023. This was because imports from the EU fell by £0.7 billion (3.2%) while imports from non-EU countries rose by £0.3 billion (1.7%). Total exports of goods decreased by £0.7 billion (2.2%) in August 2023, because of a £0.7 billion fall in exports to non-EU countries, while exports to EU countries remained stable. After the effect of inflation is removed, total goods exports fell by £1.3 billion (4.6%) in August 2023. Exports to non-EU countries decreased by £1.0 billion (7.2%) and exports to EU countries fell by £0.2 billion (1.8%). The total trade in goods and services deficit narrowed by £3.5 billion to £10.4 billion in the three months to August 2023, as imports fell by more than exports. Imports from the non-EU countries increased in August 2023, while imports from the EU countries fell EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted, January 2020 to August 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. More details can be found in our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles . Read our latest UK trade release . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">74396931</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Annual inflation remains unchanged as fuel prices rise </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukseptember2023</link>
         <description>Annual inflation remains unchanged as fuel prices rise 18 October 2023 Annual inflation, which is the rate at which the price of goods and services is rising, remained unchanged in September 2023. This was according to both the Consumer Prices Index (CPI) and Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH). In the 12 months to September 2023, CPI rose by 6.7%, and CPIH rose by 6.3%. These were the same rates as the 12 months to August 2023. It follows three consecutive months of falls in the annual inflation rate. CPIH has been falling from a peak of 9.6% in October 2022, which was the highest rate in over 40 years, according to estimates . Rising motor fuel prices were one of the main factors keeping annual inflation high. Between August and September 2023, petrol prices rose by 5.1 pence per litre to 153.6, and diesel prices rose by 6.3 pence per litre to 157.4. In the same period last year, fuel prices fell by 8.7 pence per litre for petrol and 5.0 pence per litre for diesel. Read our full Consumer Price Inflation, UK, September 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">87306074</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Private rents rise at record pace while house price growth slows</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/indexofprivatehousingrentalprices/latest</link>
         <description>Private rents rise at record pace while house price growth slows 18 October 2023 Private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 5.7% (provisional estimate) in the year to September 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 5.6% in England, 6.9% in Wales and 6.0% in Scotland in the year to September 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices in England and Wales since records began (in January 2006 and January 2010, respectively). In Scotland, this is the joint-highest annual change in rental prices since records began in January 2012, alongside August 2023. Private rental prices in Northern Ireland rose by 9.3% in the year to July 2023. Private rental prices in London (which accounts for almost a third of UK rental expenditure, as shown in our Index of Private Housing Rental Prices, UK dataset ) increased by 6.2% in the 12 months to September 2023, up from an increase of 5.9% in the 12 months to August 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change in London since the series began in January 2006. Meanwhile, average UK house price annual inflation has continued to slow. The provisional estimate for the average price of a UK house was £291,000 in August 2023. This is little changed from the same month a year ago, but £9,000 above the recent low point in March 2023. This represents an average increase of 0.2% in the year to August 2023 (provisional estimate), down slightly from growth of 0.7% in the year to July 2023 (revised estimate). Average UK house prices grew 0.2% in the year to August 2023 Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to August 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices grew 0.2% in the year to August 2023 Image .csv .xls House prices in England were little changed in the year to August 2023 (0.0%). In Wales, prices fell by 0.1% over the same period, while in Scotland they rose by 1.1%. Average house prices in Northern Ireland rose by 2.7% in the year to Quarter 2 (Apr to Jun) 2023. Of the English regions, the North East saw the highest house price inflation in the year to August 2023 (3.6%), although house prices there remain the lowest of all English regions at £165,000. The East of England saw the lowest annual house price inflation of all English regions, with average prices falling by 1.6% in the year to August 2023. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">83859043</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Visits to UK close to pre-coronavirus pandemic levels</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/overseastravelandtourismprovisionalapriltojune2023</link>
         <description>Visits to UK close to pre-coronavirus pandemic levels 19 October 2023 Visits to the UK by overseas residents between April and June 2023 reached a level close to that seen before the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Overseas residents made an estimated 9.9 million visits to the UK during April to June 2023, which was around 5% lower than the 10.4 million visits recorded during the same period of 2019. Holidays were the most popular reason for the visits (4.4 million), followed by visiting friends or relatives (3.1 million). The number of visits UK residents made abroad between April and June 2023 remained below pre-coronavirus pandemic levels. They made an estimated 23.4 million visits overseas over the period, which was 9% below the 25.8 million visits made in 2019. Read our latest Overseas travel and tourism bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88775156</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Cost of living crisis continues to damage retail sales </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Cost of living crisis continues to damage retail sales 20 October 2023 The cost of living crisis and its effect on shoppers has seen reduced spending at shops in Great Britain. Retail sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought), have fallen 0.9% in September 2023, following a rise of 0.4% the previous month. Despite the small growth in August 2023, sales volumes in the three months to September 2023 were down 0.8% compared with the previous quarter. Non-food stores saw some of the biggest drops in retail sales (1.9%) in September 2023. Shops reported that the pressures of the cost of living crisis, as well as September’s heatwave reducing sales of autumn clothing, contributed to a poor month. Similarly, non-store retailing (mostly online shops) saw a decline in sales volumes of 2.2% in September 2023. This follows a drop of 0.9% in August 2023. Despite the overall monthly decline, some sectors did experience an increase in sales volumes. Food stores saw a 0.2% increase in September 2023, following a 1.4% rise the previous month. Automotive fuel sales also partially bounced back from a 1.0% fall in August 2023 to a 0.8% rise last month. When compared with their pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) level in February 2020, total retail sales were 17.1% higher in value terms, but volumes were 2.5% lower. Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Volume and value sales, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, September 2019 to September 2023 Download this chart Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Image .csv .xls Read our Retail Sales, Great Britain: August 2023 full bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top Public sector borrowing fell in September 2023 20 October 2023 The public sector borrowed £1.6 billion less in September 2023 than it did a year earlier – the first year-on-year fall in borrowing in any month since September 2022. However, it still spent more than it received in taxes and other income, requiring it to borrow £14.3 billion. While growth in central government tax receipts has been slowing in recent months, it remains stronger than in the years running up to the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Inflation (the rate at which the price of goods and services rise) continues to put upward pressure on public spending. September saw increases for central government pay and procurement, along with uprated benefit payments. However, the interest payable on central government’s outstanding debt reduced by £7.2 billion compared with September last year. This was the third-lowest amount in any single month since monthly records began in 1997. Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">47464588</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Half of adults say cost of living has risen in last month </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain4to15october2023</link>
         <description>Half of adults say cost of living has risen in last month 20 October 2023 More than half (52%) of adults across Great Britain say that their cost of living has increased compared with a month ago. This is according to those asked between 4 and 15 October 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin. However, that was down from 79% among those asked during a similar period one year ago (29 September to 9 October 2022). Despite the drop, 90% said the cost of living was an important issue facing the UK today, a higher percentage than those citing the NHS, the economy, climate change and the environment, or housing. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">91085959</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Lowest rents not affordable for lowest income households </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/housing/bulletins/privaterentalaffordabilityengland/latest</link>
         <description>Lowest rents not affordable for lowest income households 23 October 2023 Lower-priced private rents were not affordable for households on lower incomes, according to our latest bulletin on private rental affordability. For households on the lower 25% of incomes, the cheapest 25% of private rents equalled more than 30% of their household income in the year to March 2022. This was the case in England, Wales and Northern Ireland. An area’s rents are not considered affordable if privately-renting households would have to spend more than 30% of their income on rent. For median and higher-income households, rents were more affordable, and below the 30% threshold. Private renters on median household incomes in England could expect to spend 26% of their income on rent. In Wales, they could expect to spend 23% and in Northern Ireland the figure was 25%. Average rents sat below the 30% of income threshold in all English regions apart from London, where the median rents were 35% of the median private-renting household income. Read the full Private rental affordability, England, Wales and Northern Ireland: 2022 bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">47943346</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
