<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>UK real GDP showed no growth in the third quarter of 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpfirstquarterlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>UK real GDP showed no growth in the third quarter of 2023 10 November 2023 The first quarterly estimate for Quarter 3 (July to Sept) 2023 shows the UK economy was broadly unchanged following modest growth of 0.2% in the previous quarter. Real gross domestic product (GDP) is a measure of the value of all goods and services produced in the UK after adjusting for price changes over time. GDP growth continued to slow in the most recent quarter UK, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2022 to Quarter 3 (July to Sept) 2023 Source: GDP first quarterly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart GDP growth continued to slow in the most recent quarter Image .csv .xls Following no growth in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023, service sector output decreased by 0.1% in Quarter 3 2023 driven by falls of 0.4% and 1.2% in real estate activities, and transportation and storage, respectively. There was no growth in production output in Quarter 3 2023, despite a 0.1% increase in manufacturing. Elsewhere, construction output rose by 0.1%. Growth in the volume of net trade (defined by the difference in exported and imported goods and services) was offset by falls in business investment (down 4.2%), household spending (down 0.4%) and government consumption (down 5.0%) in the most recent quarter. Business investment fell by 4.2% in the latest quarter following growth of 4.1% in Quarter 2 2023 because of increases in transport investment, especially in aircraft imports from the United States in April 2023. Households reduced their spending in the three months to September 2023, in particular their spending on “miscellaneous” goods and services (such as jewellery, clocks and watches), air and water transport, and food and non- alcoholic drink. Government consumption fell on the quarter, mainly reflecting lower spending on health and education. Read our latest bulletin on UK quarterly GDP. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">32685728</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Alternative measures to GDP to measure economic welfare </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/grossdomesticproductandwelfare</link>
         <description>Alternative measures to GDP to measure economic welfare 13 November 2023 While gross domestic product (GDP) is typically viewed as a way of measuring production and productivity, its limitations as a measure of welfare or wellbeing are widely known. There are two alternative measures of economic activity which are based on GDP but give more significance to welfare. These measures provide additional insights into the changing UK economy that are not fully captured in GDP. The first, real gross domestic income (GDI), is a measure of the purchasing power of GDP, reflecting how movements in the terms of trade can impact a nation’s ability to consume in world markets. Despite a deterioration in the UK’s terms of trade in the last two years following a strong rise in global energy and commodity prices, over the longer term the UK has benefitted from an improvement in its terms of trade. The second, real income, is a measure that is linked to the level of sustainable consumption, namely the income generated by a country that can be used to fund current and future consumption opportunities. This measure has often diverged from real GDP, suggesting the growth in UK welfare is not always in line with the volume of output or production. Real GDI has generally grown faster than real GDP, but real income has grown relatively slower Real gross domestic product (GDP), real gross domestic income (GDI) and real income (1987 = 100), UK, 1987 to 2022 Source: UK National Accounts, The Blue Book 2023 from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Real GDI has generally grown faster than real GDP, but real income has grown relatively slower Image .csv .xls Read our full Gross Domestic Product and Welfare article 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">68035002</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Real terms pay continues to rise as vacancies keep falling</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/uklabourmarket/latest</link>
         <description>Real terms pay continues to rise as vacancies keep falling 14 November 2023 Annual pay growth in real terms (adjusted for inflation) across Great Britain rose on the year by 1.4% for total pay (including bonuses) and 1.3% for regular pay (excluding bonuses), respectively, according to the latest data from the UK Labour Market Survey. By contrast, annual growth for regular pay (not adjusted for inflation) was 7.7% in July to September 2023. Though slightly lower than previous periods, this remains one of the highest annual growth rates since comparable records began in 2001. Estimated UK job vacancies fell in August to October 2023 for the 16th consecutive period, dropping by 58,000 vacancies to 957,000 on the quarter. This represents a decrease of 5.7% since May to July 2023 across 16 of the 18 industry sectors. Read more in our latest UK labour market bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">12162631</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House prices appear to fall while private rents see record rises </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukoctober2023</link>
         <description>House prices appear to fall while private rents see record rises 15 November 2023 Average UK house prices are estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in the 12 months to September 2023 (provisional estimate). This is down from an increase of 0.8% in the 12 months to August 2023 (revised estimate). The average UK house price was £291,000 in September 2023 (provisional), which is little changed from a year earlier, but above the recent low in March 2023. Average UK house prices were little changed in the 12 months to September 2023 (provisional estimate) Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to September 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices were little changed in the 12 months to September 2023 (provisional estimate) Image .csv .xls Average house prices are estimated to have fallen in England and Wales in the year to September 2023 (by 0.5% and 2.7%, respectively), while in Scotland house prices rose by 2.5% over the same period. In Northern Ireland, average house prices rose by 2.1% in the year to quarter 3 (July to September) 2023. It’s important to note that our provisional house price estimates are based on smaller data volumes than usual, meaning that future revisions to these figures may be larger than usual. For more information please see our full UK House Price Index bulletin . Private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 6.1% in the year to October 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 6.0% in England, 6.9% in Wales and 6.2% in Scotland in the year to October 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since records began (January 2006 for England, January 2010 for Wales, and January 2012 for Scotland). Private rental prices in London (which accounts for almost a third of UK rental expenditure ) increased by 6.8% in the 12 months to July 2023, the highest of any English region. This is the highest annual percentage change in London since the series began in January 2006.  The North East saw the lowest increase in rental prices, at 4.7% in the year to October 2023. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top Inflation falls to lowest level in almost two years 15 November 2023 The rate at which prices of goods and services are rising has fallen to the lowest level since November 2021, according to the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH) . Annual CPIH inflation, rose by 4.7% in the year to October 2023, down from 6.3% in September. CPIH inflation has fallen from a recent peak of 9.6% in October 2022, which was the highest in over 40 years according to indicative estimates . Some of the main downward effects on inflation came from housing and household services, particularly gas and electricity prices. Gas prices fell 31.0% in the year to October 2023, while electricity prices fell by 15.6%. These are the lowest annual inflation rates for gas and electricity since records began in January 1989. Energy prices remain high, however. The price of gas in October 2023 was around 60% higher than two years previously, while the price of electricity was 40% higher. Read our full Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">21491861</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Sales volumes at lowest levels in over two years </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainoctober2023</link>
         <description>Sales volumes at lowest levels in over two years 17 November 2023 Retail sales in Great Britain have fallen to the lowest levels since February 2021, when lockdown restrictions were still in place. Sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought) dropped by 0.3% in October 2023 following a revised drop of 1.1% the previous month, falling to the lowest level in more than two years, when restrictions on non-essential retail were still in place across the country. Automotive fuel sales fell by 2.0% in October 2023, sinking to the lowest level since March 2021. Retailers reported that the drop could be because drivers are being more cautious with money this month. The steady rise of fuel prices since July 2023 could also be a factor. Sales volumes at non-food stores fell by 0.2% in October 2023 following a 2.1% drop the previous month. Poor weather and reduced footfall were seen as potential causes by retailers. Meanwhile, non-store retailers (mostly online shops) saw a 0.8% rise in sales this month after a 2.4% decrease in September 2023. When compared with their pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic level in February 2020, total retail sales were 16.9% higher in value terms, but volumes were 3.1% lower. Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Volume and value sales, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, October 2019 to October 2023 Source: Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Image .csv .xls Read our full Retail sales, Great Britain: October 2023 release bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">18460332</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Ethnicity pay gaps remain large between Black British employees and White employees</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/ethnicitypaygapsuk2012to2022</link>
         <description>Ethnicity pay gaps remain large between Black British employees and White employees 29 November 2023 Black, African, Caribbean or Black British workers consistently earned less than their White counterparts over an 11-year period. The Annual Population Survey revealed that between 2012 and 2022, White employees earned £14.35 per hour (median gross hourly pay), while Black, African, Caribbean or Black British workers earned £13.53 per hour – 82 pence less. Between 2012 and 2022, they were the only ethnicity group to consistently earn less than White employees. Black, African, Caribbean or Black British employees consistently earned less than White employees between 2012 and 2022 Raw pay gaps, five-category ethnicity, United Kingdom, 2012 to 2022 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Analysis also revealed that country of birth affected how much employees earned. UK-born Black, African, Caribbean or Black British employees earn more (£15.18) , while non-UK-born Black British employees earned less (£12.95) when compared with UK-born White employees (£14.26). When controlling for pay-determining characteristics, to provide an adjusted pay gap based on a like-for-like comparison, we see the pay gap narrow and, in some, instances, reverse. For example, UK-born Black, African, Caribbean or Black British employees, went from earning 6.5% more to earning 5.6% less compared with White employees. With the declining sample of the Annual Population Survey (APS) and increased uncertainty since 2020, estimates covering the period 2020 to 2022 should be used with caution. This analysis predates the latest issues with the Labour Force Survey (LFS) data . Read our bulletin, Ethnicity pay gaps, UK: 2012 to 2022 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">13340266</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Black Friday gives boost to retail spending </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators1december2023</link>
         <description>Black Friday gives boost to retail spending 1 December 2023 Spending on debit cards in the UK, as measured by Revolut , rose by 9% in the week to 26 November, compared with the week before. The largest increase was in “retail”, with spending up 17%. This is in line with expected Black Friday weekend and pre-Christmas spending patterns. Total Revolut debit card spending is 6% higher than the level seen in the equivalent week in 2022. Five of the six spending sectors increased in this time, with ”food and drink” reporting the largest increase of 11%. Spending in ”pubs, restaurants, and fast food” fell by 3% when compared with the equivalent week of 2022. Read our latest Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">79186679</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Renters and parents more likely to report running out of food </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/impactofincreasedcostoflivingonadultsacrossgreatbritainjulytooctober2023</link>
         <description>Renters and parents more likely to report running out of food 4 December 2023 People with children and those living in rented accommodation are among groups more likely to report a range of impacts from cost-of-living pressures, such as running out of food. Between 12 July and 1 October 2023, 8% of parents living with a dependent child reported running out of food and being unable to afford more, compared with 5% of adults overall. Among renters, 13% reported running out of food. Among parents of dependent children who were also renters, one in five (21%) reported running out of food before they could afford to buy more. Lone parents were also particularly likely to be affected: 61% of lone adults living with at least one dependent child reported difficulty affording their rent or mortgage payments, compared with 40% of all adults making such payments. Difficulty affording rent and mortgage payments was also more common among Asian and Asian British adults (56%), and Black, African, Caribbean or Black British adults (51%). Around 3 in 10 adults (29%) said they would not be able to afford an unexpected expense of £850 or more. This rose to 40% of disabled adults and 53% of renters. Among disabled adults who were renters, two-thirds (66%) reported being unable to afford such an expense. Read our full Impacts of increased cost of living on adults across Great Britain: July to October 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">58735489</guid>
         <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 09:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
