<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Fuel imports from non-EU countries fell for third month in a row</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktradenovember2022</link>
         <description>

Fuel imports from non-EU countries fell for third month in a row13 January 2023Gas prices continued to decrease in November 2022, leading to the third consecutive month of decreases in the value of fuel imports to the UK from non-EU countries. However, the overall value of goods imports to the UK increased by £1.8 billion (3.5%). Goods imports from EU countries increased by £1.2 billion (4.7%) and imports from non-EU countries rose by £0.6 billion (2.2%), both driven by rising imports of machinery and transport equipment. When removing the effect of inflation, total imports of goods increased by £2.5 billion (6.1%) in November 2022. This was because of a £1.3 billion (7.0%) increase in imports from non-EU countries, and a £1.2 billion (5.3%) increase in imports from the EU. Total exports of goods increased slightly by £0.2 billion (0.7%) in November 2022, with an increase in exports to non-EU countries partially offset by falling exports to the EU. The decrease in exports to the EU was driven by a £0.4 billion fall in fuel exports. When removing the effect of inflation, total exports of goods increased by £0.5 billion (1.7%) in November 2022. Exports to non-EU countries increased by £0.6 billion (4.6%) while exports to the EU fell by £0.2 billion (1.2%). The trade in goods and services deficit, excluding precious metals, narrowed by £6.5 billion to £20.2 billion in the three months to November 2022. This was driven by a decrease in goods imports from non-EU countries, which is linked to falling fuel prices. Imports of goods from both EU and non-EU countries rose in November 2022EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, November 2019 to November 2022


Embed code

Embed this interactive


Copy





Notes:

Caution should be taken when interpreting these data as there is a discontinuity from January 2021 in EU trade following an HM Revenue and Customs data collection change. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics article provides more detail.
Download the data

Read our latest UK Trade bulletin.
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">7317058</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have grown 0.1% in November 2022 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpmonthlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>

UK GDP estimated to have grown 0.1% in November 2022 13 January 2023Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have grown 0.1% in November 2022, following growth of 0.5% in October 2022. Looking at the broader picture, UK GDP fell by 0.3% in the three months to November 2022 compared with the three months to August 2022. Services grew by 0.2% in November 2022, after an increase of 0.7% in October 2022. The largest contribution to the growth came from administrative and support activities, which grew by 2.0% in November 2022, following growth of 1.7% in October 2022. Production output fell by 0.2% in November 2022, after a fall of 0.1% in October 2022 . The fall of 0.5% in manufacturing was the largest contributor to the production sector’s negative growth. Construction saw no growth in November 2022, following an increase of 0.4% in October 2022. 

Services was the main contributor to positive monthly GDP growth in November 2022 
Contributions to monthly GDP growth, November 2021 to November 2022, UK 







Source: Office for National Statistics – GDP monthly estimate 


Download this chart Services was the main contributor to positive monthly GDP growth in November 2022 
Image

.csv


.xls



Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP.
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">85651678</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>A fifth of adults say travel plans affected by rail strikes </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain21december2022to8january2023</link>
         <description>

A fifth of adults say travel plans affected by rail strikes 13 January 2023Around 1 in 5 adults across Great Britain said their travel plans in the previous two weeks had been disrupted by rail strikes. That is according to data collected between 21 December 2022 and 8 January 2023 from the Opinions and Lifestyle Survey, which covers the period of industrial action on the rail network in the lead-up to, and after, Christmas. The survey also reveals around 9 in 10 adults (92%) reported the cost of living as an important issue facing the UK today. More than 8 in 10 (85%) said the NHS was an important issue, up from 81% among those surveyed between 7 and 18 December 2022. That was followed by 75% who cited the economy, while 58% said climate change. 

The cost of living was the most frequently cited concern 
Proportion of all adults in Great Britain, 21 December 2022 to 8 January 2023







Source: Office for National Statistics (ONS) - Opinions and Lifestyle Survey (OPN)


Download this chart The cost of living was the most frequently cited concern 
Image

.csv


.xls


The survey also revealed around two-thirds (65%) of adults have reported they are spending less on non-essentials because of the rising cost of living, while around 4 in 10 adults (41%) reported spending less on food shopping and essentials. That was down from 46% among those asked between 22 November and 4 December 2022. However, it was still far higher than the 25% who said the same when the question was first asked between 15 December 2021 and 3 January 2022. 

Read our latest bulletin on Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">55782062</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Real value of pay continues to fall </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uklabourmarketjanuary2023</link>
         <description>

Real value of pay continues to fall 17 January 2023Regular pay for UK employees fell at near-record levels in the three months to November 2022 after accounting for the rising cost of living. Average regular pay (excluding bonuses) among employees grew 6.4% in September to November 2022, which is the strongest growth rate seen outside the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. The private sector saw growth of 7.2%, while it rose by 3.3% in the public sector. After adjusting for inflation (the rising cost of goods and services), however, pay fell in real terms over the year by 2.6%, which is among the largest drops since records began in 2001. The number of vacancies across the UK in October to December 2022 also fell by 75,000, to 1,161,000, which survey respondents say reflects economic pressures. Although that means there have been six quarterly (three-month period) falls in a row, the number of vacancies remains at historically high levels. The redundancy rate also increased to 3.4 per 1,000 employees in September to November 2022 but remains low. Economic inactivity (people not working nor seeking work) fell very slightly in the last quarter (September to November 2022), although 21.5% of those aged 16 to 64 years in the UK were still classed as economically inactive. 

Read our Labour market overview, UK: January 2023
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">5781872</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Inflation continues to ease from record highs </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukdecember2022</link>
         <description>

Inflation continues to ease from record highs 18 January 2023The annual inflation rate in the UK has continued to ease from 40-year highs, driven by lower rises in motor fuel prices. This was partially offset by higher rises in prices for passenger travel, notably for air travel, which reached record highs. In the year to December 2022, the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupier’s housing costs (CPIH) rose by 9.2%, down from 9.3% in November and 9.6% in October. Indicative modelled estimates suggest that the October rate was the highest rate in over 40 years. In the most recent month however, the CPIH annual rate was equal to the rate recorded just over 30 years earlier, between September and December 1990. The Consumer Prices Index (CPI) rose by 10.5% in the 12 months to December 2022, down from 10.7% in November and 11.1% in October. These falls were driven by lower inflation in transport, notably for motor fuels. The annual CPIH inflation rate for transport was 6.9% in December 2022, down for a sixth consecutive month from a peak of 15.2% in June 2022, and the lowest rate since May 2021. 

Transport inflation eased in December 2022 
CPIH, transport and motor fuels annual inflation rates, UK, December 2012 to December 2022 







Source: Office for National Statistics – Consumer price inflation


Download this chart Transport inflation eased in December 2022 
Image

.csv


.xls


The easing in motor fuels inflation in December 2022 was partially offset by annual price rises of 11.3% for passenger transport by road (largely because of coach fares) and 44.1% for passenger transport by air. The annual inflation rate for passenger transport by air of 44.1% is the largest recorded rate for this class in the national statistic series, which begins in January 2006, and in the constructed series, which begins in January 1989. 

Read our latest Consumer Prices Index bulletin
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">45878293</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rental price rises break records as house price growth slows </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/indexofprivatehousingrentalpricesukdecember2022</link>
         <description>

Rental price rises break records as house price growth slows 18 January 2023Private rental prices rose at record rates in all UK countries in the year to December 2022. Overall, private rental prices in the UK increased 4.2% during that time, up from 4.0% in the year to November 2022. This is the eighth consecutive month of record-breaking growth in rental prices. In the year to December 2022, private rental prices rose in England by 4.1% and in Wales by 3.5%. These were the largest increases recorded since the data series began in each of these countries in 2006 and 2010, respectively. Rental prices in Scotland grew by 4.4% in the year to December 2022, remaining at the record high set last month. 

Private rental prices continue to rise faster in Scotland than England and Wales 
Index of Private Housing Rental Prices percentage change over 12 months for countries of the UK, January 2012 to December 2022 







Source: Office for National Statistics – Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 


Download this chart Private rental prices continue to rise faster in Scotland than England and Wales 
Image

.csv


.xls


UK house price annual growth slowed in the year to November 2022, slowing to 10.3% from 12.4% in October 2022. The average UK house price was £295,000, which is £28,000 higher than the average price in November 2021. Of all English regions, annual house price percentage change in the year to November 2022 was highest in the North West (13.5%) and lowest in London (6.3%). Although London experienced the lowest annual percentage change of all English regions in the year to November 2022, Scotland experienced lower annual growth for the same period. Average house prices in Scotland increased by 5.5% in the year to November 2022, about half the growth rate of all other UK nations. Average house price growth in Scotland has generally slowed since April 2022. 

Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices
🠕 Back to the top 


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">66946553</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Spending on debit cards continues to fall </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators19january2023</link>
         <description>

Spending on debit cards continues to fall 19 January 2023Debit card spending in the UK fell by 3 percentage points in the week to 15 January 2022, according to data from Revolut. The most notable category to see a drop in spending was “automotive fuel”, which saw the largest decrease of 19 percentage points. This category was 59 percentage points below the peak level reported for this category in mid-August 2022, coinciding with recent falls in the price of road fuel. Spending on “entertainment” and “pubs, restaurants and fast food” also continued to fall, decreasing by 8 percentage points and 7 percentage points, respectively, in line with usual seasonal reductions in consumer demand. However, spending in all categories was above the level reported in the equivalent period of the previous year. Spending in the “retail” category was 38 percentage points above the equivalent level of 2022. Users should note that these data are not adjusted for the potential effects of inflation on the value of transactions.

Read our latest Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">1411301</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Volume of sales fell again in December 2022 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritaindecember2022</link>
         <description>

Volume of sales fell again in December 2022 20 January 2023Retail sales volumes (quantity bought) fell by 1.0% in December 2022, following a fall of 0.5% in November. December’s drop took sales volumes to 1.7% below the pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) level of February 2020. However, in terms of value spent, retail sales had risen 13.6% over the same period. 

Retail sales volumes and values diverge 
Retail sales volume and value, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, December 2019 to December 2022







Source: Office for National Statistics – Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry


Download this chart Retail sales volumes and values diverge 
Image

.csv


.xls


The volume sold at food stores fell by 0.3% in December 2022, after a rise of 1.0% in November, when customers may have stocked up early for Christmas. The latest decline continues a downward trend since the lifting of restrictions on hospitality in summer 2021. The volume sold at non-food stores fell by 2.1% in December 2022. Department stores’ sales volumes fell by 3.1% after a rise of 2.1% in November when retailers reported longer Black Friday sales. Other non-food stores reported a monthly fall in sales volumes of 6.2% because of strong falls in cosmetics stores, sports equipment, games and toys stores and watches and jewellery stores. 

Read our full bulletin about Retail sales; Great Britain
🠕 Back to the top


</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">5710714</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 09:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
