<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 09:15:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows as private rents rise at record rate</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukfebruary2023</link>
         <description>House price growth slows as private rents rise at record rate 22 March 2023 Growth in UK house prices continued to slow in the year to January 2023. During that time, average house prices in the UK increased by 6.3%, down from 9.3% in December 2022. The average price of a house was £290,000, which is £17,000 higher than the same month a year ago. House prices grew the least in Scotland at a rate of 1.0%, which was lower than all English regions and was lower than the rates seen across England (6.9%) and Wales (5.8%). North East house prices increased more than any other region All dwellings annual house price rates of change, by English region, year to January 2023 Source: HM Land Registry and UK House Price Index from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart North East house prices increased more than any other region Image .csv .xls Private rental prices continued to rise at record-setting paces in all countries in the 12 months to February 2023. The average price tenants paid for private rentals in the UK increased 4.7% during that time, up from 4.4% in the 12 months to January 2023. Rental prices in Scotland increased by 4.9%, up from 4.5% in the previous month and the highest rate since records began in 2012. England and Wales also saw record growth in private rental prices, at 4.5% and 4.2%, respectively. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top Housing affordability improves in 2022 amid longer-term decline 22 March 2023 Housing affordability improved in 2022, but over the past 25 years, affordability has worsened in every local authority across England and Wales. Affordability is calculated as the ratio of the average (median) house price to the average (median) yearly earnings in a given area. A lower ratio can be understood as greater affordability. Overall in England, a full-time employee in 2022 could typically expect to spend 8.3 times their annual earnings buying a home in the local authority in which they work, so the affordability ratio was 8.3. This is lower than the ratio of 9.1 recorded the previous year. In Wales, this ratio was 6.2, which is not statistically different from the previous year. In 2022, only 7% of local authorities in England and Wales had an affordability ratio below 5, down from 89% in 1997. Changes in house prices have been the primary driver of changing affordability. Although earnings have doubled in the past 25 years, house prices are 4.5 times higher. Affordability has worsened as house price inflation outpaced earnings growth House price and earnings indices, England and Wales, 1997 to 2022 Source: House Price Statistics for Small Areas and Annual Survey of Hours and Earnings from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Affordability has worsened as house price inflation outpaced earnings growth Image .csv .xls The worsening affordability is especially true in London, where no local authority has an affordability ratio below 10. This is contrasted with the North East, the only region where no local authority had an affordability ratio over 10. Read our full bulletin on Housing affordability in England and Wales: 2022 🠕 Back to the top Inflation rises but remains below October 2022 high 22 March 2023 The rate of rising prices paid by consumers for goods and services rose to levels seen around 30 years ago in the 12 months to February 2023 but remains below the recent October 2022 peak. As measured by the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH), the annual inflation rate rose to 9.2% in February 2023. This was up from 8.8% the previous month, but below a recent peak of 9.6% in October 2022. Since then, the annual inflation rate has fluctuated around 9.2%, a rate previously seen between September and December 1990. The reason for the rise in the annual inflation rate was a 1.0% rise in prices between January and February 2023, compared with 0.7% in the same period in 2022. Larger price rises in restaurants and hotels were some of the main reasons for the rise in the annual inflation rate. The annual inflation rate for restaurants and hotels was 12.1% in February 2023, up from 10.8% in January, and the highest rate since the constructed historical estimate of 12.1% in July 1991. Read our latest Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">73958092</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 09:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Drop in number of online job adverts</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators23march2023</link>
         <description>Drop in number of online job adverts 23 March 2023 The number of online job adverts fell in the week to 17 March 2023, continuing a general decline since early last year. The total number of online job adverts decreased by 2% compared with the previous week, according to data from search engine Adzuna, with the number of adverts declining in 24 of 28 job categories. The overall figure was also 14% lower than in the equivalent period of 2022. UK retail footfall (a measure of consumer activity) increased by 9% in the week to 19 March 2023, according to data from analytics firm Springboard, and was 4% above levels recorded during the equivalent week last year. However, it was still below the level recorded in the equivalent week of 2019. Figures from financial tech company Revolut show debit card spending in the week to 19 March 2023 was broadly similar to levels seen in the previous week, although it was higher than during the equivalent week of 2022. Retail spending was 35 percentage points higher than a year earlier, which was the largest annual increase of any sector. Read our Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 23 March 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">17651367</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 09:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Discount store sales help boost retail spending in February</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainfebruary2023</link>
         <description>Discount store sales help boost retail spending in February 24 March 2023 Retail sales volumes (the amount bought in shops) rose by 1.2% across Great Britain in February 2023, following a rise of 0.9% in January. However, these are down 3.5% on the same month last year, as volumes sold fell throughout 2022. The amount sold in non-food stores saw a rise of 2.4% in the month because of strong sales in discount department stores. Department store sales volumes rose 5.5%, and clothing stores rose by 2.9%. Food store sales volumes rose 0.9% in February 2023, which may be because of reduced spending in pubs and restaurants as people eat in more because of cost of living pressures. The amount spent in retail stores (values) rose by 1.6% between January and February 2023, as inflation has led to higher prices. While the amount bought in retail stores returned to pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic February 2020 levels in the latest month, the amount spent was 16.8% higher. Read our latest Retail Sales bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">76844984</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 09:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rising rent and mortgage costs leave households struggling</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/changesinprivaterentalsectorbehaviourenglandfebruary2022tofebruary2023</link>
         <description>Rising rent and mortgage costs leave households struggling 24 March 2023 More than a third of British adults paying rent or a mortgage say these costs have risen in the last six months, and around a third also say that they are struggling to afford them. Some 36% of adults making rent or mortgage payments said that these outgoings had increased over the last six months, according to our latest survey carried out between 8 and 19 March 2023. That is an increase of 7 percentage points from 29% when we first asked this question between 3 and 14 November 2021. Around a third (34%) of those making rent or mortgage payments also reported that they were finding it very or somewhat difficult to afford them, compared with 32% in the previous survey period (22 February to 5 March 2023). The latest survey was completed shortly before the Bank of England announced that it would raise its interest rate from 4% to 4.25%. The central bank’s decision is likely to lead to higher mortgage costs for some households and could also affect renters if buy-to-let landlords pass on higher costs to tenants. The survey also reveals around one in four adults (26%) experienced shortages of essential food items in the past two weeks. This was similar to 27% in the previous period (22 February to 5 March 2023) but well above the 16% recorded during a similar period a year earlier (3 to 13 March 2022). Our latest inflation data show prices of food and non-alcoholic drinks rose at the fastest rate in more than 45 years in the 12 months to February 2023. The largest contributor to the rise in food inflation was vegetables, following media reports of shortages of salad produce and other vegetables. Read our Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 8 to 19 March 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Private rental prices more likely to have increased in past year 24 March 2023 Rental prices increased for around half (50.6%) of privately rented properties in England revisited in February 2023 that had been visited within the previous 14 months. This was up from around 36% the previous year. London was the region where privately rented properties revisited in February 2023 were most likely to have experienced a price increase since the last visit, at 66.8%. This figure was lowest in the North West, at 27.9%. Two-thirds of privately rented properties in London experienced a price increase since their last visit Proportion of privately rented properties revisited in February 2023 that have experienced a price increase since last visit, English regions, February 2023 Source: Index of Private Housing Rental Prices from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Two-thirds of privately rented properties in London experienced a price increase since their last visit Image .csv .xls Among privately rented properties in England that did experience a price increase, the magnitude of the average price percentage rise was also generally larger in February 2023 than a year ago. This means that, on average, private rental prices of properties in England revisited in February 2023 had increased by 9.6% since the last visit. For almost 2 in 10 properties, rental prices had risen by at least 10%. London also saw the largest average rental price percentage increase of all regions, at 12.0% for properties revisited in February 2023. This is up substantially from the average 4.7% increase recorded for London properties revisited in February 2022, which was the lowest increase among English regions at that time. Read our full bulletin on Changes in private rental sector behaviour, England: February 2022 to February 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">4625780</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 09:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rapid growth in proportion of working age adults in employment</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/theemploymentpopulationratioandchangesintheuklabourmarket</link>
         <description>Rapid growth in proportion of working age adults in employment 28 March 2023 The employment-population (EPOP) ratio is the proportion of those aged 16 years and over in employment. It is an indicator of how well the economy is doing in creating jobs. In the period following the global financial crisis in 2008 and before the onset of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic in 2020, the EPOP ratio increased to its highest recorded level. Despite its recent fall following the pandemic, the latest EPOP ratio remains high relative to its historic rate. This is because recent increases in inactivity have not yet offset strongly rising activity rates in the decade leading up to the COVID-19 pandemic, particularly for men and women aged 50 years and over. Employment as a proportion of the adult population was the highest on record immediately before the COVID-19 pandemic The employment-population ratio (aged 16 years and over), UK, seasonally adjusted, February to April 1971 to November to January 2023 Source: Labour Force Survey from the Office for National Statistics Notes: The population totals used for the latest Labour Force Survey (LFS) estimates use projected growth rates from Real Time Information (RTI) data for UK, EU and non-EU populations based on 2021 patterns. The total population used for the LFS, therefore, does not consider any changes in migration, birth rates, or death rates since June 2021. As such, levels estimates may be under- or over-estimating the true values and should be used with caution. Estimates of rates will, however, be more robust. Download this chart Employment as a proportion of the adult population was the highest on record immediately before the COVID-19 pandemic Image .csv .xls Read our full bulletin on The employment-population ratio and changes in the UK labour market . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88040797</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 09:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around one in six adults classed as food insecure </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/theimpactofwinterpressuresondifferentpopulationgroupsingreatbritain15to26february2023</link>
         <description>Around one in six adults classed as food insecure 30 March 2023 Around one in six adults in Great Britain (16%) were classed as food insecure, according to new analysis of the Office for National Statistics' (ONS) winter panel survey data from 15 to 26 February 2023. Food security is a households' ability to get enough food to lead a healthy life. Food insecurity was most common among adults: with moderate-to-severe depressive symptoms (42%) not in work and not looking for work (&quot;economically inactive&quot;) and not retired (35%) living in the most deprived areas of England (31%) One of the indicators we use to measure food security is whether adults report cutting down portion sizes or skipping meals. Overall, 14% of adults reported doing this, but it was more common among adults with moderate-to-severe depressive symptoms (38%), living in the most deprived areas of England (27%), and with one or more dependent children (22%). The percentage of people in Great Britain who struggled to stay warm in their home dropped in the latest period, compared with responses collected in November and December 2022 (20% compared with 24% previously). This was possibly because of milder weather. Around 54% of adults said they were taking prescription medication. Among those who pay for their prescription, 10% reported taking less medication to save on prescription costs. Read our full bulletin on the impact of winter pressures on population groups in Great Britain . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">33299330</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 09:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
