<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Most businesses have not assessed key climate change risks</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy10august2023</link>
         <description>Most businesses have not assessed key climate change risks 10 August 2023 Three-quarters (75%) of UK businesses in our latest business insights survey said that they had not assessed the risks of certain climate change effects. These effects included water scarcity, coastal erosion, increased flooding and temperature increases. Our Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS) for late July 2023 does not cover all sectors of the economy so the results reflect only those surveyed. Of those businesses that had assessed these risks of climate change, 28% had not taken any action, 18% did not expect to be impacted, while 18% reported they had been unable to take action, either due to costs or the lack of information or guidance. Our survey also showed that in late July 2023, 21% of businesses reported that they were using, or intending to use, increased homeworking as a permanent business model, with reduced overheads (51%) and improved staff well-being (47%) reported as the main reasons. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88644194</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Large falls in imports from non-EU countries in June 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/balanceofpayments/bulletins/uktrade/latest</link>
         <description>Large falls in imports from non-EU countries in June 2023 11 August 2023 The value of goods imports decreased by £2.9 billion (5.8%) in June 2023, because of a large fall in imports from non-EU countries of £3.8 billion (15.9%). This was partially offset by a rise in imports from the EU of £0.8 billion (3.2%). The fall in imports from non-EU countries was the largest since April 2020. This was because of lower gas prices in June, which led to a fall in fuel imports from these countries of £2.1 billion (39.6%). The fall was £0.7 billion (20.0%) after adjusting for inflation. The total value of goods exports increased by £0.6 billion (1.8%) in June 2023 because of a £0.6 billion (3.8%) rise in exports to non-EU countries, while exports to the EU remained stable. The rise in exports to non-EU countries was mainly because of an increase in machinery and transport equipment. The total trade in goods and services deficit narrowed slightly by £0.5 billion to £19.0 billion in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 because of a larger fall in imports than exports. The total trade deficit has reduced steadily since Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2022 when it stood at £30.4 billion. A large fall in fuel imports contributed to a drop in imports of goods from non-EU countries in June 2023 EU and non-EU goods imports by commodity, current prices, seasonally adjusted, June 2021 to June 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. Read our latest UK trade bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">927974</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP rose by an estimated 0.2% in the second quarter of 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpfirstquarterlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>UK GDP rose by an estimated 0.2% in the second quarter of 2023 11 August 2023 The UK economy grew by an estimated 0.2% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023. The figure is a measure of real gross domestic product (GDP), which is the value of all goods and services produced in the UK after adjusting for price changes over time. Real GDP is estimated to have increased by 0.2% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 UK, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2022 to Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 Source: GDP first quarterly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Real GDP is estimated to have increased by 0.2% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 Image .csv .xls The service sector grew by 0.1% in Quarter 2 2023, with the largest positive contributors being information and communication, and hospitality. Elsewhere, production output increased by 0.7%, driven largely by growth in manufacturing, while construction output increased for the seventh consecutive quarter. Investment in information and communication technology (ICT) equipment and other machinery equipment declined on the quarter in response to the super-deduction allowance ending, which enabled companies to cut their tax bill by up to 25 pence for every £1 invested. Despite this, business investment overall increased on the quarter, along with strong growth in household and government consumption. Inflationary pressures remain high by historical standards as indicated by an increase of 7.4% in the implied price (a measure of price movements over time) of household expenditure in the year to June 2023. Early estimates show wages and salaries grew by 2.6% in Quarter 2 2023, reflecting rises in public sector earning, particularly hospital wages and salaries. Read our latest bulletin on UK quarterly GDP 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">48898779</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Almost half of rent or mortgage payers in Britain report a rise</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain26julyto6august2023</link>
         <description>Almost half of rent or mortgage payers in Britain report a rise 11 August 2023 Close to 4 in every 10 adults (38%) in Great Britain who pay for rent or a mortgage are finding it very or somewhat difficult to afford these payments. This is according to those asked between 26 July and 6 August 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . It was around 3 in 10 adults (29%) in early August 2022. Among those paying for rent or a mortgage, almost half (47%) reported their payments had gone up in the last six months. Over 5 in 10 adults (56%) reported that their cost of living had increased compared with a month ago, while 41% reported it had stayed the same and 2% said it had decreased. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">30529839</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Average pay continued to rise</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/uklabourmarket/latest</link>
         <description>Average pay continued to rise 15 August 2023 Average total pay (including bonuses) and regular pay (excluding bonuses) continued to rise in April to June 2023 compared with the previous year. This, coupled with a recent reduction in the rate of inflation, means that real wages (adjusted for inflation) are beginning to improve compared with recent months. According to the latest labour market data, average regular pay (excluding bonuses) for UK employees rose by 7.8% in April to June 2023 compared with the same period the previous year. This is the highest growth rate since 2001. Total pay (including bonuses) rose by 8.2%, although this was affected by one-off bonus payments made to NHS workers in June 2023. Real terms regular pay (adjusted for Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers' housing costs, or CPIH) rose by 0.1% and real terms total pay increased by 0.5% over the same period. Job vacancies continued to fall in May to July 2023, dropping by 66,000 to 1.020 million. The estimated number of vacancies fell on the quarter for the 13th consecutive period. The UK employment rate fell by 0.1 percentage points to 75.7% in April to June 2023, driven mainly by falls in full-time employees and self-employed workers. The UK unemployment rate increased by 0.3 percentage points to 4.2%. The economic inactivity rate (people not in work or looking for work) dropped by 0.1 percentage points, down to 20.9% during April to June 2023. This was largely driven by those who were inactive because they were looking after family or the home. Meanwhile, those inactive because of long-term sickness increased to a record high. There were 160,000 working days lost because of labour disputes in June 2023. Over half of these were in the health and social work sector. Read the full Labour Market Overview, UK: August 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">97675325</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Inflation falls to lowest rate since early 2022</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukjuly2023</link>
         <description>Inflation falls to lowest rate since early 2022 16 August 2023 The rate at which prices of goods and services are rising is at the lowest level since early 2022. In the year to July 2023, the inflation rate was 6.4%, down from 7.3% in June, according to the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH). This was the lowest rate since March 2022. Inflation continues a downward trend since its peak in October 2022, when the annual CPIH inflation rate was 9.6%, the highest in more than 40 years according to indicative estimates . Excluding owner occupiers’ housing costs, the Consumer Prices Index (CPI) was 6.8% in the year to July 2023, down from 7.9% in June. This was the lowest since February 2022. Falling gas and electricity prices were the main reason for the inflation rate falling. Between June and July 2023, gas prices fell by 25.2%, the largest monthly fall since at least 1988. Over the 12 months to July 2023, inflation for housing, water, electricity, gas and other fuels was 6.8%, down from a peak of 26.7% in January 2023. The recent fall was largely because of the lowering of the Office of Gas and Electricity Markets (Ofgem) price cap in July 2023. Core inflation – which excludes energy, food, alcohol and tobacco – remained at 6.4% in the year to July 2023. Read the full Consumer Prices Index bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">53642705</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Private rents rise at record pace while house price growth slows</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/indexofprivatehousingrentalprices/latest</link>
         <description>Private rents rise at record pace while house price growth slows 16 August 2023 Private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 5.3% in the year to July 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change since this UK data series began in January 2016. Private rental prices rose by 5.2% in England, 6.5% in Wales and 5.7% in Scotland in the year to July 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since records began (January 2006 for England, January 2010 for Wales, and January 2012 for Scotland). Private rental prices in London (which accounts for almost a third of UK rental expenditure) increased by 5.5% in the 12 months to July 2023, up from an increase of 5.3% in the 12 months to June 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change in London since the data series began in January 2006. Average UK house price annual inflation has continued to slow. The provisional estimate for the average price of a UK house was £288,000 in June 2023. This is £5,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £5,000 less than the recent peak in November 2022. This represents an average increase of 1.7% in the year to June 2023 (provisional), down slightly from growth of 1.8% in the year to May 2023 (revised estimate). Average UK house prices grew 1.7% in the 12 months to June 2023 (provisional estimate) Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to June 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices grew 1.7% in the 12 months to June 2023 (provisional estimate) Image .csv .xls House prices in Scotland were little changed in the year to June 2023 (0.0%). In Wales, prices grew by 0.6% over the same period, while in England they rose by 1.9%. Average house prices in Northern Ireland rose by 2.7% in the year to Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023. Of the English regions, the North East saw the highest house price inflation in the year to June 2023 (4.7%), although average house prices here remain the lowest of all English regions at £161,000. London saw the lowest annual inflation of any English region, with prices decreasing by 0.6% in the year to June 2023. This is because average house prices rose sharply in London a year ago, rising by £9,000 between May and June 2022, compared with a smaller increase of £3,000 between May and June 2023. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">83859043</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Services sector driving increase in business turnover </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/economicoutputandproductivity/output/bulletins/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators/latest</link>
         <description>Services sector driving increase in business turnover 17 August 2023 More firms reported increased turnover than reported decreased turnover in July 2023. This was driven by businesses in the services sector. This sector saw a net 5% of firms report an increase in turnover, up from a net 4% of businesses who reported a decrease in turnover in June 2023. The service sector was the only sector that showed growth in the net proportion of firms to report an increase in turnover in July 2023, rising 9 percentage points from June 2023. This growth is outside the normal month-on-month variation. This increase was also the largest driver of the total net 4% of firms who reported increasing turnover (seasonally adjusted) in July 2023. Read the full Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 17 August 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">55196381</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Shoppers go online as wet weather dampens spending</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainjuly2023</link>
         <description>Shoppers go online as wet weather dampens spending 18 August 2023 Wet weather has resulted in a drop in retail sales as shoppers cut back on spending and turned to online stores. Retail sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought) in Great Britain fell by an estimated 1.2% in July 2023 following a rise of 0.6% in June 2023. Sales volumes at food stores dropped by 2.6% in July 2023. Supermarkets reported that wet weather caused a fall in clothing sales, although sales in food and drink also decreased. More people turned to online shopping in response to the rain. In total, 27.4% of the value of retail sales took place online in July 2023, the highest proportion since February 2022 (28.0%). Meanwhile, non-food stores also saw a decline in sales volumes, falling 1.7% in July 2023 following a 0.6% rise the previous month. Automotive fuel stores sales bounced back from a 0.6% fall in June 2023 to a 0.7% increase last month. When compared with their pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) level in February 2020, total retail sales were 16.4% higher in value terms, but volumes were 1.8% lower. Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Volume and value sales, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, July 2019 to July 2023 Source: Office for National Statistics Download this chart Higher prices mean the amount people buy and how much they spend have moved apart Image .csv .xls Read our full Retail Sales, Great Britain: July 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">68373357</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Stronger than forecast GDP improves debt picture</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Stronger than forecast GDP improves debt picture 22 August 2023 Public sector debt at the end of July 2023 was estimated at 98.5% of GDP (Gross Domestic Product). This means that the level of debt was 1.5% less than the value of the annual output of the UK economy. This represents an increase in debt of 1.9 percentage points (ppts) of GDP compared with the same point last year but 4.0 ppts less than the level forecast by the Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR) in March 2023. July saw upward revisions to our previous estimate of GDP, which have led to downward revisions to the debt ratio for recent months, with debt at the end of June being reduced by 1.3 ppts from 100.8% to 99.5% of GDP. This downward revision means that the last time the debt-to-GDP ratio was above 100% was at the end of the financial year ending March 1961. We recently published a blog explaining How the ONS estimates UK debt to GDP figures and its susceptibility to revision. In July 2023, the public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income, requiring it to borrow £4.3 billion, which is £3.4 billion more than in July last year but £1.7 billion less than forecast by the OBR. This was the fifth highest July borrowing on record, behind that of July 2020, during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic period, and that of July 2009, 2010 and 2011, following the global economic downturn. July receipts are boosted by self-assessed income tax each year, with the £11.8 billion received this month being £2.5 billion more than in July 2022, and a July record. However, inflation continues to put upward pressure on spending, with increases in July’s interest costs, central government consumption (pay and procurement), and uprated benefit payments. Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">19976198</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Half of adults spend more to get their usual food shop </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain9to20august2023</link>
         <description>Half of adults spend more to get their usual food shop 25 August 2023 Around half (51%) of adults across Great Britain say they are spending more than usual to get what they normally buy when food shopping. This is according to those asked between 9 and 20 August 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . It was up from 43% in the previous survey period (26 July to 6 August 2023). Over half (53%) of adults reported that their cost of living had increased compared with a month ago. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">29133549</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
