<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 09:13:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Rapid growth in proportion of working age adults in employment</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/theemploymentpopulationratioandchangesintheuklabourmarket</link>
         <description>Rapid growth in proportion of working age adults in employment 28 March 2023 The employment-population (EPOP) ratio is the proportion of those aged 16 years and over in employment. It is an indicator of how well the economy is doing in creating jobs. In the period following the global financial crisis in 2008 and before the onset of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic in 2020, the EPOP ratio increased to its highest recorded level. Despite its recent fall following the pandemic, the latest EPOP ratio remains high relative to its historic rate. This is because recent increases in inactivity have not yet offset strongly rising activity rates in the decade leading up to the COVID-19 pandemic, particularly for men and women aged 50 years and over. Employment as a proportion of the adult population was the highest on record immediately before the COVID-19 pandemic The employment-population ratio (aged 16 years and over), UK, seasonally adjusted, February to April 1971 to November to January 2023 Source: Labour Force Survey from the Office for National Statistics Notes: The population totals used for the latest Labour Force Survey (LFS) estimates use projected growth rates from Real Time Information (RTI) data for UK, EU and non-EU populations based on 2021 patterns. The total population used for the LFS, therefore, does not consider any changes in migration, birth rates, or death rates since June 2021. As such, levels estimates may be under- or over-estimating the true values and should be used with caution. Estimates of rates will, however, be more robust. Download this chart Employment as a proportion of the adult population was the highest on record immediately before the COVID-19 pandemic Image .csv .xls Read our full bulletin on The employment-population ratio and changes in the UK labour market . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88040797</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 09:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around one in six adults classed as food insecure </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/theimpactofwinterpressuresondifferentpopulationgroupsingreatbritain15to26february2023</link>
         <description>Around one in six adults classed as food insecure 30 March 2023 Around one in six adults in Great Britain (16%) were classed as food insecure, according to new analysis of the Office for National Statistics' (ONS) winter panel survey data from 15 to 26 February 2023. Food security is a households' ability to get enough food to lead a healthy life. Food insecurity was most common among adults: with moderate-to-severe depressive symptoms (42%) not in work and not looking for work (&quot;economically inactive&quot;) and not retired (35%) living in the most deprived areas of England (31%) One of the indicators we use to measure food security is whether adults report cutting down portion sizes or skipping meals. Overall, 14% of adults reported doing this, but it was more common among adults with moderate-to-severe depressive symptoms (38%), living in the most deprived areas of England (27%), and with one or more dependent children (22%). The percentage of people in Great Britain who struggled to stay warm in their home dropped in the latest period, compared with responses collected in November and December 2022 (20% compared with 24% previously). This was possibly because of milder weather. Around 54% of adults said they were taking prescription medication. Among those who pay for their prescription, 10% reported taking less medication to save on prescription costs. Read our full bulletin on the impact of winter pressures on population groups in Great Britain . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">33299330</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 09:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Nearly 3 in 10 businesses report worker shortages</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/businessindustryandtrade/business/businessservices/bulletins/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy/latest</link>
         <description>Nearly 3 in 10 businesses report worker shortages 6 April 2023 Nearly 3 in 10 (28%) businesses with 10 or more employees reported a shortage of workers in late March 2023. Of these businesses, nearly half (49%) said employees were working increased hours, while 40% of businesses were unable to meet demands. Among businesses with 10 or more employees, the human health and social work industry was most affected by worker shortages. Nearly half (44%) of these businesses reported worker shortages, according to the latest data from the Business Insights and Conditions Survey, collected from 20 March to 2 April 2023. Energy prices and inflation remain the main concerns for businesses. However, taxation has become more of a concern for businesses, but concerns about energy prices and falling demand for goods and services have fallen, in the most recent survey results. Read our full bulletin on Business insights and impact on the UK economy . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">83469309</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 09:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rises in consumer spending, energy prices, and possible redundancies</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators6april2023</link>
         <description>Rises in consumer spending, energy prices, and possible redundancies 6 April 2023 Revolut debit card spending rose by 16 percentage points across all categories compared with the previous week. “Retail” spending represented the largest increase, rising by 28 percentage points, followed by “entertainment”, which rose by 16 percentage points. However, although these rises are large , they are not unusual and follow typical within-month spending patterns. “Retail” spending also rose by around twice the level of increase seen in the “travel and accommodation” and “automotive fuel” categories, which increased by 14 and 13 percentage points, respectively. The System Average Price of gas saw a record increase for 2023, rising by 7% in the week to 2 April. However, the current price is nearly two-thirds lower than the equivalent week last year. According to our analysis of data made available by Elexon, the System Price of electricity also saw a record increase for 2023 in the latest week, rising by around a quarter compared with the previous week. However, this price is around half as much as the price seen during the equivalent period last year. The number of potential redundancies proposed by employers was around nine times higher than the equivalent week last year. Read our full bulletin on Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 6 April 2023 . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">25892077</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 09:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have remained flat in February 2023</title>
         <link>https://blog.ons.gov.uk/2023/02/10/trading-places/</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have remained flat in February 2023 13 April 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have shown no growth in February 2023, where falls in services and production were offset by growth in construction. This follows growth of 0.4% in January 2023. Looking at the broader picture, GDP grew by 0.1% in the three months to February 2023 compared with the three months to November 2022. Services fell by 0.1% in February 2023, after growing by 0.7% in January 2023. The largest contributions to the fall in February 2023 came from education, and public administration and defence; compulsory social security. Industrial action took place in both of these industries in February 2023. Production output fell by 0.2% in February 2023, following a fall of 0.5% in January 2023. Electricity, gas, steam and air conditioning supply was the largest contributor to the fall within the production sector. Construction saw a 2.4% growth in February 2023, following a 1.7% fall in January 2023. Growth in the construction sector offset falls in services and production in February 2023 Contributions to monthly GDP growth, February 2022 to February 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Notes: Sum of component contributions may not sum to total growth because of rounding. Download this chart Growth in the construction sector offset falls in services and production in February 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP. 🠕 Back to the top UK trade in goods and services deficit continues to widen because of falls in exports 13 April 2023 The total trade in goods and services deficit, the amount by which the cost of a country's imports exceeds the value of its exports, widened by £2.3 billion to £23.5 billion in the three months to February 2023, as exports fell by more than imports. The value of goods exports decreased by £1.1 billion (3.5%) in February 2023, linked to a fall in fuel exports to EU countries. Accounting for inflation, total exports of goods decreased by £0.8 billion (3.1%). The value of goods imported to the UK decreased by £0.7 billion (1.4%) in February 2023. After removing the effect of inflation, imports of goods decreased by £0.6 billion (1.5%). Imports of goods from EU countries increased by £0.4 billion (1.5%) and imports from non-EU countries fell by £1.1 billion (4.5%) in February 2023, in value terms. Fuel imports from non-EU countries fell by £0.8 billion because of reduced imports of gas and crude oil from the United States and gas from Norway in February 2023. The continued fall in gas prices contributed to this. Imports of goods from non-EU countries continued to decrease in February 2023, while imports from the EU increased EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, February 2020 to February 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Notes: Caution should be taken when interpreting these data as there is a discontinuity from January 2021 in EU trade following an HM Revenue and Customs data collection change. Our article, Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics , provides more detail. Staged Customs Controls allowed traders importing goods from the EU to delay customs declarations in 2021 by up to 175 days, and as a result some double counting may have occurred between January and June 2022. For more detail, read our Trading places: How we are producing consistent estimates of trade figures following the UK’s EU exit blog . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">77656376</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 09:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Easter boosts debit card spending on eating out and pubs</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators14april2023</link>
         <description>Easter boosts debit card spending on eating out and pubs 14 April 2023 Revolut debit card spending rose by 17 percentage points in the “pubs, restaurants and fast food” category, compared with the previous week. While four of the six spending categories saw increases in debit card spending, “pubs, restaurants and fast food” saw the largest increase. The “travel and accommodation” category remained broadly unchanged, while the “retail” category was the only category which decreased, dropping by 9 percentage points, likely the result of store closures over the Easter weekend. Experimental data from the CHAPS-based indicator of aggregate credit and debit card spending estimates an increase in all of the four of its spending categories in the latest week to 6 April 2023, with “staple” showing the biggest increase at 13 percentage points. The monthly CHAPS-based indicator of aggregate credit and debit card spending in March 2023 was 3 percentage points higher than in February 2023, having trended upwards since the start of the year, in line with usual seasonal patterns. All spending categories except “delayable” increased from February 2023 to March 2023, with the largest increase reported in the &quot;staple&quot; category, up 7 percentage points compared with February 2023. “Delayable” decreased by 3 percentage points compared with February 2023. The monthly CHAPS indicator in March 2023 was 2 percentage points higher than in March 2022. All categories except &quot;delayable&quot; increased compared with March 2022, with &quot;staple&quot; spending seeing the largest increase of 12 percentage points, followed by &quot;work related&quot; increasing by 10 percentage points and &quot;social&quot; increasing by 3 percentage points. Retail footfall saw an increase in the week to 9 April 2023, increasing to 108% of the level in the previous week. All three categories increased, with high street footfall, shopping centre footfall and retail park footfall at 113%, 105% and 101%, respectively, driven by increased activity over the Easter weekend at monitored retail zones. Similarly, all categories were above the level in the equivalent period of 2022, with high street footfall, shopping centre footfall and retail park footfall at 115%%, 107% and 103%, respectively. Retail footfall increased in all of the 12 UK regions and countries in the week to 9 April 2023, with the largest increase in the South West where footfall was 113% of the level of the previous week. Footfall in all 12 UK regions and countries was above the level in the equivalent period of 2022, with Scotland and Northern Ireland the furthest above this both at 118%. Read our bulletin Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators: 14 April 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">64163950</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 09:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
