<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:05:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in May 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpmonthlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in May 2023 13 July 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have fallen by 0.1% in May 2023, with the production sector being the main contributor. This follows growth of 0.2% in April 2023. Looking at the broader picture, GDP showed no growth in the three months to May 2023 compared with the three months to February 2023. Production output fell by 0.6% in May 2023 after a fall of 0.2% in April 2023, revised up from a fall of 0.3% in the previous publication. This sector was the main contributor to the fall in monthly GDP in May. Services output showed no growth in May 2023, following a growth 0.3% in April 2023. Within the sector the largest increase came from Human health and social work activities, largely driven by an increase of 1.8% in Human health activities after falls in March and April. The construction sector fell by 0.2% in May 2023 following a fall of 0.9% in April 2023, revised down from a fall of 0.6% in the previous publication. The production sector was the main contributor to the fall in GDP in May Contributions to monthly GDP growth, May 2022 to May 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics. Download this chart The production sector was the main contributor to the fall in GDP in May Image .csv .xls Read our latest UK monthly GDP bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">13375816</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:05:02 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Almost a quarter of businesses experiencing fall in turnover </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy13july2023</link>
         <description>Almost a quarter of businesses experiencing fall in turnover 13 July 2023 Almost a quarter (24%) of UK trading businesses reported lower turnover for June 2023 compared with May 2023. In comparison, 15% reported a higher turnover for June 2023, with both figures broadly stable with the proportions reported for May 2023. When trading businesses were asked to look ahead to August, more than half (54%) expect turnover to stay the same, while 15% expect it to increase, down from 19% reported for July 2023. Less than one in six (15%) trading businesses expect to raise the prices of goods or services they sell in August 2023; of these, a quarter (25%) reported energy prices as a reason for considering doing so, 21% reported labour costs and 19% reported raw material prices. The proportion of businesses expecting staff costs to rise over the next three months was 17%, down from 30% reported in the three months to April 2023. A quarter (25%) of businesses in the accommodation and food service activities industry said they expected their staffing costs to increase over the next three months. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">74654421</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:05:02 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Renters more likely to be financially vulnerable </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain28juneto9july2023</link>
         <description>Renters more likely to be financially vulnerable 14 July 2023 Renters across Britain are nearly five (4.7) times as likely to be financially vulnerable as those who own their home outright. That was higher than people with mortgages, who on average were two (2.0) times as likely as people who own their own homes to be financially vulnerable. People aged 25 to 34 years and disabled adults also had greater odds of being financially vulnerable, according to our survey on the impact of increased cost of living covering the period 8 February to 1 May 2023 . Renters at greater financial risk than mortgage holders or homeowners Odds of experiencing financial vulnerability compared with reference group, Great Britain, 8 February to 1 May 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download data for odds of financial vulnerability, 8 February to 1 May 2023, Great Britain, (XLSX, 24KB) .xlsx A person was considered to be financially vulnerable if three or more of the following applied to them: being unable to afford an unexpected, but necessary, expense of £850 borrowing more money or using more credit than usual, in the last month, compared with a year ago being unable to save in the next 12 months finding it very or somewhat difficult to afford energy bills Read our bulletin on the Impact of increased cost of living on adults across Great Britain: February to May 2023 🠕 Back to the top More people dipping into savings 14 July 2023 Adults in Britain are becoming more likely to say they are using their savings to manage the increased cost of living. Some 3 in 10 (30%) reported using their savings, according to our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin for the period 28 June to 9 July 2023. That was up from a quarter (25%) of adults who reported doing this in late April 2023. Around 6 in 10 (60%) adults said that their cost of living had increased compared with a month ago, although this proportion has gradually decreased since early April 2023. When asked about the important issues facing the UK today, people were most likely to cite the cost of living (92%), followed by the NHS (88%), the economy (79%), climate change and the environment (62%) and housing (62%). Read our bulletin on Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 28 June to 9 July 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">11206624</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:05:02 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Falling motor fuel prices help ease inflation </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukjune2023</link>
         <description>Falling motor fuel prices help ease inflation 19 July 2023 The rate at which prices of goods and services are rising eased to 7.3% in the year to June 2023, down from 7.9% in May. This is according to the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH). It has fallen from a peak in October 2022, when the annual inflation rate stood at 9.6%, the highest in over 40 years, according to indicative modelled consumer price inflation estimates . The recent easing is mainly because of falls in petrol and diesel prices. Overall, motor fuel prices fell by 22.7% in the year to June 2023, after a fall of 13.1% in May. However, core inflation, which excludes energy, food, alcohol and tobacco, remains at historic highs. Core CPIH rose by 6.4% in the year to June 2023, slightly down from 6.5% in May, which was the highest rate for more than 30 years. For more information, read our full Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">15263928</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:05:02 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/indexofprivatehousingrentalprices/june2023</link>
         <description>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace 19 July 2023 Annual growth in UK house prices has continued to slow. The provisional estimate for the average price of a UK house was £286,000 in May 2023. This is £6,000 higher than in the same month a year ago, but £7,000 less than the recent peak in September 2022. This represents an average increase of 1.9% in the year to May 2023 (provisional), down from growth of 3.2% in the year to April 2023 (revised estimate). Average UK house prices grew 1.9% in the 12 months to May 2023 (provisional estimate) Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to May 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices grew 1.9% in the 12 months to May 2023 (provisional estimate) Image .csv .xls Of the UK nations, the lowest annual increases in house prices were seen in England at 1.7% in the year to May 2023. However, average house prices are still higher in England than in any other nation, at £304,000. Of the English regions, the North East saw the highest house price growth in the year to May 2023 (4.0%), although house prices here remain the lowest of all English regions at £159,000. The East of England saw the lowest annual inflation (0.0%). Private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 5.1% in the year to June 2023. This is the largest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 5.1% in England, 5.8% in Wales and 5.5% in Scotland in the year to June 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since January 2006 in England, since January 2010 in Wales, and since January 2012 in Scotland. Private rental prices in London (which accounts for almost a third of UK rental expenditure ) increased by 5.3% in the 12 months to June 2023, up from an increase of 5.1% in the 12 months to May 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change in London since September 2012. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">49253274</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 09:05:02 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
