<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>UK disposable income rose between 2020 and 2021</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/regionalgrossdisposablehouseholdincomeuk1997to2021</link>
         <description>UK disposable income rose between 2020 and 2021 14 September 2023 Gross disposable household income (GDHI) in the UK rose 3.6% between 2020 and 2021, as household finances started to recover from the impacts of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. GDHI is the amount of money available for people to spend or save after taxes and benefits. In 2021, London had the highest GDHI per head of any UK nation or English region, at £31,094. Northern Ireland had the lowest, at £17,636. Of 179 local areas in the UK, 152 saw GDHI rise more than inflation (CPIH), while in the remaining 27, growth in disposable income was lower than inflation, which suggests a decrease in the real-terms value of disposable income. The local areas that saw the biggest increases in GDHI between 2020 and 2021 were the London boroughs of Kensington and Chelsea and Hammersmith and Fulham, where disposable income rose by 6.4%. Causeway Coast and Glens in Northern Ireland had the smallest increase, at 0.2%. We have mapped how GDHI has changed in areas of the UK between 1997 and 2021. Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Read the full Regional gross disposable household income, UK: 1997 to 2021 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">14149305</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Inflation eases with food prices rising at slower pace</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukaugust2023</link>
         <description>Inflation eases with food prices rising at slower pace 20 September 2023 The rate at which prices of goods and services are rising for consumers has continued to ease, with the annual inflation rate falling to 6.3% in the year to August 2023. This was down from 6.4% in July, according to our Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH) release. The easing of inflation was partly because food and non-alcoholic beverages prices rose by a smaller amount than the same time last year. Food and non-alcoholic beverage prices rose by 0.3% between July and August 2023, compared with 1.5% between the same two months in 2022. This led to a fall in the annual rate to 13.6% in the year to August 2023. This was down from 14.9% in July and a recent high of 19.2% in March. Prices of some foods, notably milk, cheese, fish and vegetables, fell between July and August 2023. Accommodation prices also fell between July and August 2023. This helped the annual inflation rate for restaurants and hotels ease to 8.3% in August, down from 9.6% in July. Read our latest Consumer price inflation, UK: August 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">48333249</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows while private rents rise at a record pace</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/indexofprivatehousingrentalprices/latest</link>
         <description>House price growth slows while private rents rise at a record pace 20 September 2023 The annual inflation rate of average UK house prices continued to slow in the year to July 2023, with prices decreasing over the year in some regions. The provisional estimate for the average price of a UK house was £290,000 in July 2023. This is £2,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £2,000 less than the recent peak in November 2022. This represents an average increase of 0.6% in the year to July 2023 (provisional), down from growth of 1.9% in the year to May 2023 (revised estimate). House prices in England also increased by 0.6% in the 12 months to July 2023. Annual house price inflation was slower in Scotland, at 0.1%, while average house prices in Wales fell by 0.1% in the 12 months to July 2023. Of the English regions, the North East saw the highest house price inflation in the year to July 2023 (2.7%), although this was down from 5.7% in the year to June 2023. House prices in the North East remain the lowest of all English regions at £163,000. The South West saw the lowest annual inflation of any English region, with prices decreasing by 1.0% in the year to July 2023. London was the only other region where prices decreased in the year to July 2023. The North East saw the highest annual inflation in house prices of any English region All dwellings annual house price percentage change, by English region, 12 months to July 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry and Office for National Statistics Download this chart The North East saw the highest annual inflation in house prices of any English region Image .csv .xls Meanwhile, private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 5.5% in the year to August 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 5.4% in England, 6.5% in Wales and 6.0% in Scotland in the year to August 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since records began (January 2006 for England, January 2010 for Wales, and January 2012 for Scotland). Private rental prices in London (a city that accounts for almost a third of total UK rental expenditure ) increased by 5.9% in the 12 months to August 2023. This was the highest annual percentage change of any English region, and the highest in London since the series began in January 2006. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">27513165</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Trading businesses reported lower turnover for August 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Trading businesses reported lower turnover for August 2023 21 September 2023 More than a quarter (27%) of trading businesses experienced a fall in turnover in August 2023, compared with the previous calendar month, up 2 percentage points from the 25% reported in July 2023. In contrast, 15% reported their turnover was higher. Businesses who reported their turnover had stayed the same were up 2 percentage points over the same period, to 52%. More than a quarter (27%) of trading businesses reported lower turnover in August 2023 compared with July 2023 Impact on turnover, businesses currently trading, broken down by industry, weighted by count, UK, 1 to 31 August 2023 Source: Business Insights and Conditions Survey from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart More than a quarter (27%) of trading businesses reported lower turnover in August 2023 compared with July 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our Business insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Public sector borrowing is lower than official forecasts 21 September 2023 The public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income, in August 2023. This required it to borrow £11.6 billion, which is £3.5 billion more than in August last year but £1.4 billion less than forecast by the Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR). This was the fourth-highest August borrowing on record, behind that of August of 2020 and 2021, during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, and also behind August 2009, following the global economic downturn. While growth in central government tax receipts has been slowing in recent months, it remains stronger than in the years before the coronavirus pandemic. Inflation continues to put upward pressure on spending, and although there was a reduction in debt interest payable this month compared with a year earlier, there continued to be increases in central government pay and procurement spending and because benefit payments have been uprated. This all brings the amount borrowed in the financial year to August 2023 (April to August) to £69.6 billion, £19.3 billion more than in the same five-month period last year but £11.4 billion less than the £81.0 billion the OBR forecast. Public sector net debt at the end of August 2023 was provisionally estimated at 98.8% of GDP (gross domestic product). That is to say, the level of debt was slightly less than the value of the output of the UK economy over a 12-month period. On 29 September 2023, we will publish updated estimates of GDP. These data will be reflected in our next public sector finances statistical bulletin published on 20 October 2023. We recently published a blog explaining How the ONS estimates UK debt to GDP figures and their susceptibility to revision. Read our latest UK public sector finances bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">83710554</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around 4 in every 10 adults finding energy bills difficult to afford</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain6to17september2023</link>
         <description>Around 4 in every 10 adults finding energy bills difficult to afford 22 September 2023 Around 4 in every 10 (42%) of adults in Great Britain report they are finding it very or somewhat difficult to afford energy bills. This is according to those asked between 6 and 17 September 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin. This was slightly lower than 48% in a similar period last year (31 August to 11 September 2022). Among the 56% of people who said their cost of living had risen in the previous month, 60% said the price of their fuel had increased. Almost half (47%) said they were using less fuel such as gas or electricity in their homes because of the rising cost of living. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">26417185</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Number of businesses fell in the year to March 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/experimentalestimatesofgreenjobs</link>
         <description>Number of businesses fell in the year to March 2023 27 September 2023 The number of Value Added Tax (VAT) and/or Pay As You Earn (PAYE) businesses in the UK as of March 2023 was 2.727 million, a decrease of 1.5% from March 2022. Through the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, the business population remained broadly steady but is now showing a small fall. While growth in the number of businesses has slowed since 2018, this is the first annual fall since 2010 to 2011. The numbers of businesses within all categories of legal status fell except for local authorities and non-profits. The professional, scientific, and technical industry accounted for the largest number of businesses, with 15.2% of all registered businesses in the UK. This was compared with 15.6% in March last year. The number of businesses in this industry has decreased for four years running, but it remains the largest broad industry group since 2013. The transport and storage (including postal) broad industry group experienced the largest fall in the year to March 2023. After strong growth in 2021, the number of transport and storage businesses has fallen in the last two years, with a decrease of 6.9% in 2023. Read our latest bulletin, UK business; activity, size and location: 2023 🠕 Back to the top More than half a million jobs in green industries in 2020 27 September 2023 In 2020 there were an estimated 526,000 full-time equivalent (FTE) people employed in green industries in the UK, compared with 507,000 FTE in 2015. In 2018, there was a peak of 545,000 FTE. A green job is defined as employment in an activity that contributes to protecting or restoring the environment. These can be jobs in green industries, jobs in green occupations or jobs in green firms. Looking at green occupations, analysis of recent responses to our Opinions and Lifestyle Survey in May 2023 found that around a quarter (27%) of working adults in Great Britain would describe any part of their job as a “green job”. Meanwhile, around 1 in 20 working adults (4%) reported that all or most of their job relates to “green” activities. Working males (30%) appeared more likely than working females (24%) to describe any part of their job as green. In Scotland and Wales, working adults were more likely to describe any part of their job as green, at 38% and 36%, respectively, while 26% of working adults in England said the same. See our Experimental Estimates of Green Jobs bulletin for more information and details on the approaches to measuring green jobs 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">92783970</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK business investment revised up in April to June 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/businessinvestment/latest</link>
         <description>UK business investment revised up in April to June 2023 29 September 2023 UK business investment increased by 4.1% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023, revised up from the provisional estimate of 3.4% growth. This reflects upwards revisions to investments in transport, intellectual property products (IPP), and information and communication technology (ICT) and other machinery and equipment. Business investment has grown by 9.2% compared with the same quarter a year ago. Whole economy investment (technically known as gross fixed capital formation), which includes investment by business and public sector investment, increased by 0.8% in Quarter 2 2023. This was revised up from the provisional estimate of 0.0% growth. The largest contribution to growth in the latest quarter came from transport, with a smaller positive contribution coming from intellectual property products. Business investment, after lagging behind whole economy investment for much of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic and the period after, is now closing the gap. Business investment continued to grow at a faster rate than gross fixed capital formation (GFCF) in Q2 2023 UK business investment and whole economy investment, chained volume measure, seasonally adjusted, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 1997 to Quarter 2 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: Q1 refers to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar), Q2 refers to Quarter 2 (Apr to June), Q3 refers to Quarter 3 (July to Sept) and Q4 refers to Quarter 4 (Oct to Dec). UK business investment, chained volume measure, seasonally adjusted, excluding the reclassification of British Nuclear Fuels (BNFL) in Quarter 2 2005. Quarter 2 2020 was the largest fall on record for gross fixed capital formation, excluding the reclassification of British Nuclear Fuels in Quarter 2 2005. Index is referenced to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar), 1997 = 100. Download the data .xlsx This release contains data that are consistent with the UK National Accounts (also known as the Blue Book 2023), which will be released on 31 October 2023. Data for all periods in this release are subject to revision in line with the National Accounts Revision Policy. Read the full bulletin on Business investment in the UK: April to June 2023 revised results 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">47939294</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rent or mortgage payments up for nearly half of adults</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain20septemberto1october2023</link>
         <description>Rent or mortgage payments up for nearly half of adults 06 October 2023 Almost half (47%) of adults in Great Britain paying rent or a mortgage said their payments had increased in the last six months. This is according to those asked between 20 September and 1 October 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . This was 33% during a similar period last year (29 September to 9 October 2022). Among rent and mortgage payers, 40% said they were finding the payments very or somewhat difficult to afford. That was compared with 30% a year ago. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">34465739</guid>
         <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:05:17 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
