<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 09:14:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Half of British adults worried about cost of energy and food </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainmarch2023</link>
         <description>Half of British adults worried about cost of energy and food 21 April 2023 Around half of British adults say they have worried about the cost of energy and food in recent weeks. That is according to our latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey, which asked people what issues they had worried about in the past fortnight. The most-reported problems were the cost of energy (49%) and cost of food (49%), according to responses collected between 5 and 16 April 2023. People living in the most-deprived areas in England were more likely to report such concerns. Among those living in the most-deprived fifth of areas in England, 64% said they had been worried about the cost of food and 60% about the cost of energy. This was compared with 40% and 42%, respectively, in the least-deprived fifth of areas in the country. Estimates by deprivation are provided for England only. This is because of the smaller sample sizes from the survey in Scotland and Wales. The cost of energy and food are the most common concerns Proportion of all adults in Great Britain, 5 to 16 April 2023 Source: Opinions and Lifestyle Survey from the Office for National Statistics Notes: Question: &quot; Which of the following issues, if any, have you been worried about in the past two weeks?&quot;. Base: all adults. Respondents were able to choose more than one option. 15% of adults reported that they have not been worried about any issues in the past two weeks. This has not been included in the chart because respondents who selected this response option were unable to select any other response option. Download this chart The cost of energy and food are the most common concerns Image .csv .xls Around two in five British adults (39%) also said they had been affected by industrial action in the last month, which was up from 27% in the previous survey period (22 March to 2 April 2023). This coincided with industrial action taken by NHS workers in England and civil servants in His Majesty’s Passport Office. Read our full Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 5 to 16 April 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Retail sales volumes fall by 0.9% 21 April 2023 Retail sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought) are estimated to have fallen by 0.9% in March 2023. The retail sales volume fall follows a rise of 1.1% in February 2023 and 1.2% in January, meaning that the broader picture shows sales volumes rising by 0.6% in the three months to March 2023 when compared with the three previous months. This has been the first three-month on three-month rise since August 2021. Non-food store sales volumes fell by 1.3% in March 2023, following a rise of 2.4% in February. Food store sales volumes fell by 0.7% in March 2023, following a rise of 0.6% in February 2023. Non-store retailing, the majority of which are online stores, saw sales volumes fall by 0.8% in March 2023, which followed a rise of 0.3% in February 2023. Meanwhile, automotive fuel sales volumes rose by 0.2% in March 2023 following a fall of 1.2% in February 2023. Fuel sales remain at 8.5% below their pre coronavirus (COVID-19) February 2020 levels. Retail sales in March 2023 were impacted by falls in non-food stores sales volumes Contribution to monthly growth, volume seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, March 2023 compared with February 2023 Source: Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry from the Office for National Statistics Notes: Individual contributions may not sum to the total because of rounding. Download this chart Retail sales in March 2023 were impacted by falls in non-food stores sales volumes Image .csv .xls Read our full Retail sales; Great Britain: March 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">53711160</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 09:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>1 in 20 adults running out of food</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/trackingtheimpactofwinterpressuresingreatbritain</link>
         <description>1 in 20 adults running out of food 24 April 2023 In February 2023, 5% of people said they had run out of food and been unable to afford more in the past two weeks. In November 2022 to January 2023, and in February 2023, we surveyed adults in Great Britain about their experiences of affording food over winter. New analysis looks at how many people struggled with these issues across both survey periods, and how many reported struggling for part of the winter but not the other. The 5% of adults who reported running out of food in February 2023. This comprised 3% who persistently reported this across both survey periods, and 2% who did not report this previously but did in the latest period. Running out of food was more common for people in certain groups. One in five (20%) people experiencing moderate to severe depressive symptoms said they had run out of food in the latest period. This comprised 13% who reported this persistently across both survey periods, and 6% who did not report this issue in the previous period but did in the latest (these figures do not sum to 20% because of rounding). The following groups appeared more likely to persistently report running out of food and being unable to buy more: those not in work, not seeking work and not retired (10%) those living in the most deprived areas of England (8%) disabled people (6%) You can explore further how different groups have been affected by a range of issues over time in the full article. Read the full article tracking the impact of winter pressures in Great Britain 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">14782990</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 09:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Annual public sector borrowing below official forecast</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Annual public sector borrowing below official forecast 25 April 2023 In March 2023, the public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income, requiring it to borrow £21.5 billion. Combined with a reduction of £14.6 billion to our previously published financial year-to-February borrowing figure, this brings the initial estimate for borrowing in the financial year ending (FYE) 2023 to £139.2 billion. This was the fourth highest financial year borrowing on record, behind FYE 2021 (during the COVID-19 pandemic) and both FYE 2010 and FYE 2011 (after the effects of the global financial downturn). The Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR) predicts final public sector borrowing in the FYE 2023 will be £13.2 billion higher than our initial estimate, at £152.4 billion. Debt at the end of March was £2,530.4 billion, £16.0 billion less than forecast by the OBR. This was equivalent to 99.6% of the UK’s annual gross domestic product (GDP), 1.0 percentage point lower than forecast. Debt is only one of several measures of the public sector balance sheet. This month we expanded our balance sheet presentation to include public sector net worth, which we explain in our blog What the UK government owns and what it owes . Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88095023</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 09:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Sickness absence rate highest since 2004 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/overseastravelandtourismdecember2022provisionalresults</link>
         <description>Sickness absence rate highest since 2004 26 April 2023 The UK sickness absence rate – the percentage of working hours lost because of sickness or injury – rose to 2.6% in 2022, an increase of 0.4 percentage points from 2021 and the highest it has been since 2004, when it was 2.7%. The sickness absence rate rose to 2.6% in 2022 Sickness absence rate, for all people in employment aged 16 years and over, UK, 1995 to 2022 Source: Labour Force Survey from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart The sickness absence rate rose to 2.6% in 2022 Image .csv .xls There were an estimated 185.6 million working days lost because of sickness or injury in 2022, a new record high. This represents an increase of 35.8 million from 2021 and 47.4 million more than the 2019 (pre-coronavirus pandemic) level. While the number of working days lost was a record high in 2022, days lost per worker was not, as the total number of workers in the UK has risen since the 1990s. Minor illnesses were the most common reason given for sickness absence in 2022, accounting for 29.3% of absences. This was followed by: “other” conditions at 23.8% musculoskeletal problems at 10.5% respiratory conditions at 8.3% mental health conditions at 7.9% All age groups experienced increases in their sickness absence rate in 2022. Groups with the highest rates of sickness absence in 2022 included women, older workers, those with long-term health conditions, people working part-time, and people working in care, leisure, or other service occupations. Read our Sickness absence in the UK labour market: 2022 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Visits down but spending up for UK residents abroad 26 April 2023 UK residents spent millions more on visits abroad in December 2022 compared with before the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, despite making far fewer trips. They made a total of 4.0 million overseas visits during the month, according to estimates from our latest International Passenger Survey. That was down 21% on the 5.1 million visits made in December 2019, which was the last comparable month before the pandemic. Despite making fewer visits, UK residents spent an estimated £3.4 billion abroad in December 2022. That was a 9% increase from £3.1 billion in December 2019. Overseas residents made 3.0 million visits to the UK in December 2022, which was 14% below the 3.4 million trips recorded pre-pandemic. Spending by overseas residents also fell by 11% over the period, from £2.7 billion to £2.4 billion. Read our Overseas travel and tourism: December 2022 provisional results bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">39504866</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 09:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Online job adverts 17% lower than 2022</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators27april2023</link>
         <description>Online job adverts 17% lower than 2022 27 April 2023 Online job adverts were 17% lower on 21 April 2023 than the equivalent period in 2022. Only 2 of the 12 UK countries and English regions, along with 4 of the 28 job categories, saw an increase in online job adverts compared with the equivalent period of 2022, according to data from Adzuna. The total number of online job adverts on 21 April 2023 was unchanged from the previous week. The total number of online job adverts on 21 April 2023 was unchanged from the previous week Volume of online job adverts, index: 100 = February 2020 average, 7 February 2018 to 21 April 2023, non-seasonally adjusted, UK Source: Adzuna Download this chart The total number of online job adverts on 21 April 2023 was unchanged from the previous week Image .csv .xls Although the total number of online job adverts remained unchanged on 21 April 2023 compared with the previous week, there were increases in 12 categories, falls in 11, and 5 remained unchanged. Large increases were seen in the “part time or weekend” and “other or general” categories, which rose by 50% and 13%, respectively. The largest decreases week-on-week were seen in “education” and “charity or voluntary”, which fell by 12% and 5%, respectively. The number of adverts in “charity or voluntary” also fell below the pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) baseline for the first time since late January 2023. Read our Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">33095968</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 09:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>ONS launches shopping prices comparison tool</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/articles/ukconsumerpriceinflationbasketofgoodsandservices/latest</link>
         <description>ONS launches shopping prices comparison tool 03 May 2023 The Office for National Statistics (ONS) has released a new tool allowing you to compare the average prices of over 450 items in the consumer prices inflation basket. In the past year, 95% of these items have increased in price , with cucumbers (up 52%), olive oil (up 49%) and hard cheese (up 44%) seeing the largest increases. The tool contains items ranging from bananas to nursery fees and aims to help improve the accessibility of existing ONS data by easily allowing users to track average price trends. As well as showing average price changes on an item-by-item basis, the tool also lets you create your own bespoke basket of items and calculate the total average price change across these items. For example, a roast dinner for four people, including a whole chicken weighing (1.5kg), white potatoes (1kg), carrots (1 kg), broccoli (350g) and butter (100g), could cost £8.68 on average in March 2023, based on a 2023 sample. This is £1.68 more than in March 2022, with broccoli recording the highest increase at 34%. The tool will be updated every month to reflect the latest inflation data and will be refreshed each March to accommodate the latest changes to the items in the inflation basket . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">75035941</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 09:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
