<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 09:04:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Long-term sickness pushes more people out of labour market </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/risingillhealthandeconomicinactivityduetolongtermsicknessuk2019to2023</link>
         <description>Long-term sickness pushes more people out of labour market 26 July 2023 More than 2.5 million people across the UK were neither working nor looking for work because of long-term sickness in the three months to May 2023. It means the number of working-age people out of the labour market (known as “economically inactive”) has risen by more than 400,000 since the start of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Economic inactivity linked to long-term sickness is rising Cumulative change in economic inactivity (seasonally adjusted), people aged 16 to 64 years, December to February 2020 to March to May 2023 Source: Labour Force Survey from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Economic inactivity linked to long-term sickness is rising Image .csv .xls Overall, 36% of working-age people said that they had at least one long-term health condition between January and March 2023. This was up from 31% in the same period of 2019, and 29% in the same period of 2016. During the same period, more than 1.35 million (53%) of those inactive because of long-term sickness reported that they had depression, bad nerves or anxiety. The majority of those (more than 1 million) said it was a secondary health condition rather than their main one. Read our article on Rising ill-health and economic inactivity because of long-term sickness 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">27022529</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Business creations and closures fell compared with a year ago </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/housingpurchaseaffordabilitygreatbritain2022</link>
         <description>Business creations and closures fell compared with a year ago 27 July 2023 The number of new businesses in the UK has dropped in the space of a year. Experimental figures from the Inter-Departmental Business Register (IDBR) showed that there were 77,095 businesses created between Quarter 2 (Apr to Jun) 2023 and Quarter 2 2022. This is a drop of 14% and is the second lowest number of business creations in a second quarter since the start of this series in 2017. The number of business creations decreased in 14 out of 16 industry groups this quarter when compared with Quarter 2 2022. The most significant decrease came in the transport and storage industry, where business creations were down by 59%. The number of business closures in the UK in Quarter 2 2023 was 84,150. This is 15% lower than in Quarter 2 2022. The number of business closures decreased in 14 out of 16 main industrial groups. The most significant decrease in closures came in the professional, scientific and technical industry (down 25%). This is now the eighth quarter in a row where there have been more closures than creations. The statistics presented are Experimental Statistics , so care needs to be taken when interpreting them. Our annual business demography publication remains the best source of information on business demography. Read our full Business demography, quarterly experimental statistics, UK: April to June 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Average homes across UK cost more than five years’ income 27 July 2023 Since 2017, the affordability ratio (how many “years of income” the average house price represents) in all UK nations has remained above five, making them outside the Office for National Statistic’s broad threshold for what is affordable. In England, it has been above five since 2002. In the year to March 2022, the average house price in England was £275,000, or 8.4 years of income for the average household. In Wales, the average house price was 6.4 times the average income. In Scotland, it was 5.3 times the average income and in Northern Ireland it was 5.1 times the average income. For households with the lowest incomes, the average home in England cost 19 years of income. England had the widest range in housing affordability of all UK nations Number of years income applied to the equivalent cost of an average price home, by income decile and by country, 2022 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Read our full Housing Purchase Affordability in the UK, 2022 article 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">68568187</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Most businesses have not assessed key climate change risks</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy10august2023</link>
         <description>Most businesses have not assessed key climate change risks 10 August 2023 Three-quarters (75%) of UK businesses in our latest business insights survey said that they had not assessed the risks of certain climate change effects. These effects included water scarcity, coastal erosion, increased flooding and temperature increases. Our Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS) for late July 2023 does not cover all sectors of the economy so the results reflect only those surveyed. Of those businesses that had assessed these risks of climate change, 28% had not taken any action, 18% did not expect to be impacted, while 18% reported they had been unable to take action, either due to costs or the lack of information or guidance. Our survey also showed that in late July 2023, 21% of businesses reported that they were using, or intending to use, increased homeworking as a permanent business model, with reduced overheads (51%) and improved staff well-being (47%) reported as the main reasons. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88644194</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Large falls in imports from non-EU countries in June 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/balanceofpayments/bulletins/uktrade/latest</link>
         <description>Large falls in imports from non-EU countries in June 2023 11 August 2023 The value of goods imports decreased by £2.9 billion (5.8%) in June 2023, because of a large fall in imports from non-EU countries of £3.8 billion (15.9%). This was partially offset by a rise in imports from the EU of £0.8 billion (3.2%). The fall in imports from non-EU countries was the largest since April 2020. This was because of lower gas prices in June, which led to a fall in fuel imports from these countries of £2.1 billion (39.6%). The fall was £0.7 billion (20.0%) after adjusting for inflation. The total value of goods exports increased by £0.6 billion (1.8%) in June 2023 because of a £0.6 billion (3.8%) rise in exports to non-EU countries, while exports to the EU remained stable. The rise in exports to non-EU countries was mainly because of an increase in machinery and transport equipment. The total trade in goods and services deficit narrowed slightly by £0.5 billion to £19.0 billion in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 because of a larger fall in imports than exports. The total trade deficit has reduced steadily since Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2022 when it stood at £30.4 billion. A large fall in fuel imports contributed to a drop in imports of goods from non-EU countries in June 2023 EU and non-EU goods imports by commodity, current prices, seasonally adjusted, June 2021 to June 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. Read our latest UK trade bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">927974</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP rose by an estimated 0.2% in the second quarter of 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/gdpfirstquarterlyestimateuk/latest</link>
         <description>UK GDP rose by an estimated 0.2% in the second quarter of 2023 11 August 2023 The UK economy grew by an estimated 0.2% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023. The figure is a measure of real gross domestic product (GDP), which is the value of all goods and services produced in the UK after adjusting for price changes over time. Real GDP is estimated to have increased by 0.2% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 UK, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2022 to Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 Source: GDP first quarterly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Real GDP is estimated to have increased by 0.2% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023 Image .csv .xls The service sector grew by 0.1% in Quarter 2 2023, with the largest positive contributors being information and communication, and hospitality. Elsewhere, production output increased by 0.7%, driven largely by growth in manufacturing, while construction output increased for the seventh consecutive quarter. Investment in information and communication technology (ICT) equipment and other machinery equipment declined on the quarter in response to the super-deduction allowance ending, which enabled companies to cut their tax bill by up to 25 pence for every £1 invested. Despite this, business investment overall increased on the quarter, along with strong growth in household and government consumption. Inflationary pressures remain high by historical standards as indicated by an increase of 7.4% in the implied price (a measure of price movements over time) of household expenditure in the year to June 2023. Early estimates show wages and salaries grew by 2.6% in Quarter 2 2023, reflecting rises in public sector earning, particularly hospital wages and salaries. Read our latest bulletin on UK quarterly GDP 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">48898779</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Almost half of rent or mortgage payers in Britain report a rise</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain26julyto6august2023</link>
         <description>Almost half of rent or mortgage payers in Britain report a rise 11 August 2023 Close to 4 in every 10 adults (38%) in Great Britain who pay for rent or a mortgage are finding it very or somewhat difficult to afford these payments. This is according to those asked between 26 July and 6 August 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . It was around 3 in 10 adults (29%) in early August 2022. Among those paying for rent or a mortgage, almost half (47%) reported their payments had gone up in the last six months. Over 5 in 10 adults (56%) reported that their cost of living had increased compared with a month ago, while 41% reported it had stayed the same and 2% said it had decreased. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">30529839</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
