<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 09:04:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Around 4 in every 10 adults finding energy bills difficult to afford</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain6to17september2023</link>
         <description>Around 4 in every 10 adults finding energy bills difficult to afford 22 September 2023 Around 4 in every 10 (42%) of adults in Great Britain report they are finding it very or somewhat difficult to afford energy bills. This is according to those asked between 6 and 17 September 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin. This was slightly lower than 48% in a similar period last year (31 August to 11 September 2022). Among the 56% of people who said their cost of living had risen in the previous month, 60% said the price of their fuel had increased. Almost half (47%) said they were using less fuel such as gas or electricity in their homes because of the rising cost of living. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">26417185</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Number of businesses fell in the year to March 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/experimentalestimatesofgreenjobs</link>
         <description>Number of businesses fell in the year to March 2023 27 September 2023 The number of Value Added Tax (VAT) and/or Pay As You Earn (PAYE) businesses in the UK as of March 2023 was 2.727 million, a decrease of 1.5% from March 2022. Through the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, the business population remained broadly steady but is now showing a small fall. While growth in the number of businesses has slowed since 2018, this is the first annual fall since 2010 to 2011. The numbers of businesses within all categories of legal status fell except for local authorities and non-profits. The professional, scientific, and technical industry accounted for the largest number of businesses, with 15.2% of all registered businesses in the UK. This was compared with 15.6% in March last year. The number of businesses in this industry has decreased for four years running, but it remains the largest broad industry group since 2013. The transport and storage (including postal) broad industry group experienced the largest fall in the year to March 2023. After strong growth in 2021, the number of transport and storage businesses has fallen in the last two years, with a decrease of 6.9% in 2023. Read our latest bulletin, UK business; activity, size and location: 2023 🠕 Back to the top More than half a million jobs in green industries in 2020 27 September 2023 In 2020 there were an estimated 526,000 full-time equivalent (FTE) people employed in green industries in the UK, compared with 507,000 FTE in 2015. In 2018, there was a peak of 545,000 FTE. A green job is defined as employment in an activity that contributes to protecting or restoring the environment. These can be jobs in green industries, jobs in green occupations or jobs in green firms. Looking at green occupations, analysis of recent responses to our Opinions and Lifestyle Survey in May 2023 found that around a quarter (27%) of working adults in Great Britain would describe any part of their job as a “green job”. Meanwhile, around 1 in 20 working adults (4%) reported that all or most of their job relates to “green” activities. Working males (30%) appeared more likely than working females (24%) to describe any part of their job as green. In Scotland and Wales, working adults were more likely to describe any part of their job as green, at 38% and 36%, respectively, while 26% of working adults in England said the same. See our Experimental Estimates of Green Jobs bulletin for more information and details on the approaches to measuring green jobs 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">92783970</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK business investment revised up in April to June 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/grossdomesticproductgdp/bulletins/businessinvestment/latest</link>
         <description>UK business investment revised up in April to June 2023 29 September 2023 UK business investment increased by 4.1% in Quarter 2 (Apr to June) 2023, revised up from the provisional estimate of 3.4% growth. This reflects upwards revisions to investments in transport, intellectual property products (IPP), and information and communication technology (ICT) and other machinery and equipment. Business investment has grown by 9.2% compared with the same quarter a year ago. Whole economy investment (technically known as gross fixed capital formation), which includes investment by business and public sector investment, increased by 0.8% in Quarter 2 2023. This was revised up from the provisional estimate of 0.0% growth. The largest contribution to growth in the latest quarter came from transport, with a smaller positive contribution coming from intellectual property products. Business investment, after lagging behind whole economy investment for much of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic and the period after, is now closing the gap. Business investment continued to grow at a faster rate than gross fixed capital formation (GFCF) in Q2 2023 UK business investment and whole economy investment, chained volume measure, seasonally adjusted, Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 1997 to Quarter 2 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: Q1 refers to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar), Q2 refers to Quarter 2 (Apr to June), Q3 refers to Quarter 3 (July to Sept) and Q4 refers to Quarter 4 (Oct to Dec). UK business investment, chained volume measure, seasonally adjusted, excluding the reclassification of British Nuclear Fuels (BNFL) in Quarter 2 2005. Quarter 2 2020 was the largest fall on record for gross fixed capital formation, excluding the reclassification of British Nuclear Fuels in Quarter 2 2005. Index is referenced to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar), 1997 = 100. Download the data .xlsx This release contains data that are consistent with the UK National Accounts (also known as the Blue Book 2023), which will be released on 31 October 2023. Data for all periods in this release are subject to revision in line with the National Accounts Revision Policy. Read the full bulletin on Business investment in the UK: April to June 2023 revised results 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">47939294</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rent or mortgage payments up for nearly half of adults</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain20septemberto1october2023</link>
         <description>Rent or mortgage payments up for nearly half of adults 06 October 2023 Almost half (47%) of adults in Great Britain paying rent or a mortgage said their payments had increased in the last six months. This is according to those asked between 20 September and 1 October 2023 as part of our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin . This was 33% during a similar period last year (29 September to 9 October 2022). Among rent and mortgage payers, 40% said they were finding the payments very or somewhat difficult to afford. That was compared with 30% a year ago. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">34465739</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.2% in August 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktradeaugust2023</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.2% in August 2023 12 October 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have grown by 0.2% in August 2023, following a fall of 0.6% in July 2023. Looking at the broader picture, GDP increased by 0.3% in the three months to August 2023, with growth in all sectors. Services output grew by 0.4% in August 2023, after a fall of 0.6% in July 2023, and was the main contributor to the growth in GDP in July. Output in consumer facing services fell by 0.6% in August 2023 following a fall of 0.2% in July. Production output fell by 0.7% in August 2023, following a fall of 1.1% in July 2023. The construction sector declined by 0.5% in August 2023, following a 0.4% decrease in July 2023. Services output was the main contributor to the growth in GDP in August 2023 Contributions to monthly GDP growth, August 2022 to August 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Services output was the main contributor to the growth in GDP in August 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our latest UK monthly GDP bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top Total imports of goods from the non-EU countries rose in August 12 October 2023 Total imports of goods in &quot;current prices&quot;, which are not adjusted for inflation, increased by £0.8 billion (1.7%) in August 2023. Imports from EU countries fell by £0.2 billion, while imports from non-EU countries rose by £1.0 billion. The rise in imports from non-EU countries was mainly the result of higher imports of oil and gas. After removing the effect of inflation by calculating &quot;chained volume measures&quot;, total goods imports decreased by £0.4 billion (1.1%) in August 2023. This was because imports from the EU fell by £0.7 billion (3.2%) while imports from non-EU countries rose by £0.3 billion (1.7%). Total exports of goods decreased by £0.7 billion (2.2%) in August 2023, because of a £0.7 billion fall in exports to non-EU countries, while exports to EU countries remained stable. After the effect of inflation is removed, total goods exports fell by £1.3 billion (4.6%) in August 2023. Exports to non-EU countries decreased by £1.0 billion (7.2%) and exports to EU countries fell by £0.2 billion (1.8%). The total trade in goods and services deficit narrowed by £3.5 billion to £10.4 billion in the three months to August 2023, as imports fell by more than exports. Imports from the non-EU countries increased in August 2023, while imports from the EU countries fell EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted, January 2020 to August 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. More details can be found in our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles . Read our latest UK trade release . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">74396931</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 09:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
