<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:05:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Energy prices not main concern for businesses for first time this year</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators22june2023</link>
         <description>Energy prices not main concern for businesses for first time this year 22 June 2023 Falling demand for goods and services replaced energy prices as businesses’ main concern for the next month for the first time in 2023. As part of the Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS), businesses were asked about their main concern for the next month, July 2023. For the first time this year, energy prices were not the top reported concern. Falling demand for goods and services was reported as the main concern for the next month by 15% of businesses, up 12% from the previous month. Inflation of goods and services was reported as a main concern by 14% of businesses, down from 15% in the previous month. And energy prices were reported as a main concern by 12% of businesses, down by 15% from the previous month. The percentage of businesses that reported no concerns increased to 25% from 23% in the previous month. For the first time in 2023, energy prices were not the top reported concern for businesses when asked about their main concern for the next month Businesses’ main concern, businesses not permanently stopped trading, broken down by response option, weighted by count, UK, 1 June to 31 July 2023 Source: Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS) from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart For the first time in 2023, energy prices were not the top reported concern for businesses when asked about their main concern for the next month Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">6493298</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Shoppers buy more overall but cut back on food </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainmay2023</link>
         <description>Shoppers buy more overall but cut back on food 23 June 2023 Shoppers across Britain bought more overall in May 2023, although retailers suggest a drop in the amount bought in food stores could be down to higher prices. Retail sales volumes across Britain are estimated to have risen by 0.3% in May 2023, following a rise of 0.5% in April 2023. Non-store retail sales volumes rose by 2.7% in May because of strong sales by online retailers selling outdoor-related goods and summer clothing. This was boosted by the warm weather in the second half of the month, according to feedback from retailers. However, shoppers bought less in food stores in May, with retailers suggesting that the increased cost of living and food prices continue to affect sales. There was also some evidence that the 0.5% fall in food store sales volumes over the month could be partly down to higher spending on takeaways and fast food. This may have been because of the extra bank holiday for the coronation of King Charles III on 8 May. People are spending more in food stores but buying less Volume and value sales, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, May 2019 to May 2023 Source: Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart People are spending more in food stores but buying less Image .csv .xls The survey period included the early bank holiday on 1 May, as well as the extra one for the coronation on 8 May. Read our full Retail sales, Great Britain: May 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">3982358</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Trade surplus in all UK nations in 2021</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/internationaltradeinuknationsregionsandcities2021</link>
         <description>Trade surplus in all UK nations in 2021 28 June 2023 There was a trade surplus in England, Northern Ireland, Scotland and Wales in 2021. This means that the value of goods and services exported from each nation was higher than the value of goods and services imported to each nation. England had a trade deficit until the onset of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, when the value of imports fell by more than the value of exports. Compared with before the pandemic (2018), exports increased in London, the North West, Scotland and the East of England, but fell in all other nations and English regions. Total exports in London, East of England, the North West and Scotland have returned to pre-pandemic levels Total trade exports by International Territorial Level (ITL) 1 region, UK, 2018 to 2021 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: Extra-regio includes parts of the national economic territory which cannot be attached directly to a single region including some offshore oil transactions and territorial enclaves. Download the data .xlsx In London, the rise was driven by exports of services, while increases in Scotland and the North East were driven by exports in goods. In the East of England, exports of both goods and services rose. The region is home to multiple medical, pharmaceutical and bioscientific research institutions, which may have boosted exports in response to the pandemic. Meanwhile, imports fell in all nations and English regions, with the largest falls in the South East and the West Midlands. Read our bulletin on International trade in UK nations, regions and cities: 2021 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">92078388</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Signs of improvement for businesses </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy29june2023</link>
         <description>Signs of improvement for businesses 29 June 2023 While business conditions remain challenging, there have been signs of improvement, according to our latest Business Insights and Conditions Survey . More than two-thirds (68%) of businesses with 10 or more employees were able to get the goods they needed from within the UK in May 2023 without any form of disruption (up 3 percentage points from April 2023). A further 13% of businesses reported they had to change suppliers or find alternative solutions to get the goods they required. A similar proportion, 67% of businesses, reported some form of concern for their business for July 2023. The is the lowest percentage reported since late March 2022. Around 1 in 8 (13%) businesses reported that their employees' hourly wages had increased in May 2023 compared with April 2023: this was 22% for businesses with 10 or more employees. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">25872886</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around half of adults see rises in rent or mortgage payments </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain14to25june2023</link>
         <description>Around half of adults see rises in rent or mortgage payments 30 June 2023 Around half (47%) of adults in Great Britain have seen rises in their rent or mortgage payments in the past six months. This is according to our latest Public opinions and social trends survey , carried out between 14 and 25 June 2023. It is up from 30% of those asked in June 2022 who said that they had seen rises in the previous six months. There has been a corresponding rise among those saying that they are finding it difficult to afford their rent or mortgage payments. In the latest period, 43% said that they were finding these payments very or somewhat difficult, up from a quarter (25%) in June 2022. Among those surveyed in the latest period, 1 in 50 (2%) said that they were behind on their rent or mortgage payments. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">96406868</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Output per hour worked decreased in Quarter 1 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/productivityoverviewukjanuarytomarch2023</link>
         <description>Output per hour worked decreased in Quarter 1 2023 07 July 2023 Labour productivity in the UK, measured as output per hour worked, was 0.6% below in the year to Quarter 1 (Jan to Mar) 2023 when compared with the same quarter a year ago. The decrease was driven by growth in hours worked (0.8%) being larger than growth in gross value added (GVA), which was at 0.2%. Excluding the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic period, Quarter 1 2023 saw the largest fall in output per hour worked since Quarter 1 2013. Compared with pre-pandemic levels (2019 average), output per hour worked grew 0.6% in Quarter 1 2023. This growth was driven by an increase of GVA of 0.6% since 2019. The number of hours worked remained constant over this period, with a growth of 0.0%. Other measures of productivity, such as output per worker and output per job, were 0.9% and 1.0% below their respective Quarter 1 2022 levels. This is because of higher growth in the number of workers (1.1%) and jobs (1.2%) than in GVA (0.2%). Administrative service and construction industries made the biggest upwards industry contribution to annual productivity growth (output per hour worked) as of Quarter 1 2023. In contrast, finance and insurance and real estate industries showed the biggest negative contribution to productivity growth. Read our latest Productivity overview, UK bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">6818183</guid>
         <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 09:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
