<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Second highest April borrowing on record</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Second highest April borrowing on record 23 May 2023 In April 2023, the public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income, requiring it to borrow £25.6 billion, £11.9 billion more than in April last year. This was the second highest April borrowing on record, behind that of April 2020, and £3.1 billion more than forecast by the Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR). Borrowing in the financial year ending March 2023 (FYE 2023), remained the fourth highest in any financial year on record, after provisional estimates were revised down this month. The second provisional estimate reduced our first estimate by £2.1billion to £137.1 billion borrowed in the FYE 2023, largely because of new tax information. This means borrowing in the financial year to 2023 remained high, behind FYE 2021 (during the COVID-19 pandemic) and both FYE 2010 and 2011 (after the effects of the global financial downturn). The Office for Budget Responsibility predicts final public sector borrowing in the FYE 2023 will be £152.4 billion, £15.3 billion higher than our current estimate. Debt at the end of April 2023 was £2,536.9 billion or 99.2 % of the UK’s annual gross domestic product (GDP). Debt is only one of several measures of the public sector balance sheet. In April 2023 we expanded our balance sheet presentation to include Public sector net worth, which we explain in our blog What the UK government owns and what it owes . Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">18424192</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukapril2023</link>
         <description>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace 24 May 2023 Annual growth in UK house prices has continued to slow as the average cost of a home fell for the fourth consecutive month. The average price of a UK house was £285,000 in March 2023. This is £11,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £8,000 less than the recent peak in November 2022. This represents an average increase of 4.1% in the year to March 2023, down from growth of 5.8% in the year to February 2023. Average UK house prices grew 4.1% in the 12 months to March 2023 Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to March 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices grew 4.1% in the 12 months to March 2023 Image .csv .xls London saw the lowest growth rate of any UK nation or region in the year to March 2023, at 1.5%. However, London property prices remain the most expensive of any region, with an average price of £523,000 in March 2023. The South West had the highest house price growth of any UK nation or region in the year to March 2023, at 5.4%. Meanwhile, private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 4.8% in the year to April 2023. This is the largest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 4.7% in England, 4.8% in Wales and 5.2% in Scotland in the year to April 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since January 2006 in England, since January 2010 in Wales, and since January 2012 in Scotland. Both London and Yorkshire and The Humber had the largest growth in private rental prices of any region in the year to April 2023, at 5.0%. This is the second consecutive month that private rental prices in London have been growing at a faster annual rate than the UK average, last seen in December 2016. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top Inflation eased further in April 2023 24 May 2023 The cost of goods and services rose at a slower rate in the year to April 2023 as inflation continues to ease. The Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH) rose by 7.8% in the 12 months to April 2023, down from 8.9% in March and from a recent peak of 9.6% in October 2022. The October 2022 rate was the highest rate in over 40 years, according to indicative modelled estimates of consumer price inflation . Inflation rates continue to ease in April 2023 CPIH, OOH component and CPI annual inflation rates for the last 10 years, UK, April 2013 to April 2023 Source: Consumer price inflation from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Inflation rates continue to ease in April 2023 Image .csv .xls The CPIH annual inflation rate for housing, water, electricity, gas and other fuels was 7.3% in April 2023, down from a peak of 11.8% in January 2023 and a rise of 11.6% in March 2023. Monthly gas prices fell by 1.0% between March and April this year, compared with a rise of 66.8% between the same two months a year ago. This was the first time since October 2020 that monthly gas prices fell. Electricity prices also fell by 1.1% between March and April this year, compared with a rise of 40.5% between the same two months a year ago. Read our latest Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">3586395</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Gas and Electricity prices at lowest level of 2023 to date</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/economicoutputandproductivity/output/bulletins/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators/latest</link>
         <description>Gas and Electricity prices at lowest level of 2023 to date 25 May 2023 The System Average Price (SAP) of gas and the System Price (SP) of electricity are at their lowest level of 2023 to date. In the week to 21 May 2023, the SAP and SP fell by 16% and 25% respectively in comparison with the previous week. Both prices have been falling since mid-December 2022, according to data from the National Gas Transmission and Elexon. In the week to 21 May 2023, the SP of electricity decreased by 25% compared with the previous week and was 40% below the level in the equivalent week of 2022. This price is 82% lower than the peak level seen in mid-December 2022, the lowest it has been this year. The SAP of gas fell by 16% in the week to 21 May 2023 when compared with the previous week, continuing the downward trend observed since mid-December 2022. This was the largest week on week decrease since 1 January 2023 (20%). This price is also 20% below the level seen in the equivalent week of 2022 and is 85% below the weekly peak level seen in late August 2022. Read the latest Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">41036482</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Travel to and from the UK closer to 2019 levels</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/businessindustryandtrade/retailindustry/bulletins/retailsales/latest</link>
         <description>Travel to and from the UK closer to 2019 levels 26 May 2023 Visits to and from the UK last year were significantly up on 2021 but still well below the levels recorded before the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Spending on visits to and from the UK was also higher but remained short of the estimated totals for 2019. The number of visits made by overseas residents to the UK in 2022 was 31.2 million. This was much higher than the 6.4 million recorded in 2021, when pandemic-related restrictions affected travel. Despite the rise, the number was still below 40.9 million in 2019, according to estimates from our International Passenger Survey. Visits to and from the UK remain below the 2019 peak Overseas and UK residents’ visits to and from the UK, 2001 to 2022 Source: International Travel and Tourism from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Visits to and from the UK remain below the 2019 peak Image .csv .xls Overseas residents spent £26.5 billion on their visits to the UK in 2022, which was up from just £5.6 billion in 2021, but still 7% below the £28.4 billion spent in 2019. UK residents' visits abroad also increased significantly between 2021 and 2022, from 19.1 million to 71.0 million, although that was still 24% less than the 93.1 million visits in 2019. Spending by UK residents followed a similar pattern, rising by £43.0 billion from £15.5 billion in 2021 to £58.5 billion in 2022, but remaining below 2019 spending levels (£62.3 billion). Read our Travel trends: 2022 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Retail sales volumes rebound after March bad weather 26 May 2023 Retail sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought) in Great Britain have bounced back after poor weather resulted in a decline in March 2023. Our latest data show that sales volumes increased by 0.5% in April 2023, compared with a fall of 1.2% (revised from 0.9%) in March. Sales volumes have also risen an estimated 0.8% in the three months to April 2023 – the highest three-monthly increase since August 2021 (1.3%). Non-food stores sales volumes increased by an estimated 1.0% in April 2023, after poor weather contributed to a fall of 1.8% in March. Strong sales in shops selling watches and jewellery, and sports equipment helped contribute to the rise. Meanwhile, food stores sales volumes rose by an estimated 0.7% in April 2023, following a fall of 0.8% the previous month. Sales volumes were 2.7% below their pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) February 2020 levels. When compared with their pre-coronavirus February 2020 level, total retail sales were 16.5% higher in value terms but volume was 0.8% lower. Read the latest Retail Sales, Great Britain release 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">79338254</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Household spending rose 6% in year to March 2022, adjusted for inflation</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/articles/theoccupationsmostdependentonolderandyoungerworkers/2023-05-31</link>
         <description>Household spending rose 6% in year to March 2022, adjusted for inflation 31 May 2023 UK households spent £528.80 per week on average in the financial year ending (FYE) March 2022. This is £47.30 (10%) higher than in FYE 2021, but £59.10 (10%) lower than in FYE 2020, before the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Inflation (changes in the cost of goods and services), accounted for some of this change: average weekly spending was £28.80 (6%) higher in FYE 2022 after adjusting for inflation, and was £78.80 (13%) below FYE 2020. A number of factors could have driven higher spending. Some restrictions put in place to curb the spread of COVID-19 were eased, meaning there was more opportunity to socialise indoors and attend large events. Higher costs also affected households, with domestic energy prices rising in the last six months of FYE 2022. The average (mean) household disposable income in FYE 2022 (the money available after direct taxes have been accounted for) remained similar to the previous year, after adjusting for inflation. In financial year ending (FYE) 2022, average weekly expenditure increased by 6% while average household disposable income remained stable Inflation-adjusted average household weekly expenditure and average household weekly disposable income in the UK, FYE 2002 to FYE 2022, at FYE 2022 prices Source: Household Finances Survey and Living Costs and Food Survey from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart In financial year ending (FYE) 2022, average weekly expenditure increased by 6% while average household disposable income remained stable Image .csv .xls The biggest contributions to increases in spending were in transport, recreation and culture, and restaurants and hotels. Meanwhile, average spending on food and non-alcoholic drinks fell. The largest proportion of household expenditure went on housing, fuel and power (17%), followed by transport (14%). Read the full bulletin on Family spending in the UK: April 2021 to March 2022 . 🠕 Back to the top Digital jobs younger in age profile than print-related roles 31 May 2023 Typists and bookbinders might be giving way to data entry and analysis, Census 2021 data show. Digital information jobs, such as “data analyst” and “actuaries, economists and statisticians” had younger age profiles compared with print-related roles. “Business and related research professionals”, another category that was relatively young, includes social media analysts and games researchers. However, print information jobs such as “librarians” were generally older in age profile Digital data jobs are more popular than print-related jobs among younger people Proportion of working adults employed in selected print and digital information occupations, England and Wales, Census 2021 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Analysis included the 27.8 million people aged 16 years and over who said they were in employment at the time of the census, in March 2021. People on furlough were asked to record their employment as ongoing, but some people may have said they were out of work instead. For more than 400 occupations, we looked at differences in age profile, how work varies for men and women, and types of employment. We found that younger women were more likely than older women to work in engineering, that two-fifths of farmers were aged 60 years or older, and that the most common job was “sales and retail assistant”. Use our interactive tool, &quot;How many people do my job?&quot; to find out more about the people in a particular role. For more information, read our The occupations more dependent on older and younger workers article. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">87929908</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around 3 in 10 workers think their job is at least partly “green”</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/deprivationinequalitiesinexperiencesofyoungpeoplewhowerestudyingfortheirgcsesduringthepandemicenglandseptember2021tomarch2022</link>
         <description>Around 3 in 10 workers think their job is at least partly “green” 2 June 2023 Around 3 in 10 working adults in Britain would describe any part of their job as “green”. Some 29% of working adults said that their job involved helping to protect or contribute towards the environment, such as helping to combat climate change or improve the natural environment. That is according to our latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey conducted between 17 and 29 May 2023. Around 1 in 25 working adults (4%) reported all or most of their job related to “green” activities. Around 1 in 7 (15%) said that they worked for an organisation that did specific green activities but that their own work was not directly related to this. The survey also asked people about their cost of living, with around two-thirds (67%) of adults saying it had increased when compared with a month ago. Of those who said that their cost of living had risen, 97% said increases in the price of food shopping was a reason for the rise. This was followed by 69% who cited rising gas or electricity bills, and 40% who said an increase in the price of fuel was a factor. Read our Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 17 to 29 May 2023 bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top Pupils in more deprived areas of England felt more behind after lockdowns 2 June 2023 Students in the most deprived areas were more likely to report they had fallen behind their classmates because of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. A study of student experiences during national lockdown periods examined the availability of online learning, study support and students’ plans for their future. It found that pupils in the most deprived areas were less likely than those in the least deprived areas to be provided with online learning for lessons during the third lockdown. Activities to help students catch up on missed or disrupted learning during the pandemic were more commonly reported in the most deprived areas, where there was also a higher take up among students of this support. Two-fifths of students (42%) in the most deprived areas said they had fallen behind their classmates during the coronavirus pandemic Proportions of students in England who agreed with the following statements around catch-up concerns, September 2021 to March 2022 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Overall, nearly four in five pupils (79%) said that their progress during Year 11 had suffered as a result of the coronavirus pandemic. Read the full article Deprivation inequalities in the experiences of GCSE students during coronavirus (COVID-19) . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">17253699</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Households are still the largest contributor to UK emissions</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/ukenvironmentalaccounts2023</link>
         <description>Households are still the largest contributor to UK emissions 5 June 2023 UK greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions on a residence basis – a different measure from the territorial measure often used relating to UK residents and UK-registered businesses, regardless of whether they are in the UK or overseas – increased by 3% between 2020 and 2021, to just over 502 million tonnes of carbon dioxide equivalent (Mt Co2e). Households, through consumer expenditure, are the largest single contributor to UK emissions. In 2021, emissions related to consumer expenditure – primarily from heating homes and travelling – reached 26% of the total. The second-highest emitter was the energy sector, at 17% of the total. The transport sector’s emissions reduced by 9% in 2021 following a 28% fall in 2020; the largest decrease (34%) of all sectors since 2019. Households remain the highest contributors to overall UK greenhouse gas emissions in 2021 Trend for Greenhouse gas emissions for the three highest-emitting industries, and households, UK, 1990 to 2021 Source: UK Environmental Accounts from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Households remain the highest contributors to overall UK greenhouse gas emissions in 2021 Image .csv .xls A reduction in overall UK GHG emission intensity would in theory indicate that the UK is moving towards a lower carbon economy. In 2021, the UK emitted 0.19 thousand tonnes of CO2e per £ million of gross value added (GVA) on a residence basis: a drop of 67% since 1990. Agriculture, forestry and fishing was the most emission-intensive industry in 2021 after surpassing electricity, gas, steam and air conditioning supply in 2016. This is likely a combination of the agriculture industry being the heaviest emitter of methane, a potent GHG, and the reduction in emission intensity from the electricity industry. Most GHG emissions are related to energy use. The UK used a total of almost 176 million tonnes of oil equivalent (Mtoe) of energy in 2021, with 80% coming from fossil fuels. Energy from renewable sources accounted for 13% of all energy use in the UK in 2021, compared with 0.9% in 1990. The environmental goods and services sector (EGSS) statistics measure 17 activities across the economy that produce goods and services for environmental protection and resource management purposes. Read our UK Environmental Accounts: 2023 release . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">17731644</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 09:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
