<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Value of UK goods imports and exports rose in 2022</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktradeingoodsyearinreview2022</link>
         <description>Value of UK goods imports and exports rose in 2022 17 February 2023 The value of total goods imports increased by £155.5 billion (32.3%) and the value of total goods exports increased by £66.2 billion (20.8%) in 2022 when compared with 2021. However, after removing the effect of inflation (the rising price of goods and services), total goods imports increased by £53.2 billion (11.5%) and total goods exports increased by just £9.1 billion (2.9%) compared with 2021. The Russian invasion of Ukraine was a leading contributor to higher prices. It disrupted trade in multiple commodities, forced the UK to change some trade partners and led to increased import prices. The value of fuel imports increased by £63.6 billion (119.1%) in 2022 when compared with 2021, driven by European gas prices reaching record levels. High fuel prices also had a knock-on effect on the price of other commodities because of increased transport and production costs. In December 2022, the Sterling to Euro exchange rate stood at 1.16, while the Sterling to Dollar exchange rate stood at 1.21. In both cases, these rates are down compared with the average exchange rate in 2021. Weaker exchange rates will have made the prices of imports higher while reducing the prices of UK exports. Read our UK trade in goods, year in review: 2022 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88839518</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Renters and parents more likely to be financially vulnerable</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/personalandhouseholdfinances/expenditure/articles/impactofincreasedcostoflivingonadultsacrossgreatbritain/september2022tojanuary2023</link>
         <description>Renters and parents more likely to be financially vulnerable 20 February 2023 Renters, younger adults (aged 25 to 34 years) and parents living with dependent children were among the groups most likely to experience some form of financial vulnerability. Adults were considered to have experienced some form of financial vulnerability if three or more of the following applied to them: being unable to afford an unexpected, but necessary, expense of £850 borrowing more money or using more credit than usual in the last month, compared with a year ago being unable to save in the next 12 months finding it very or somewhat difficult to afford energy bills Adults aged 25 to 34 years had the highest odds of experiencing some form of financial vulnerability compared with those aged 75 years and over. Parents living with dependent children and those on lower incomes were also more likely to have experienced financial vulnerability than those without or not living with dependent children, or those earning more than £50,000 per year. Renters had four times the odds of experiencing some form of financial vulnerability than those who owned their homes outright. Read our Impact of increased cost of living on adults across Great Britain: September 2022 to January 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">94378693</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Record self-assessment receipts contribute to a January surplus</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicsectorfinancesukjanuary2023</link>
         <description>Record self-assessment receipts contribute to a January surplus 21 February 2023 In January 2023, the public sector spent less than it received in taxes and other income, resulting in a surplus of £5.4 billion. The UK government receives most of its annual self-assessed tax receipts in January. This year these receipts were partly offset by substantial spending on the energy support schemes and large one-off payments relating to historic customs duties owed to the EU. Self-assessed income tax receipts were £21.9 billion in January 2023. This is the highest January figure since monthly records began in April 1999, and £5.5 billion or one-third higher than in January 2022. The £5.4 billion surplus in January 2023, combined with a reduction of £5.8 billion to our previously published financial year-to-December borrowing estimate, brings the total borrowed in the financial year-to-January to £116.9 billion. This was £7.0 billion more than was borrowed in the same period last year, but £30.6 billion below the official forecast on a like-for-like basis. Debt at the end of January was £2.5 trillion (£2,492.1 billion) or 98.9% of the UK’s annual gross domestic product (GDP). Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">85017606</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Winter spending rises as inflation drives up prices</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/howhasdiscretionaryspendingbeenimpactedinrecentwinters</link>
         <description>Winter spending rises as inflation drives up prices 21 February 2023 Non-essential consumer spending on sales days such as Boxing Day and Black Friday rose in winter 2022 to 2023, despite overall spending power being eroded. In the year to January 2023 retail sales values rose by 4.1% while sales volumes fell by 5.1%, as consumers spend more and buy less. Spending data from Revolut show consumer spending patterns in winter 2022-23 were generally in line with previous winters, despite cost of living pressures and widespread industrial action, alongside factors specific to this winter. Clothing and footwear sales volumes unexpectedly rose in November and December 2022, by 1.1% and 1.0% respectively. They peaked on Black Friday (25 November 2022) at 31.3% higher than Boxing Day and 77.0% higher than New Year’s Day. The week to Christmas Eve 2022 provided the largest cash value ever recorded for a trading week in the food sector, partly due to inflation, with the amount sold being similar to previous years. Industrial action carried out by rail and postal workers appears to have had no significant negative impact on travel spending, or in-store shopping, and the first ever winter FIFA World Cup did not result in substantial increases in spending on entertainment. Read our full article on How has discretionary spending been impacted in recent winters 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">91324250</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Adults under financial pressures report higher anxiety and lower happiness</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/wellbeing/articles/howarefinancialpressuresaffectingpeopleingreatbritain/february2023</link>
         <description>Adults under financial pressures report higher anxiety and lower happiness 22 February 2023 Adults in Great Britain who report borrowing more money or using more credit in the last month compared with a year ago were twice as likely to report low levels of happiness, compared with those who are not borrowing more money. A fifth of adults (22%) who reported borrowing more money or using more credit than usual in the last month, compared with a year ago, between 14 September 2022 and 8 January 2023 also reported low levels of happiness, compared with 11% of those who were not borrowing more. Those who were borrowing more money were also more likely than those who were not to report high levels of anxiety. More than 4 in 10 adults who were borrowing more money or using more credit reported high levels of anxiety Wellbeing measures by whether respondent was borrowing more money or using more credit in the last month compared with a year ago, Great Britain, 14 September 2022 to 8 January 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Adults who reported being behind on their energy bills, or struggling to afford their energy or rent or mortgage payments, were also more likely to report lower levels of happiness and higher levels of anxiety. More than a fifth of adults in Great Britain (22%, equal to around 11.5 million people) reported borrowing more money or using more credit than usual in the last month, compared with a year ago, when surveyed between 25 January and 5 February 2023. This is an increase from 17% of adults surveyed the year before (between 19 and 30 January 2022). Read our full article on How are financial pressures affecting people in Great Britain 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">98169981</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rise in young people not in education, employment or training</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy23february2023</link>
         <description>Rise in young people not in education, employment or training 23 February 2023 The number of young people who are not in education, employment or training (NEET) has risen by more than 60,000 in the past three months. A total of 788,000 people aged 16 to 24 were estimated to be NEET from October to December 2022, up from 724,000 in the previous quarter a – an increase of 64,000. This means that NEET young people now make up an estimated 11.5% of the UK's population of 16- to 24-year-olds. The number of male and female NEETs both rose by 32,000 in the last quarter. Of the total number of NEETs, 416,000 were men and 372,000 were women. There has also been an increase in the number of young people who were NEET and unemployed. In October to December 2022, this figure was estimated to be 299,000, an increase of 32,000 on the previous quarter. Read our Young people not in education, employment or training (NEET), UK: February 2022 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Valentine’s Day brings spending boost 23 February 2023 Spending in pubs, restaurants and fast food chains rose in the week of Valentine’s Day, helping a general rise in debit card spending. Revolut data show a rise in debit card spending of 5 percentage points in the week to 19 February 2023. The largest rise was among pubs, restaurants and fast food, where spending rose 15 percentage points on the previous week. According to data from OpenTable , in the same period the number of UK seated diners increased by 23 percentage points from the previous week. This was in line with expected trends because of a rise in the number of diners on Valentine’s Day. Overall retail footfall increased in the week to 19 February 2023 to 108% of the level of the previous week and 123% of the level in the equivalent week of 2022. Read our latest Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top More than one in three trading businesses pass on price rises 23 February 2023 More than a third (34%) of UK businesses not permanently stopped trading say they have passed on price increases to customers over the last six months. A quarter (25%) of trading businesses also expect to increase their prices in March 2023, according to our latest business insights and conditions survey. Energy prices remain the top reason trading businesses are considering doing so, with 35% citing this reason. For trading businesses in the accommodation and food service activities (hospitality) industry, 45% expect a rise in prices. We urge caution when interpreting questions on future expectations as the employees responding to the survey may not always have full oversight of the business. Hospitality businesses were most likely to expect to raise their prices in March 2023 Price expectations, businesses currently trading, broken down by industry, weighted by count, UK, 1 to 31 March 2023 Source: Office for National Statistics – Business Insights and Conditions Survey Download this chart Hospitality businesses were most likely to expect to raise their prices in March 2023 Image .csv .xls The survey data also show that more than a quarter (28%) of businesses not permanently stopped trading with 10 or more employees reported they had found it difficult to recruit new staff in January 2023. For the same month, nearly 3 in 10 trading businesses (29%) reported lower turnover (the amount of money taken) compared with December 2022. However, trading businesses were more optimistic about their turnover for March 2023. A fifth (21%) of businesses reported that they expect their turnover to increase over the month, up from 10% reported for January 2023. Read our latest Business insights and impact on the UK economy: 23 February 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">41962750</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Students hit by rising cost of living</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/costoflivingandhighereducationstudentsengland30januaryto13february2023</link>
         <description>Students hit by rising cost of living 24 February 2023 More than 9 in 10 university students in England say their cost of living has risen over the last year, with many worried it will negatively affect their studies. Some 92% of higher education students said their cost of living had increased compared with last year, according to a survey carried out between 30 January and 13 February 2023. Around half (49%) felt they had financial difficulties, with 33% saying these were minor and 16% saying they had major money problems. The survey data suggest this may be leading to higher debt levels, with 3 in 10 students (30%) saying they had taken on new debt in response to rising living costs, up from 25% in early November 2022. Of those, 71% said this was because their student loan did not cover their living costs. More than three-quarters (78%) of students were concerned that rising prices may affect how well they do in their studies, while more than a third (35%) reported they are now less likely to do further study after finishing their course. This could be affecting students’ mental health, with around 46% reporting their mental health and well-being had worsened since the start of the Autumn term 2022. Read our Cost of living and higher education students: England, 30 January to 13 February 2023 bulletin. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">49632342</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around 1 in 11 adults report running out of food</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/trackingtheimpactofwinterpressuresingreatbritain18to29january2023</link>
         <description>Around 1 in 11 adults report running out of food 27 February 2023 Adults across Britain are experiencing food insecurity and are having to cut down on portion sizes or skip meals altogether. Around 1 in 11 adults (9%) reported they had often or sometimes run out of food and could not afford to buy more in the past month. That is according to figures from our Winter Survey tracking the impact of winter pressures, which were collected from 18 to 29 January 2023. Around one in eight (13%) said they had cut down on meal sizes or skipped meals altogether in the past month because there was not enough money for food. Of those, 21% reported having done so on more than 14 days in the month. The survey also shows that nearly one in five adults (18%) waiting for NHS treatment say they had an appointment cancelled or delayed in the past month. Around 3 in 10 (31%) employed or self-employed adults who were waiting for NHS treatment said it had affected their work. Reasons their work was affected that they cited included having to change working tasks, not going for promotion or training opportunities, and finding new employment. Read our Tracking the impact of winter pressures in Great Britain: 18 to 29 January 2023 bulletin. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">77928343</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
