<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 09:05:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Long-term sickness pushes more people out of labour market </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/risingillhealthandeconomicinactivityduetolongtermsicknessuk2019to2023</link>
         <description>Long-term sickness pushes more people out of labour market 26 July 2023 More than 2.5 million people across the UK were neither working nor looking for work because of long-term sickness in the three months to May 2023. It means the number of working-age people out of the labour market (known as “economically inactive”) has risen by more than 400,000 since the start of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Economic inactivity linked to long-term sickness is rising Cumulative change in economic inactivity (seasonally adjusted), people aged 16 to 64 years, December to February 2020 to March to May 2023 Source: Labour Force Survey from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Economic inactivity linked to long-term sickness is rising Image .csv .xls Overall, 36% of working-age people said that they had at least one long-term health condition between January and March 2023. This was up from 31% in the same period of 2019, and 29% in the same period of 2016. During the same period, more than 1.35 million (53%) of those inactive because of long-term sickness reported that they had depression, bad nerves or anxiety. The majority of those (more than 1 million) said it was a secondary health condition rather than their main one. Read our article on Rising ill-health and economic inactivity because of long-term sickness 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">27022529</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 09:05:39 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Business creations and closures fell compared with a year ago </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/housingpurchaseaffordabilitygreatbritain2022</link>
         <description>Business creations and closures fell compared with a year ago 27 July 2023 The number of new businesses in the UK has dropped in the space of a year. Experimental figures from the Inter-Departmental Business Register (IDBR) showed that there were 77,095 businesses created between Quarter 2 (Apr to Jun) 2023 and Quarter 2 2022. This is a drop of 14% and is the second lowest number of business creations in a second quarter since the start of this series in 2017. The number of business creations decreased in 14 out of 16 industry groups this quarter when compared with Quarter 2 2022. The most significant decrease came in the transport and storage industry, where business creations were down by 59%. The number of business closures in the UK in Quarter 2 2023 was 84,150. This is 15% lower than in Quarter 2 2022. The number of business closures decreased in 14 out of 16 main industrial groups. The most significant decrease in closures came in the professional, scientific and technical industry (down 25%). This is now the eighth quarter in a row where there have been more closures than creations. The statistics presented are Experimental Statistics , so care needs to be taken when interpreting them. Our annual business demography publication remains the best source of information on business demography. Read our full Business demography, quarterly experimental statistics, UK: April to June 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Average homes across UK cost more than five years’ income 27 July 2023 Since 2017, the affordability ratio (how many “years of income” the average house price represents) in all UK nations has remained above five, making them outside the Office for National Statistic’s broad threshold for what is affordable. In England, it has been above five since 2002. In the year to March 2022, the average house price in England was £275,000, or 8.4 years of income for the average household. In Wales, the average house price was 6.4 times the average income. In Scotland, it was 5.3 times the average income and in Northern Ireland it was 5.1 times the average income. For households with the lowest incomes, the average home in England cost 19 years of income. England had the widest range in housing affordability of all UK nations Number of years income applied to the equivalent cost of an average price home, by income decile and by country, 2022 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Read our full Housing Purchase Affordability in the UK, 2022 article 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">68568187</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 09:05:39 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Two-fifths struggling with rent or mortgage </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain12to23july2023</link>
         <description>Two-fifths struggling with rent or mortgage 28 July 2023 Some 4 in 10 renters or mortgage holders (40%) across Britain are finding it difficult to afford their payments. That is according to our latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey for the period 12 to 23 July 2023. The figure has increased from around 3 in 10 (31%) in July 2022. Among those currently paying rent or a mortgage, over 4 in 10 (45%) reported that their rent or mortgage payments had gone up in the past six months. Overall, around 6 in 10 adults (59%) reported that their cost of living had increased when compared with a month ago. However, this proportion appears to have gradually dropped since early April 2023, when it was at 76%. For more information, read our Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 12 to 23 July 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">3335204</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 09:05:39 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Most businesses have not assessed key climate change risks</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy10august2023</link>
         <description>Most businesses have not assessed key climate change risks 10 August 2023 Three-quarters (75%) of UK businesses in our latest business insights survey said that they had not assessed the risks of certain climate change effects. These effects included water scarcity, coastal erosion, increased flooding and temperature increases. Our Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS) for late July 2023 does not cover all sectors of the economy so the results reflect only those surveyed. Of those businesses that had assessed these risks of climate change, 28% had not taken any action, 18% did not expect to be impacted, while 18% reported they had been unable to take action, either due to costs or the lack of information or guidance. Our survey also showed that in late July 2023, 21% of businesses reported that they were using, or intending to use, increased homeworking as a permanent business model, with reduced overheads (51%) and improved staff well-being (47%) reported as the main reasons. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">88644194</guid>
         <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 09:05:39 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
