<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Record high number inactive because of long term sickness </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uklabourmarketmay2023</link>
         <description>Record high number inactive because of long term sickness 16 May 2023 Labour market data show the economic inactivity rate fell by 0.4 percentage points on the quarter, to 21.0% in January to March 2023. However, those inactive because of long term sickness reached a record high in the same period. Flows estimates show that between October to December and for January to March 2023 there has been a record high net flow of people moving out of economic inactivity. This has largely been driven by people moving from economic inactivity into employment. The UK employment rate was estimated at 75.9% in January to March 2023, with a 0.2 percentage point rise from October to December 2022. This was driven by rises in part-time employees and self-employed workers. Read our latest UK Labour Market bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">671065</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Consumer behaviour indicators decrease</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators18may2023</link>
         <description>Consumer behaviour indicators decrease 18 May 2023 UK consumer behaviour indicator activity has decreased in the latest week, coinciding with the coronation of King Charles III and Camilla, Her Majesty the Queen. In the latest week there were notable falls in spending, potentially also driven by usual within month spending patterns. The aggregate CHAPS-based indicator of credit and debit card purchases decreased by 10 points in the week to 11 May 2023 according to data from the Bank of England. The monthly indicator in April 2023 was 1 percentage point higher than in April 2022. Of the four CHAPS spending categories, “staple” and “work related” both saw an increase, at 12 and 4 percentage points. Meanwhile, “delayable” decreased by 9 percentage points and “social” remained unchanged compared with April 2022. Revolut debit card spending decreased by 10 percentage points in the week to 14 May 2023 compared with the previous week. It was 17 percentage points higher than the equivalent period last year. Five of the six Revolut spending categories saw decreases in debit card spending when compared with the previous week. The biggest decreases were in the “retail” and “pubs, restaurants, and fast food” categories, decreasing 16 and 10 percentage points, respectively. Entertainment was the only category to see an increase, rising by 4 percentage points. Overall retail footfall decreased in the week to 14 May 2023 to 96% of the level of the previous week but was 101% of the level in the equivalent week last year, according to data from Springboard. Read our Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">25532050</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Fewer trading businesses report being affected by price rises</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy18may2023</link>
         <description>Fewer trading businesses report being affected by price rises 18 May 2023 Business conditions continue to be affected by price rises, although there has been a steady downward trend in the number of trading businesses affected since September last year. More than a third (35%) of trading companies reported an increase in the price of goods or services bought in April 2023 compared with the previous month, according to the latest Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS) . However, this has dropped by 2 percentage points compared with March 2023 and is currently at the lowest level seen since March 2022. Almost two-thirds (63%) of businesses not permanently stopped trading reported that they have been affected by general price increases, and over a third of companies saying the same about rising energy costs in April 2023. By contrast, the proportion of trading businesses who expect to raise the prices of their goods or services in June 2023 fell by 5 percentage points, dropping from 23% to 18% compared with expectations for May 2023. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">81713071</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Cost of living increases for around two-thirds of UK adults</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain4to14may2023</link>
         <description>Cost of living increases for around two-thirds of UK adults 19 May 2023 Around two-thirds of UK adults (67%) have experienced an increased cost of living in the last month, when asked between May 4 and May 14 2023. This is according to our latest Public opinions and social trends release. The most common reasons reported by adults who said that their cost of living had increased were an increase in the price of food shopping (96%), an increase in gas or electricity bills (74%) and an increase in the price of fuel (38%). When they were asked what they feel are the most important issues facing the UK today, the most reported issues were the cost of living (91%), the NHS (82%), the economy (73%) and climate change and the environment (59%). around two-thirds (67%) said that their cost of living had increased over the past month, more than 9 in 10 (93%) said it had gone up compared with a year ago. Some of the most frequent actions adults took because of the rising cost of living included spending less on non-essentials (66%), using less fuel in the home (49%) and shopping around more (49%). Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">60244961</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Second highest April borrowing on record</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Second highest April borrowing on record 23 May 2023 In April 2023, the public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income, requiring it to borrow £25.6 billion, £11.9 billion more than in April last year. This was the second highest April borrowing on record, behind that of April 2020, and £3.1 billion more than forecast by the Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR). Borrowing in the financial year ending March 2023 (FYE 2023), remained the fourth highest in any financial year on record, after provisional estimates were revised down this month. The second provisional estimate reduced our first estimate by £2.1billion to £137.1 billion borrowed in the FYE 2023, largely because of new tax information. This means borrowing in the financial year to 2023 remained high, behind FYE 2021 (during the COVID-19 pandemic) and both FYE 2010 and 2011 (after the effects of the global financial downturn). The Office for Budget Responsibility predicts final public sector borrowing in the FYE 2023 will be £152.4 billion, £15.3 billion higher than our current estimate. Debt at the end of April 2023 was £2,536.9 billion or 99.2 % of the UK’s annual gross domestic product (GDP). Debt is only one of several measures of the public sector balance sheet. In April 2023 we expanded our balance sheet presentation to include Public sector net worth, which we explain in our blog What the UK government owns and what it owes . Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">18424192</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukapril2023</link>
         <description>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace 24 May 2023 Annual growth in UK house prices has continued to slow as the average cost of a home fell for the fourth consecutive month. The average price of a UK house was £285,000 in March 2023. This is £11,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £8,000 less than the recent peak in November 2022. This represents an average increase of 4.1% in the year to March 2023, down from growth of 5.8% in the year to February 2023. Average UK house prices grew 4.1% in the 12 months to March 2023 Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to March 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices grew 4.1% in the 12 months to March 2023 Image .csv .xls London saw the lowest growth rate of any UK nation or region in the year to March 2023, at 1.5%. However, London property prices remain the most expensive of any region, with an average price of £523,000 in March 2023. The South West had the highest house price growth of any UK nation or region in the year to March 2023, at 5.4%. Meanwhile, private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 4.8% in the year to April 2023. This is the largest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 4.7% in England, 4.8% in Wales and 5.2% in Scotland in the year to April 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since January 2006 in England, since January 2010 in Wales, and since January 2012 in Scotland. Both London and Yorkshire and The Humber had the largest growth in private rental prices of any region in the year to April 2023, at 5.0%. This is the second consecutive month that private rental prices in London have been growing at a faster annual rate than the UK average, last seen in December 2016. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top Inflation eased further in April 2023 24 May 2023 The cost of goods and services rose at a slower rate in the year to April 2023 as inflation continues to ease. The Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH) rose by 7.8% in the 12 months to April 2023, down from 8.9% in March and from a recent peak of 9.6% in October 2022. The October 2022 rate was the highest rate in over 40 years, according to indicative modelled estimates of consumer price inflation . Inflation rates continue to ease in April 2023 CPIH, OOH component and CPI annual inflation rates for the last 10 years, UK, April 2013 to April 2023 Source: Consumer price inflation from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Inflation rates continue to ease in April 2023 Image .csv .xls The CPIH annual inflation rate for housing, water, electricity, gas and other fuels was 7.3% in April 2023, down from a peak of 11.8% in January 2023 and a rise of 11.6% in March 2023. Monthly gas prices fell by 1.0% between March and April this year, compared with a rise of 66.8% between the same two months a year ago. This was the first time since October 2020 that monthly gas prices fell. Electricity prices also fell by 1.1% between March and April this year, compared with a rise of 40.5% between the same two months a year ago. Read our latest Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">3586395</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Gas and Electricity prices at lowest level of 2023 to date</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/economicoutputandproductivity/output/bulletins/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators/latest</link>
         <description>Gas and Electricity prices at lowest level of 2023 to date 25 May 2023 The System Average Price (SAP) of gas and the System Price (SP) of electricity are at their lowest level of 2023 to date. In the week to 21 May 2023, the SAP and SP fell by 16% and 25% respectively in comparison with the previous week. Both prices have been falling since mid-December 2022, according to data from the National Gas Transmission and Elexon. In the week to 21 May 2023, the SP of electricity decreased by 25% compared with the previous week and was 40% below the level in the equivalent week of 2022. This price is 82% lower than the peak level seen in mid-December 2022, the lowest it has been this year. The SAP of gas fell by 16% in the week to 21 May 2023 when compared with the previous week, continuing the downward trend observed since mid-December 2022. This was the largest week on week decrease since 1 January 2023 (20%). This price is also 20% below the level seen in the equivalent week of 2022 and is 85% below the weekly peak level seen in late August 2022. Read the latest Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">41036482</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Travel to and from the UK closer to 2019 levels</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/businessindustryandtrade/retailindustry/bulletins/retailsales/latest</link>
         <description>Travel to and from the UK closer to 2019 levels 26 May 2023 Visits to and from the UK last year were significantly up on 2021 but still well below the levels recorded before the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Spending on visits to and from the UK was also higher but remained short of the estimated totals for 2019. The number of visits made by overseas residents to the UK in 2022 was 31.2 million. This was much higher than the 6.4 million recorded in 2021, when pandemic-related restrictions affected travel. Despite the rise, the number was still below 40.9 million in 2019, according to estimates from our International Passenger Survey. Visits to and from the UK remain below the 2019 peak Overseas and UK residents’ visits to and from the UK, 2001 to 2022 Source: International Travel and Tourism from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Visits to and from the UK remain below the 2019 peak Image .csv .xls Overseas residents spent £26.5 billion on their visits to the UK in 2022, which was up from just £5.6 billion in 2021, but still 7% below the £28.4 billion spent in 2019. UK residents' visits abroad also increased significantly between 2021 and 2022, from 19.1 million to 71.0 million, although that was still 24% less than the 93.1 million visits in 2019. Spending by UK residents followed a similar pattern, rising by £43.0 billion from £15.5 billion in 2021 to £58.5 billion in 2022, but remaining below 2019 spending levels (£62.3 billion). Read our Travel trends: 2022 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Retail sales volumes rebound after March bad weather 26 May 2023 Retail sales volumes (the amount of stuff bought) in Great Britain have bounced back after poor weather resulted in a decline in March 2023. Our latest data show that sales volumes increased by 0.5% in April 2023, compared with a fall of 1.2% (revised from 0.9%) in March. Sales volumes have also risen an estimated 0.8% in the three months to April 2023 – the highest three-monthly increase since August 2021 (1.3%). Non-food stores sales volumes increased by an estimated 1.0% in April 2023, after poor weather contributed to a fall of 1.8% in March. Strong sales in shops selling watches and jewellery, and sports equipment helped contribute to the rise. Meanwhile, food stores sales volumes rose by an estimated 0.7% in April 2023, following a fall of 0.8% the previous month. Sales volumes were 2.7% below their pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) February 2020 levels. When compared with their pre-coronavirus February 2020 level, total retail sales were 16.5% higher in value terms but volume was 0.8% lower. Read the latest Retail Sales, Great Britain release 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">79338254</guid>
         <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 09:12:59 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
