<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Falling motor fuel prices help ease inflation </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukjune2023</link>
         <description>Falling motor fuel prices help ease inflation 19 July 2023 The rate at which prices of goods and services are rising eased to 7.3% in the year to June 2023, down from 7.9% in May. This is according to the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH). It has fallen from a peak in October 2022, when the annual inflation rate stood at 9.6%, the highest in over 40 years, according to indicative modelled consumer price inflation estimates . The recent easing is mainly because of falls in petrol and diesel prices. Overall, motor fuel prices fell by 22.7% in the year to June 2023, after a fall of 13.1% in May. However, core inflation, which excludes energy, food, alcohol and tobacco, remains at historic highs. Core CPIH rose by 6.4% in the year to June 2023, slightly down from 6.5% in May, which was the highest rate for more than 30 years. For more information, read our full Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">15263928</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/indexofprivatehousingrentalprices/june2023</link>
         <description>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace 19 July 2023 Annual growth in UK house prices has continued to slow. The provisional estimate for the average price of a UK house was £286,000 in May 2023. This is £6,000 higher than in the same month a year ago, but £7,000 less than the recent peak in September 2022. This represents an average increase of 1.9% in the year to May 2023 (provisional), down from growth of 3.2% in the year to April 2023 (revised estimate). Average UK house prices grew 1.9% in the 12 months to May 2023 (provisional estimate) Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to May 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices grew 1.9% in the 12 months to May 2023 (provisional estimate) Image .csv .xls Of the UK nations, the lowest annual increases in house prices were seen in England at 1.7% in the year to May 2023. However, average house prices are still higher in England than in any other nation, at £304,000. Of the English regions, the North East saw the highest house price growth in the year to May 2023 (4.0%), although house prices here remain the lowest of all English regions at £159,000. The East of England saw the lowest annual inflation (0.0%). Private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 5.1% in the year to June 2023. This is the largest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 5.1% in England, 5.8% in Wales and 5.5% in Scotland in the year to June 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since January 2006 in England, since January 2010 in Wales, and since January 2012 in Scotland. Private rental prices in London (which accounts for almost a third of UK rental expenditure ) increased by 5.3% in the 12 months to June 2023, up from an increase of 5.1% in the 12 months to May 2023. This is the highest annual percentage change in London since September 2012. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">49253274</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Net 2% of firms report decreased turnover </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators20july2023</link>
         <description>Net 2% of firms report decreased turnover 20 July 2023 A net 2% of firms in June 2023 reported decreased turnover on the previous month after seasonal adjustment, driven by a worsening picture in the services sector. This figure was down 4 percentage points from a net 2% of firms who reported increasing turnover in May 2023, though this latest figure remains within normal month-on-month variation. This was according to data from HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC). A net 2% of firms reported decreasing turnover in June 2023 Weighted Value Added Tax turnover diffusion indices, UK, January 2020 to June 2023, seasonally adjusted Embed code Embed this interactive Copy The services sector saw a net 3% of firms reporting a decrease in turnover, down from a net 2% of firms who reported increasing turnover in May 2023. It is the first time more firms in the services sector have reported decreased turnover than increased turnover since September 2022. Construction and production were the only industries where more firms reported an increase in turnover than a decrease, at net 2% and 1%, respectively. Agriculture was the only sector that showed growth in the net proportion of firms reporting an increase in turnover. The sector rose 2 percentage points in June 2023 following a rise of 6 percentage points in May 2023. This was despite the agriculture sector having 3% more firms reporting a decreased turnover than reporting an increased turnover. Read our latest Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">89082376</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Debt as percentage of GDP at levels last seen in early 1960s </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Debt as percentage of GDP at levels last seen in early 1960s 21 July 2023 The public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income in June 2023, requiring it to borrow £18.5 billion, £0.4 billion less than in June last year. This was the third highest June borrowing on record, behind that of both 2020 and 2022. It was £2.7 billion less than forecast by the Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR). This month, higher tax receipts and a substantial fall in debt interest payable compared with June 2022 were largely offset by uprated benefit payments and other costs. The interest payable on central government debt in June was £12.5 billion, the third highest in any single month on record. However, it was £7.5 billion less than the peak of £20.0 billion in June 2022. Debt at the end of June 2023 was just below £2.6 trillion and initially estimated at 100.8% of gross domestic product (GDP). Estimates of debt as a ratio of GDP should be treated as highly provisional, and likely to be revised in future publications. The last time an estimate of the debt-to-GDP ratio remained above 100% for a sustained period was in March 1961. In our What the UK government owns and what it owes blog , we explain that debt is only one of several measures of the public sector balance sheet. Our Public sector finances, UK: May 2023 statistical bulletin places these measures in context with each other. Read our latest Public sector finances, UK bulletin . 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">84421452</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Summer sales lead to national shopping boost </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainjune2023</link>
         <description>Summer sales lead to national shopping boost 21 July 2023 Summer sales at department stores and furniture shops have contributed to an overall boost in retail sales volumes. This is the highest monthly increase since February 2023. Sales volumes increased by an estimated 0.7% in June 2023, following a revised rise of 0.1% in May 2023. Sales volumes (how much people buy) increased across all main sectors except automotive fuel. Summer sales and increased footfall at department stores and furniture retailers pushed up non-food stores sales in June 2023. These rose by 1.0%, following a 0.5% fall in May 2023. Food stores sales volumes also bounced back, experiencing a 0.7% increase in June 2023 after a 0.4% fall in the previous month. Supermarkets reported that good weather and summer promotions helped sales. The only main sector not to experience a boost last month was automotive fuel stores, where sales volumes fell by 0.3%, compared with a rise of 1.7% in May. When compared with their pre-coronavirus (COVID-19) level in February 2020, total retail sales were 17.9% higher in value terms, but volumes were 0.2% lower. Higher prices mean that the amount people buy and how much they spend have got further apart Volume and value sales, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, June 2019 to June 2023 Source: Source: Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Higher prices mean that the amount people buy and how much they spend have got further apart Image .csv .xls Read our latest Retail sales, Great Britain: June 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">37087413</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Long-term sickness pushes more people out of labour market </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/risingillhealthandeconomicinactivityduetolongtermsicknessuk2019to2023</link>
         <description>Long-term sickness pushes more people out of labour market 26 July 2023 More than 2.5 million people across the UK were neither working nor looking for work because of long-term sickness in the three months to May 2023. It means the number of working-age people out of the labour market (known as “economically inactive”) has risen by more than 400,000 since the start of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Economic inactivity linked to long-term sickness is rising Cumulative change in economic inactivity (seasonally adjusted), people aged 16 to 64 years, December to February 2020 to March to May 2023 Source: Labour Force Survey from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Economic inactivity linked to long-term sickness is rising Image .csv .xls Overall, 36% of working-age people said that they had at least one long-term health condition between January and March 2023. This was up from 31% in the same period of 2019, and 29% in the same period of 2016. During the same period, more than 1.35 million (53%) of those inactive because of long-term sickness reported that they had depression, bad nerves or anxiety. The majority of those (more than 1 million) said it was a secondary health condition rather than their main one. Read our article on Rising ill-health and economic inactivity because of long-term sickness 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">27022529</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Business creations and closures fell compared with a year ago </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy27july2023</link>
         <description>Business creations and closures fell compared with a year ago 27 July 2023 The number of new businesses in the UK has dropped in the space of a year. Experimental figures from the Inter-Departmental Business Register (IDBR) showed that there were 77,095 businesses created between Quarter 2 (Apr to Jun) 2023 and Quarter 2 2022. This is a drop of 14% and is the second lowest number of business creations in a second quarter since the start of this series in 2017. The number of business creations decreased in 14 out of 16 industry groups this quarter when compared with Quarter 2 2022. The most significant decrease came in the transport and storage industry, where business creations were down by 59%. The number of business closures in the UK in Quarter 2 2023 was 84,150. This is 15% lower than in Quarter 2 2022. The number of business closures decreased in 14 out of 16 main industrial groups. The most significant decrease in closures came in the professional, scientific and technical industry (down 25%). This is now the eighth quarter in a row where there have been more closures than creations. The statistics presented are Experimental Statistics , so care needs to be taken when interpreting them. Our annual business demography publication remains the best source of information on business demography. Read our full Business demography, quarterly experimental statistics, UK: April to June 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Average homes across UK cost more than five years’ income 27 July 2023 Since 2017, the affordability ratio (how many “years of income” the average house price represents) in all UK nations has remained above five, making them outside the Office for National Statistic’s broad threshold for what is affordable. In England, it has been above five since 2002. In the year to March 2022, the average house price in England was £275,000, or 8.4 years of income for the average household. In Wales, the average house price was 6.4 times the average income. In Scotland, it was 5.3 times the average income and in Northern Ireland it was 5.1 times the average income. For households with the lowest incomes, the average home in England cost 19 years of income. England had the widest range in housing affordability of all UK nations Number of years income applied to the equivalent cost of an average price home, by income decile and by country, 2022 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Download the data .xlsx Read our full Housing Purchase Affordability in the UK, 2022 article 🠕 Back to the top Direct Debit failure rate for energy payments quadruples 27 July 2023 More than 1 in every 100 monthly electricity and gas payments made by Direct Debit failed because of insufficient funds in June 2023, according to data from Pay.UK and Vocalink. This was four times higher than in May 2020, when 0.22% of energy payments failed. The average transaction amount for gas and electricity payments has risen from £108 in May 2020 to £200 in June 2023. Average gas and electricity Direct Debit amounts have been rising steadily since September 2021, in part because of higher wholesale energy prices. The Direct Debit failure rate for electricity and gas has decreased from the previous month but remains nearly four times higher than in May 2020 Direct Debit failure, January 2019 to June 2023, non-seasonally adjusted, UK Source: Pay.uk and Vocalink Download this chart The Direct Debit failure rate for electricity and gas has decreased from the previous month but remains nearly four times higher than in May 2020 Image .csv .xls Average monthly mortgage payments made by Direct Debit have also been rising steadily, from £718 in December 2021 to £852 in June 2023. Read our full Economic activity and social change in the UK: real time indicators bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Business conditions remain challenging, with partial signs of improvement 27 July 2023 Latest results show that while business conditions continue to remain challenging, estimates indicate some signs of improvement. For example, fewer firms reported energy prices as their main concern. Looking ahead to August 2023, around two-thirds (67%) of businesses reported some form of concern for their business. This is the lowest percentage reported since late February 2022, though it is broadly stable with July 2023. Fewer than 1 in 10 businesses (9%) reported energy prices as their main concern for August 2023. This is the lowest proportion since the question was first introduced in February 2022, as presented in the Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS). More commonly reported concerns included the falling demand of goods and services (16%) and the inflation of goods and services prices (16%), although 24% of businesses reported having no concerns for their business. Around one in eight (13%) businesses were experiencing worker shortages in mid-July 2023, with 38% of those businesses reporting that employees were working increased hours as a consequence. These percentages were 29% and 53%, respectively, for businesses with 10 or more employees. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">68568187</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Two-fifths struggling with rent or mortgage </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain12to23july2023</link>
         <description>Two-fifths struggling with rent or mortgage 28 July 2023 Some 4 in 10 renters or mortgage holders (40%) across Britain are finding it difficult to afford their payments. That is according to our latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey for the period 12 to 23 July 2023. The figure has increased from around 3 in 10 (31%) in July 2022. Among those currently paying rent or a mortgage, over 4 in 10 (45%) reported that their rent or mortgage payments had gone up in the past six months. Overall, around 6 in 10 adults (59%) reported that their cost of living had increased when compared with a month ago. However, this proportion appears to have gradually dropped since early April 2023, when it was at 76%. For more information, read our Public opinions and social trends, Great Britain: 12 to 23 July 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">3335204</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
