<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Real earnings are still falling</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/uklabourmarket/latest</link>
         <description>Real earnings are still falling 13 June 2023 Average pay for UK employees rose in February to April 2023 compared with the previous year. However, after taking into account inflation (rising prices), pay actually fell in real terms. According to new labour market data, average total pay for employees (which includes bonuses) rose by 6.5% in February to April 2023, and average regular pay (excluding bonuses) rose by 7.2%. This is the largest growth rate seen outside of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. After adjusting for inflation, real-terms total pay fell by 2.0%, and real-terms regular pay fell by 1.3%. The UK employment rate rose by 0.2 percentage points, to 76.0% in February to April 2023, with the number of people in employment reaching a record high. The unemployment rate also increased by 0.1 percentage point, to 3.8%. The economic inactivity rate (those not in work and not looking for work) fell by 0.4 percentage points, to 21.0%. This was largely driven by a decrease in those who were inactive for “other reasons” or because they were looking after family or the home. Economic inactivity because of long-term sickness remained at a record high. The number of job vacancies in the UK fell by 79,000 on the quarter in March to May 2023, to 1.051 million. This was the eleventh consecutive quarterly fall in vacancies, with survey respondents continuing to cite economic pressures as a factor holding back recruitment. Read the full Labour Market Overview, UK: June 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">47760274</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.2% in April 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/uktradeapril2023</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.2% in April 2023 14 June 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP), which is the total value of goods and services produced after adjusting for inflation, is estimated to have grown by 0.2% in April 2023 after a fall of 0.3% in March. Looking at the broader picture, GDP grew by 0.1% in the three months to April 2023 compared with the three months to January 2023. Services grew by 0.3% in April 2023, after falling by 0.5% in March 2023, and was the main contributor to the growth. The largest contributions to the growth in services came from the “wholesale and retail trade; repair of motor vehicles and motorcycles” and “information and communication” sectors. Production output fell by 0.3% in April 2023, following growth of 0.7% in March 2023. Manufacturing was the largest contributor to the fall within the production sector. Construction saw a 0.6% fall in April 2023, following growth of 0.2% in March 2023. Growth in the services sector was slightly offset by falls in production and construction in April 2023 Contributions to monthly GDP growth, April 2022 to April 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics. Download this chart Growth in the services sector was slightly offset by falls in production and construction in April 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP 🠕 Back to the top Large fall in imports narrows UK trade deficit 14 June 2023 A large fall in imports in the three months to April 2023 narrowed the UK trade deficit. The total value of goods imported to the UK decreased by £14.1 billion (8.8%) and imports of services decreased by an estimated £2.2 billion (3.3%) in the three months to April 2023. Over the same period, the total value of goods exports from the UK decreased by £3.3 billion (3.4%), while exports of services fell by £0.3 billion (0.3%). The larger fall in imports meant that the total trade in goods and services deficit, the amount by which the cost of a country's imports exceeds the value of its exports, narrowed to £12.3 billion over the three months. Read our latest UK trade: April 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">21641591</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Price of food increases cost of living </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain31mayto11june2023</link>
         <description>Price of food increases cost of living 16 June 2023 The cost of living remains the most pressing issue for people in Great Britain, according to our latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey. Around 9 in 10 people (91%) who were asked about the most important issues facing the UK today cited the cost of living, when asked between 1 and 11 June 2023. Around 6 in 10 (62%) adults reported that their cost of living had increased, compared with a month ago; this proportion appears to have gradually decreased since early April 2023, when it was at 76%. Commonly reported reasons why adults said their cost of living had increased compared with a month ago were; an increase in the price of food shopping (97%), an increase in gas or electricity bills (64%), an increase in the price of fuel (39%), or an increase in their rent or mortgage costs (23%). Read our latest bulletin on Public opinions and social trends 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">32717911</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Core inflation reaches highest level in over 30 years</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/governmentpublicsectorandtaxes/publicsectorfinance/bulletins/publicsectorfinances/latest</link>
         <description>Core inflation reaches highest level in over 30 years 21 June 2023 Core inflation for the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH), which measures rising prices across goods and services excluding energy, food, alcohol, and tobacco, rose to 6.5% in the year to May 2023. This is the highest the core CPIH inflation rate has been for more than 30 years. In the same period, the annual CPIH inflation rate rose to 7.9%, up from 7.8% in April. The rise was in part because of prices rising for air travel, recreation and cultural goods and services, and second-hand cars. Prices for recreational and cultural goods and services, which include live music, games and hobbies, rose by 6.8% in the year to May 2023, the highest since August 1991. Motor fuel prices fell by 13.1% in the same period, which helped to offset these rises. Read our latest Consumer Price Inflation: May 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top Debt as a percentage of GDP is at levels last seen in the early 1960s 21 June 2023 The public sector borrowed £20.0 billion in May 2023, £10.7 billion more than in May last year, having spent more than it received in taxes and other income. This provisional estimate puts borrowing in May 2023 at the second highest of any May on record, behind that of May 2020. It is £1.7 billion more than what was forecast by the Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR). Growth in receipts of taxes and income continue to be exceeded by the additional costs of the energy support schemes and increases in both benefit payments and staff costs. These staff costs included the £2.7 billion non-consolidated National Health Service (NHS) pay deal in England. Public sector net debt at the end of May 2023 was £2,567.2 billion and initially estimated at 100.1% of the UK’s annual gross domestic product (GDP). However, this is a provisional estimate. The estimate of debt as a ratio of GDP should be treated as highly provisional. It is likely to be revised in future publications because it partly relies on GDP estimates based on the latest OBR forecast. The last time the debt-to-GDP ratio was above 100% was March 1961. During the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, early provisional estimates initially indicated that the debt-to-GDP ratio had reached this level, before being revised down when stronger GDP data replaced initial forecasts. Excluding the Bank of England, debt in May 2023 was £2,298.6 billion or provisionally around 89.6% of GDP. This was £268.6 billion (or 10.5 percentage points of GDP) lower than the wider debt measure. Debt is only one of several measures of the public sector balance sheet. In April 2023, we expanded our balance sheet presentation to include public sector net worth, which we explain in our blog, What the UK government owns and what it owes . Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">46967475</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/bulletins/indexofprivatehousingrentalprices/latest</link>
         <description>House price growth slows while private rents rise at record pace 21 June 2023 Annual growth in UK house prices has continued to slow. The average price of a UK house was £286,000 in April 2023. This is £9,000 higher than the same month a year ago, but £7,000 less than the recent peak in September 2022. This represents an average increase of 3.5% in the year to April 2023, down from growth of 4.1% in the year to March 2023. Average UK house prices grew 3.5% in the 12 months to April 2023 Annual house price rates of change for all dwellings, UK, January 2006 to April 2023 Source: UK House Price Index from the HM Land Registry, Registers of Scotland, Land and Property Services Northern Ireland, Office for National Statistics Download this chart Average UK house prices grew 3.5% in the 12 months to April 2023 Image .csv .xls Of the UK nations, the lowest annual increases in house prices were seen in Scotland and Wales, with prices increasing by 2.0% in the year to April 2023 in both nations. Of the English regions, the North West saw the highest house price growth in the year to April 2023 (5.5%), while London saw the lowest annual inflation (2.4%). We have also published data on House price statistics for smaller areas in England and Wales , for the year ending December 2022. Private rental prices paid by tenants in the UK increased by 5.0% in the year to May 2023. This is the largest annual percentage change since this UK series began in January 2016. Private rent prices rose 4.9% in England, 5.0% in Wales and 5.4% in Scotland in the year to May 2023. These are the highest annual changes in rental prices since January 2006 in England, since January 2010 in Wales, and since January 2012 in Scotland. Our recently published Private rental market summary statistics estimate the average monthly prices for private rents by local authority in England during the period April 2022 to March 2023. Read our latest bulletins on the UK House Price Index and the Index of Private Housing Rental Prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">3586395</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Energy prices not main concern for businesses for first time this year</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/economicactivityandsocialchangeintheukrealtimeindicators22june2023</link>
         <description>Energy prices not main concern for businesses for first time this year 22 June 2023 Falling demand for goods and services replaced energy prices as businesses’ main concern for the next month for the first time in 2023. As part of the Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS), businesses were asked about their main concern for the next month, July 2023. For the first time this year, energy prices were not the top reported concern. Falling demand for goods and services was reported as the main concern for the next month by 15% of businesses, up 12% from the previous month. Inflation of goods and services was reported as a main concern by 14% of businesses, down from 15% in the previous month. And energy prices were reported as a main concern by 12% of businesses, down by 15% from the previous month. The percentage of businesses that reported no concerns increased to 25% from 23% in the previous month. For the first time in 2023, energy prices were not the top reported concern for businesses when asked about their main concern for the next month Businesses’ main concern, businesses not permanently stopped trading, broken down by response option, weighted by count, UK, 1 June to 31 July 2023 Source: Business Insights and Conditions Survey (BICS) from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart For the first time in 2023, energy prices were not the top reported concern for businesses when asked about their main concern for the next month Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin Economic activity and social change in the UK, real-time indicators 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">6493298</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Shoppers buy more overall but cut back on food </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/retailsalesgreatbritainmay2023</link>
         <description>Shoppers buy more overall but cut back on food 23 June 2023 Shoppers across Britain bought more overall in May 2023, although retailers suggest a drop in the amount bought in food stores could be down to higher prices. Retail sales volumes across Britain are estimated to have risen by 0.3% in May 2023, following a rise of 0.5% in April 2023. Non-store retail sales volumes rose by 2.7% in May because of strong sales by online retailers selling outdoor-related goods and summer clothing. This was boosted by the warm weather in the second half of the month, according to feedback from retailers. However, shoppers bought less in food stores in May, with retailers suggesting that the increased cost of living and food prices continue to affect sales. There was also some evidence that the 0.5% fall in food store sales volumes over the month could be partly down to higher spending on takeaways and fast food. This may have been because of the extra bank holiday for the coronation of King Charles III on 8 May. People are spending more in food stores but buying less Volume and value sales, seasonally adjusted, Great Britain, May 2019 to May 2023 Source: Monthly Business Survey, Retail Sales Inquiry from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart People are spending more in food stores but buying less Image .csv .xls The survey period included the early bank holiday on 1 May, as well as the extra one for the coronation on 8 May. Read our full Retail sales, Great Britain: May 2023 bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">3982358</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Trade surplus in all UK nations in 2021</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/internationaltradeinuknationsregionsandcities2021</link>
         <description>Trade surplus in all UK nations in 2021 28 June 2023 There was a trade surplus in England, Northern Ireland, Scotland and Wales in 2021. This means that the value of goods and services exported from each nation was higher than the value of goods and services imported to each nation. England had a trade deficit until the onset of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, when the value of imports fell by more than the value of exports. Compared with before the pandemic (2018), exports increased in London, the North West, Scotland and the East of England, but fell in all other nations and English regions. Total exports in London, East of England, the North West and Scotland have returned to pre-pandemic levels Total trade exports by International Territorial Level (ITL) 1 region, UK, 2018 to 2021 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: Extra-regio includes parts of the national economic territory which cannot be attached directly to a single region including some offshore oil transactions and territorial enclaves. Download the data .xlsx In London, the rise was driven by exports of services, while increases in Scotland and the North East were driven by exports in goods. In the East of England, exports of both goods and services rose. The region is home to multiple medical, pharmaceutical and bioscientific research institutions, which may have boosted exports in response to the pandemic. Meanwhile, imports fell in all nations and English regions, with the largest falls in the South East and the West Midlands. Read our bulletin on International trade in UK nations, regions and cities: 2021 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">92078388</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Signs of improvement for businesses </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/businessinsightsandimpactontheukeconomy29june2023</link>
         <description>Signs of improvement for businesses 29 June 2023 While business conditions remain challenging, there have been signs of improvement, according to our latest Business Insights and Conditions Survey . More than two-thirds (68%) of businesses with 10 or more employees were able to get the goods they needed from within the UK in May 2023 without any form of disruption (up 3 percentage points from April 2023). A further 13% of businesses reported they had to change suppliers or find alternative solutions to get the goods they required. A similar proportion, 67% of businesses, reported some form of concern for their business for July 2023. The is the lowest percentage reported since late March 2022. Around 1 in 8 (13%) businesses reported that their employees' hourly wages had increased in May 2023 compared with April 2023: this was 22% for businesses with 10 or more employees. Read our latest Business Insights and impact on the UK economy bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">25872886</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around half of adults see rises in rent or mortgage payments </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain14to25june2023</link>
         <description>Around half of adults see rises in rent or mortgage payments 30 June 2023 Around half (47%) of adults in Great Britain have seen rises in their rent or mortgage payments in the past six months. This is according to our latest Public opinions and social trends survey , carried out between 14 and 25 June 2023. It is up from 30% of those asked in June 2022 who said that they had seen rises in the previous six months. There has been a corresponding rise among those saying that they are finding it difficult to afford their rent or mortgage payments. In the latest period, 43% said that they were finding these payments very or somewhat difficult, up from a quarter (25%) in June 2022. Among those surveyed in the latest period, 1 in 50 (2%) said that they were behind on their rent or mortgage payments. Read our latest Public opinions and social trends bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">96406868</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 09:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
