<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 09:15:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Re-opening economy contributed to 2022 inflation</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/theroleofdemandandsupplyfactorsincpiinflation2021to2022</link>
         <description>Re-opening economy contributed to 2022 inflation 9 March 2023 The disruption caused by the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic is one factor behind recent inflation pressures. Supply and demand shocks contributed to some items rising in price after the economy re-opened in 2021, as items that had not been available suddenly had high demand and, in some cases, reduced supply. Purchases on clothing and footwear, accommodation services, and air fares dropped sharply during coronavirus restrictions, followed by a sudden increase as the economy re-opened. There were also supply bottlenecks in production, such as getting microchips for new cars, which caused delays and increased demand for second-hand cars, pushing up their prices. Consumer price inflation (CPI) reached 40-year highs in late 2022. Food and energy price inflation accounted for half of the 9% increase in consumer prices in that year but core inflation – which excludes food and energy – also rose. Understanding what is behind inflation for a particular item is complex because multiple effects happened at once; 2022 included the impacts of Brexit, the coronavirus pandemic, and the recent energy price shock. Energy price increases may also have indirectly driven up consumer prices, because of higher production costs and overheads for service providers, such as accommodation and food businesses. Items affected by the re-opening of the economy explained around a sixth of inflation in 2022. Items affected by supply bottlenecks explained a tenth, showing that these factors contribute to the picture of high inflation and that food and energy are not the only drivers. Read the full article on the Role of Demand and Supply Factors in CPI Inflation 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">40754177</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 09:15:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.3% in January 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/balanceofpayments/bulletins/uktrade/latest</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.3% in January 2023 10 March 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have grown by 0.3% in January 2023, following a fall of 0.5% in December 2022. Looking at the broader picture, GDP remained flat in the three months to January 2023 compared with the three months to October 2022. Services grew by 0.5% in January 2023, after falling by 0.8% in December 2022. The largest contribution to the growth came from education, transport and storage, human health activities and arts, entertainment and recreation activities, all of which have rebounded after falls in December 2022. Production output fell by 0.3% in January 2023, after growth of 0.3% in December 2022. Manufacturing was the largest contributor to the production sector’s negative growth. Construction saw a 1.7% fall in January 2023, following flat growth in December 2022. The “Services” sector was the main contributor to monthly GDP growth in January 2023 Contributions to monthly GDP growth, January 2022 to January 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart The “Services” sector was the main contributor to monthly GDP growth in January 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP. 🠕 Back to the top Imports of goods fell in January 10 March 2023 The value of goods imported to the UK decreased by £4.9 billion (8.7%) in January 2023. Goods imports from the EU fell by £2.5 billion (8.8%) and those from non-EU countries fell by £2.4 billion (8.7%) in January 2023. The total value of fuel imported from non-EU countries decreased in January 2023 as gas prices fell following a sharp rise in December . However, when the effect of inflation is removed, fuel imports from non-EU countries increased in January 2023. The value of goods exported from the UK decreased by £0.6 billion (1.8%) in January 2023. Exports to EU countries fell by £0.7 billion, as exports of fuels, chemicals and material manufactures to EU countries each fell by £0.2 billion. Exports to non-EU countries increased by £0.1 billion. After removing the effect of inflation, total exports of goods to EU and non-EU countries fell by £0.1 billion (0.8%) and £0.2 billion (1.2%), respectively. Imports of goods from both EU and non-EU countries decreased in January 2023 EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted, January 2020 to January 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. Download the data .xlsx Read the full bulletin on UK trade: January 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">99860086</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 09:15:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around 3 in 10 adults experiencing essential food shortages</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain22februaryto5march2023</link>
         <description>Around 3 in 10 adults experiencing essential food shortages 10 March 2023 Around 3 in 10 (27%) adults in Great Britain experienced shortages of essential food items in the last two weeks, according to the latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey . This was based on data collected between 22 February to 5 March 2023, an increase from 18% in the previous period (8 to 19 February 2023). Around 3 in 10 (28%) experienced shortages of non-essential food items in the previous two weeks, up from 22% in the previous period. These are the largest increases, and highest percentages, of food shortage experiences since the data was first collected in September 2021. More than a third of adults (35%) reported they could not find a replacement when the items they needed were not available when food shopping in the past two weeks. Around half (51%) of adults reported less variety than normal when food shopping, which was the highest percentage since the data was first collected in October 2021. Read our latest Public Opinions and Social Trends article 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">79264750</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 09:15:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Real value of pay continues to fall</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peoplenotinwork/unemployment/bulletins/youngpeoplenotineducationemploymentortrainingneet/february2022</link>
         <description>Real value of pay continues to fall 14 March 2023 Total pay (including bonuses) for employees rose by 5.7% in November 2022 to January 2023, compared with the previous year. Regular pay growth (excluding bonuses) was 6.5%. However, after adjusting for rising prices, real terms pay fell by 3.2% year-on-year for total pay and by 2.4% for regular pay. The number of job vacancies in the UK fell by 51,000 in December 2022 to February 2023, compared with the previous quarter. This is the eighth consecutive period in which vacancies fell on the quarter, reflecting uncertainty across industries. Employers continue to cite economic pressures as a factor in holding back on recruitment. The employment rate increased on the quarter in November 2022 to January 2023, driven by part-time employees and self-employed workers. The economic inactivity rate (those not in work and not actively seeking work) decreased in the same period, while the unemployment rate remained similar. Read our latest Labour market overview, UK 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">44236916</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 09:15:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Cost of energy support schemes push borrowing to February record</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/articles/comparingcensus2021andlabourforcesurveyestimatesofthelabourmarketenglandandwales/13march2023</link>
         <description>Cost of energy support schemes push borrowing to February record 21 March 2023 In February 2023, the public sector spent more than it received in taxes and other income, requiring it to borrow £16.7 billion. This was £9.7 billion more borrowing than that in February 2022 and the highest February borrowing since monthly records began in 1993. While central government tax receipts grew by a steady £3.6 billion to £58.4 billion compared to February last year, it wasn’t enough to offset the cost of the combined energy schemes provided to households and businesses in February 2023, provisionally estimated at around £9.3 billion. The £16.7 billion borrowed in February 2023 combined with a reduction of £1.4 billion to our previously published financial year-to-January borrowing estimate brings the total borrowed in the financial year-to-February 2023 to £132.2 billion. This was £15.5 billion more borrowing than in the same period last year and the third highest financial year-to-February borrowing since monthly records began. Debt at the end of January was £2.5 trillion (£2,507.3 billion) or 99.2% of the UK’s annual gross domestic product (GDP). Read our latest bulletin on UK public sector finances 🠕 Back to the top People born in EU countries had highest proportion in employment 21 March 2023 Of adults aged 16 years and over in England and Wales on Census Day, 27.8 million (57.2%) were in employment on Census Day, 21 March 2021. Those born in EU countries had the highest percentage in employment, at 70.8%, 58.0% of those not born in the EU were employed, and those born in the UK had the lowest employment percentage, at 55.9%. This variation can be partially explained by the age profile of the different population groups. Migrant groups tend to be younger than the UK-born and younger people are more likely to be in employment than older people. This is shown when looking at the 16 to 64 years population (working age), where 71.2% of the UK-born were in employment compared with 78.2% of the EU-born in this age group. Professional occupations (such as doctors, nurses and teachers) was the most common occupational group for most migrant groups. Around a third (35.7%) of those born in Australia, New Zealand, Papua New Guinea and other Pacific Island nations (known as “Antarctica, Oceania and other”) were employed in this occupational group. When breaking down the economy into 21 industrial sectors, we see that country of birth groups have different distributions among the industries. Nearly a quarter (24.3%) of those working in the wholesale trade industry were born outside the UK. Two in five of those working in the manufacture of food products industry were born outside the UK (40.4%). Notes: Estimates from Census 2021 will differ to those collected on the Labour Force Survey because of a range of conceptual differences between the two sources. Our Comparing Census 2021 and Labour Force Survey estimates of the labour market, England and Wales article provides more detail. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">96267567</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 09:15:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Inflation rises but remains below October 2022 high</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/consumerpriceinflationukfebruary2023</link>
         <description>Inflation rises but remains below October 2022 high 22 March 2023 The rate of rising prices paid by consumers for goods and services rose to levels seen around 30 years ago in the 12 months to February 2023 but remains below the recent October 2022 peak. As measured by the Consumer Prices Index including owner occupiers’ housing costs (CPIH), the annual inflation rate rose to 9.2% in February 2023. This was up from 8.8% the previous month, but below a recent peak of 9.6% in October 2022. Since then, the annual inflation rate has fluctuated around 9.2%, a rate previously seen between September and December 1990. The reason for the rise in the annual inflation rate was a 1.0% rise in prices between January and February 2023, compared with 0.7% in the same period in 2022. Larger price rises in restaurants and hotels were some of the main reasons for the rise in the annual inflation rate. The annual inflation rate for restaurants and hotels was 12.1% in February 2023, up from 10.8% in January, and the highest rate since the constructed historical estimate of 12.1% in July 1991. Read our latest Consumer Price Inflation bulletin 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">42753382</guid>
         <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 09:15:34 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
