<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
   <channel>
      <title>UK Economy RSS</title>
      <link>https://github.com/tdrgregw/sandbox_actions/blob/main/misc/rss/test_rss.xml</link>
      <description>RSS feed capturing updates to the ONS UK Economy blog</description>
      <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
      <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
         <title>Record growth in prices food and drink manufacturers charged in January 2023 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/inflationandpriceindices/articles/recenttrendsinukfoodanddrinkproducerandconsumerprices/january2023</link>
         <description>Record growth in prices food and drink manufacturers charged in January 2023 8 March 2023 The prices UK food and drinks manufacturers charged for their products rose 17.1% in the year to January 2023, the highest annual rate on record. The prices manufacturers paid for their materials and fuels rose 19.8% in the year to January 2023. This is a slight decrease from a peak of 22.7% in the year to October 2022. This reflects rising prices of commodities worldwide, which have been affected by rising energy prices, supply chain disruption following the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, and the Russian invasion of Ukraine. Global prices of natural gas, food and fertilisers have all seen rapid increases during 2021 and 2022. The prices food and drink manufacturers charge to their customers are different to the prices consumers pay in shops and supermarkets. Consumer prices for food and non-alcoholic drinks rose 16.8% in the year to January 2023. The chart compares the increase in prices manufacturers charged for different food and drink items, and the prices retailers charged. There is a positive association between the food and drink prices charged by manufacturers and paid by consumers. Dairy products, such as milk and cheese, saw some of the largest price increases both among manufacturers and retailers. Dairy products saw some of the largest annual growth in both consumer and producer prices in January 2023 Annual percentage change in selected food and drink products CPIH and output PPI inflation, UK, January 2023 Source: Producer price inflation and Consumer price inflation from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart Dairy products saw some of the largest annual growth in both consumer and producer prices in January 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our full bulletin on Recent trends in UK food and drink producer and consumer prices 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">70230489</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>2.5 million working days lost to strikes in late 2022 </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/theimpactofstrikesintheukjune2022tofebruary2023</link>
         <description>2.5 million working days lost to strikes in late 2022 8 March 2023 An estimated 2.5 million working days were lost because of industrial disputes between June and December 2022. Of these, almost 2 million (79%) were among workers in transport, storage, information and communication. This includes both railway workers and postal workers, both of which went on strike in this period. The second highest number of days lost between June and December 2022 was in education (226,000), with 174,000 working days lost during strikes in November 2022. There is some evidence of strikes having an impact on output in the affected industries. Rail and postal workers held several strike days in December 2022; this month also saw the largest falls in output for these industries. In December 2022, rail transport output fell 7.0%, and postal and courier activities fell 10.5%. Read our full release on The impact of strikes in the UK: June 2022 to February 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">77001319</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Mortgage Calculator shows rising monthly repayment costs </title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/housing/articles/howaremonthlymortgagerepaymentschangingingreatbritain/2023-03-08</link>
         <description>Mortgage Calculator shows rising monthly repayment costs 8 March 2023 The monthly cost of a new mortgage rose by 61% in the year to December 2022 for the average semi-detached house in the UK. Our new personalised Mortgage Calculator , based on our House Price Index (HPI), shows how rising interest rates have caused monthly mortgage payments to rise sharply in England, Scotland and Wales. Because mortgage loans tend to be for large amounts of money, small increases in mortgage rates can have a big impact on the amount that households will have to pay back each month. Based on a 75% loan-to-value ratio, the average mortgage rate offered by lenders on a five-year fixed rate loan was 5.05% in December 2022, according to the Bank of England . That figure was up from 1.59% in December 2021. At a 75% loan-to-value rate, the average monthly mortgage repayment on a 25-year term for a semi-detached UK property was £1,262 in December 2022. This was a £481 (61%) increase on December 2021. Other property types have also experienced similar changes between December 2021 and December 2022. The monthly mortgage repayments on an average detached UK property rose by 60.7% to £2,041. The repayments on an average terraced UK property increased by 59.6% to £1,063 per month, while flats and maisonettes experienced a 54.6% rise to £1,028 per month. Read our What the ONS interactive map shows us about changing mortgage rates article . You can use our new Mortgage Calculator tool to see how mortgage repayment costs have changed around the country and enter your own inputs to personalise estimates for where you live. 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">86081112</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Re-opening economy contributed to 2022 inflation</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/theroleofdemandandsupplyfactorsincpiinflation2021to2022</link>
         <description>Re-opening economy contributed to 2022 inflation 9 March 2023 The disruption caused by the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic is one factor behind recent inflation pressures. Supply and demand shocks contributed to some items rising in price after the economy re-opened in 2021, as items that had not been available suddenly had high demand and, in some cases, reduced supply. Purchases on clothing and footwear, accommodation services, and air fares dropped sharply during coronavirus restrictions, followed by a sudden increase as the economy re-opened. There were also supply bottlenecks in production, such as getting microchips for new cars, which caused delays and increased demand for second-hand cars, pushing up their prices. Consumer price inflation (CPI) reached 40-year highs in late 2022. Food and energy price inflation accounted for half of the 9% increase in consumer prices in that year but core inflation – which excludes food and energy – also rose. Understanding what is behind inflation for a particular item is complex because multiple effects happened at once; 2022 included the impacts of Brexit, the coronavirus pandemic, and the recent energy price shock. Energy price increases may also have indirectly driven up consumer prices, because of higher production costs and overheads for service providers, such as accommodation and food businesses. Items affected by the re-opening of the economy explained around a sixth of inflation in 2022. Items affected by supply bottlenecks explained a tenth, showing that these factors contribute to the picture of high inflation and that food and energy are not the only drivers. Read the full article on the Role of Demand and Supply Factors in CPI Inflation 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">40754177</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.3% in January 2023</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/balanceofpayments/bulletins/uktrade/latest</link>
         <description>UK GDP estimated to have grown by 0.3% in January 2023 10 March 2023 Monthly real gross domestic product (GDP) is estimated to have grown by 0.3% in January 2023, following a fall of 0.5% in December 2022. Looking at the broader picture, GDP remained flat in the three months to January 2023 compared with the three months to October 2022. Services grew by 0.5% in January 2023, after falling by 0.8% in December 2022. The largest contribution to the growth came from education, transport and storage, human health activities and arts, entertainment and recreation activities, all of which have rebounded after falls in December 2022. Production output fell by 0.3% in January 2023, after growth of 0.3% in December 2022. Manufacturing was the largest contributor to the production sector’s negative growth. Construction saw a 1.7% fall in January 2023, following flat growth in December 2022. The “Services” sector was the main contributor to monthly GDP growth in January 2023 Contributions to monthly GDP growth, January 2022 to January 2023, UK Source: GDP monthly estimate from the Office for National Statistics Download this chart The “Services” sector was the main contributor to monthly GDP growth in January 2023 Image .csv .xls Read our latest bulletin on UK monthly GDP. 🠕 Back to the top Imports of goods fell in January 10 March 2023 The value of goods imported to the UK decreased by £4.9 billion (8.7%) in January 2023. Goods imports from the EU fell by £2.5 billion (8.8%) and those from non-EU countries fell by £2.4 billion (8.7%) in January 2023. The total value of fuel imported from non-EU countries decreased in January 2023 as gas prices fell following a sharp rise in December . However, when the effect of inflation is removed, fuel imports from non-EU countries increased in January 2023. The value of goods exported from the UK decreased by £0.6 billion (1.8%) in January 2023. Exports to EU countries fell by £0.7 billion, as exports of fuels, chemicals and material manufactures to EU countries each fell by £0.2 billion. Exports to non-EU countries increased by £0.1 billion. After removing the effect of inflation, total exports of goods to EU and non-EU countries fell by £0.1 billion (0.8%) and £0.2 billion (1.2%), respectively. Imports of goods from both EU and non-EU countries decreased in January 2023 EU and non-EU goods imports and exports, excluding precious metals, current prices, seasonally adjusted, January 2020 to January 2023 Embed code Embed this interactive Copy Notes: HM Revenue and Customs (HMRC) data collection changes following EU exit have affected statistics on UK trade in goods with the EU. Our Impact of trade in goods data collection changes on UK trade statistics articles provide more detail. Download the data .xlsx Read the full bulletin on UK trade: January 2023 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">99860086</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Around 3 in 10 adults experiencing essential food shortages</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/releases/publicopinionsandsocialtrendsgreatbritain22februaryto5march2023</link>
         <description>Around 3 in 10 adults experiencing essential food shortages 10 March 2023 Around 3 in 10 (27%) adults in Great Britain experienced shortages of essential food items in the last two weeks, according to the latest Opinions and Lifestyle Survey . This was based on data collected between 22 February to 5 March 2023, an increase from 18% in the previous period (8 to 19 February 2023). Around 3 in 10 (28%) experienced shortages of non-essential food items in the previous two weeks, up from 22% in the previous period. These are the largest increases, and highest percentages, of food shortage experiences since the data was first collected in September 2021. More than a third of adults (35%) reported they could not find a replacement when the items they needed were not available when food shopping in the past two weeks. Around half (51%) of adults reported less variety than normal when food shopping, which was the highest percentage since the data was first collected in October 2021. Read our latest Public Opinions and Social Trends article 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">79264750</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Real value of pay continues to fall</title>
         <link>https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peoplenotinwork/unemployment/bulletins/youngpeoplenotineducationemploymentortrainingneet/february2022</link>
         <description>Real value of pay continues to fall 14 March 2023 Total pay (including bonuses) for employees rose by 5.7% in November 2022 to January 2023, compared with the previous year. Regular pay growth (excluding bonuses) was 6.5%. However, after adjusting for rising prices, real terms pay fell by 3.2% year-on-year for total pay and by 2.4% for regular pay. The number of job vacancies in the UK fell by 51,000 in December 2022 to February 2023, compared with the previous quarter. This is the eighth consecutive period in which vacancies fell on the quarter, reflecting uncertainty across industries. Employers continue to cite economic pressures as a factor in holding back on recruitment. The employment rate increased on the quarter in November 2022 to January 2023, driven by part-time employees and self-employed workers. The economic inactivity rate (those not in work and not actively seeking work) decreased in the same period, while the unemployment rate remained similar. Read our latest Labour market overview, UK 🠕 Back to the top</description>
         <author>Gregory.Weegenaar@tdrcapital.com (Gregory Weegenaar)</author>
         <guid isPermaLink="false">44236916</guid>
         <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 09:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      </item>
   </channel>
</rss>
